{"test_questions": [[{"question": "To prevent a DC return between source and load, it is necessary to use", "opta": "resistor between source and load", "optb": "inductor between source and load", "optc": "capacitor between source and load", "optd": "either (a) or (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Capacitor offers infinite impedance to DC."}, {"question": "For a base current of 10 \u03bcA, what is the value of collector current in common emitter if \u03b2dc = 100", "opta": "10 \u03bcA", "optb": "100 \u03bcA", "optc": "1 mA", "optd": "10 mA", "ans": "C", "explanation": "IC = 10 x 100 \u03bcA = 1 mA."}, {"question": "Which of the following oscillators is suitable for frequencies in the range of mega hertz?", "opta": "RC phase shift", "optb": "Wien bridge", "optc": "Hartley", "optd": "Both (a) and (c)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Only LC oscillators are suitable for MHz range."}, {"question": "If the input to the ideal comparator shown in the figure is a sinusoidal signal of 8 V (peak to peak) without any DC component, then the output of the comparator has a duty cycle of", "opta": "1/2", "optb": "1/3", "optc": "1/6", "optd": "1/12", "ans": "B", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "A half wave diode circuit using ideal diode has an input voltage 20 sin \u03c9t volts. Then average and rms values of output voltage are", "opta": "and 10 V", "optb": "and 10 V", "optc": "and 5 V", "optd": "and 5 V", "ans": "B", "explanation": "and VC = 0.5 x 20 = 10 V."}, {"question": "An RC coupled amplifier has an open loop gain of 200 and a lower cutoff frequency of 50 Hz. If negative feedback with \u03b2 = 0.1 is used, the lower cut off frequency will be", "opta": "about 50 Hz", "optb": "about 5 Hz", "optc": "about 2.38 Hz", "optd": "about 70.5 Hz", "ans": "C", "explanation": "New lower cutoff frequency =  ."}, {"question": "In figure v1 = 8 V and v2 = 4 V. Which diode will conduct?", "opta": "D2 only", "optb": "D1 only", "optc": "Both D1 and D2", "optd": "Neither D1 nor D2", "ans": "B", "explanation": "D1 will conduct and the output voltage will be about 7 V. Therefore D2 will be reverse biased and will not conduct."}, {"question": "The load impedance ZL of a CE amplifier has R and L in series. The phase difference between output and input will be", "opta": "180\u00b0", "optb": "0", "optc": "more than 90\u00b0 but less than 180\u00b0", "optd": "more than 180\u00b0 but less than 270\u00b0", "ans": "D", "explanation": "It is 180\u00b0 for purely resistive load and between 180\u00b0 and 270\u00b0 for R-L load."}, {"question": "Gain of the amplifier is 'A'. Then the I/P impedance and O/P impedance of the closed loop amplifier shown below would be", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "By using Miller theorem circuit can be redrawn as\n\n."}, {"question": "If an amplifier with gain of - 1000 and feedback factor \u03b2 = - 0.1 had a gain change of 20% due to temperature, the change in gain of the feedback amplifier would be", "opta": "10%", "optb": "5%", "optc": "0.2%", "optd": "0.01%", "ans": "C", "explanation": "As we know, Gain with feedback\n\n\nA = - 1000, \u03b2 = -0.1 ."}, {"question": "In figure The minimum and maximum load currents are", "opta": "0 and 60 mA", "optb": "0 and 120 mA", "optc": "10 mA and 60 mA", "optd": "10 mA and 120 mA", "ans": "B", "explanation": "When RL = \u221e, IL = 0, \nWhen RL = 100 &ohm;,  or 120 mA."}, {"question": "In figure, VEB = 0.6 V, \u03b2 = 99. Then VC and IC are", "opta": "9.3 V and 1.98 mA respectively", "optb": "4.6 V and 1.98 mA respectively", "optc": "9.3 V and 0.02 mA respectively", "optd": "4.6 V and 0.02 mA respectively", "ans": "A", "explanation": "VC = 20 - 1.98 x 10-3 x 5.4 x 103  9.3 V."}, {"question": "The input impedance of op-amp circuit of figure is", "opta": "120 k ohm", "optb": "110 k ohm", "optc": "infinity", "optd": "10 k ohm", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Due to the presence of virtual ground at input, the resistance in the series path of input of inverting amplifier is input impedance."}, {"question": "In a BJT circuit a pnp transistor is replaced by npn transistor. To analyse the new circuit", "opta": "all calculations done earlier have to be repeated", "optb": "replace all calculated voltages by reverse values", "optc": "replace all calculated currents by reverse values", "optd": "replace all calculated voltages and currents by reverse values", "ans": "D", "explanation": "All voltages and currents have reverse polarity."}, {"question": "To protect the diodes in a rectifier and capacitor input filter circuit it is necessary to use", "opta": "surge resistor", "optb": "surge inductor", "optc": "surge capacitor", "optd": "both (a) and (b)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Resistor reduces surge current."}, {"question": "The output V0 in figure is", "opta": "-100 V", "optb": "-100 mV", "optc": "10 V", "optd": "10 mV", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Input to non-inverting op-amp is -10 x 10-6 x 103 = -10 mV.\nTherefore output =  = -100 mV."}, {"question": "In a CE amplifier the input impedance is equal to the ratio of", "opta": "ac base voltage to ac base current", "optb": "ac base voltage to ac emitter current", "optc": "ac emitter voltage to ac collector current", "optd": "ac collector voltage to ac collector current", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Input is applied to base with emitter grounded. The input impedance is the ratio of ac base voltage to ac base current."}, {"question": "For a system to work, as oscillator the total phase shift of the loop gain must be equal to", "opta": "90\u00b0", "optb": "45\u00b0", "optc": "270\u00b0", "optd": "360\u00b0", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Gain of system with + ve feedback =  for oscillation \nbut V0 \u2260 0\nso, that 1 - AB = 0  AB = 1 \u22200\u00b0 or 360\u00b0."}, {"question": "An amplifier has a large ac input signal. The clipping occurs on both the peaks. The output voltage will be nearly a", "opta": "sine wave", "optb": "square wave", "optc": "triangular wave", "optd": "(a) or (c)", "ans": "B", "explanation": "When a sinusoidal voltage is clipped on both sides it resembles a square wave."}, {"question": "The transistor of following figure in Si diode with a base current of 40 \u03bcA and ICBO = 0, if VBB = 6V, RE = 2 k&ohm; and \u03b2 = 90, IBQ = 20 \u03bcA then RB =", "opta": "200 k&ohm;", "optb": "265 k&ohm;", "optc": "150 k&ohm;", "optd": "100 k&ohm;", "ans": "B", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "In the amplifier circuit of figure hfe = 100 and hie = 1000 &ohm;. The voltage gain of amplifier is about", "opta": "0.33", "optb": "0.5", "optc": "0.66", "optd": "1", "ans": "D", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "The efficiency of a full wave rectifier using centre tapped transformer is twice that in full wave bridge rectifier.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Efficiency of full wave rectifier with centre tapped transformer is slightly higher than that of bridge rectifier."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  CE amplifier is the most widely used BJT amplifierReason (R):  CE amplifier has zero phase difference between input and output", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation for A", "optb": "Both A and R are correct but R is not correct explanation for A", "optc": "A is correct R is wrong", "optd": "A is wrong R is correct", "ans": "C", "explanation": "There is 180\u00b0 phase difference between input and output."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  For large signal variations an amplifier circuit has to be analysed graphicallyReason (R):  The output characteristics of a transistor is nonlinear.", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation for A", "optb": "Both A and R are correct but R is not correct explanation for A", "optc": "A is correct R is wrong", "optd": "A is wrong R is correct", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since the characteristics is non-linear, graphical analysis is needed."}, {"question": "Negative feedback reduces noise originating at the amplifier input.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "It has no effect on noise originating at amplifier input."}, {"question": "Maximum efficiency of class B power amplifier is 50%.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Maximum efficiency for class B-operation can be 78.5% ."}, {"question": "In figure what is the base current if VBE = 0.7 V", "opta": "10 mA", "optb": "9.3 mA", "optc": "10 \u03bcA", "optd": "9.3 \u03bcA", "ans": "D", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "In figure ID = 4 mA. Then VS =", "opta": "20 V", "optb": "4.4 V", "optc": "0.4 V", "optd": "0.44 V", "ans": "B", "explanation": "VS = ISRS = 4 x 10-3 x 1.1 x 103 = 4.4 V."}, {"question": "The self bias provides", "opta": "stable Q point", "optb": "large voltage gain", "optc": "high input impedance", "optd": "high base current", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Stable Q point is the advantage of self bias circuit."}, {"question": "In figure what is value of IC if \u03b2dc = 100. Neglect VBE", "opta": "5 mA", "optb": "5 \u03bcA", "optc": "10 mA", "optd": "10 \u03bcA", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Since IB = 100 \u03bcA, IC = \u03b2IB = 10 mA."}, {"question": "In figure the saturation collector current is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Since IE  IC, ."}, {"question": "Consider the following statements : A clamper circuit adds or subtracts a dc voltage to a waveformdoes not change the waveformamplifiers the waveform Which are correct?", "opta": "1, 2", "optb": "1, 3", "optc": "1, 2, 3", "optd": "2, 3", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Clamper does not amplify the waveform. Hence 1 and 2 are correct."}, {"question": "In figure v1 = 8 V and v2 = 8 V. Which diode will conduct?", "opta": "D1 only", "optb": "D2 only", "optc": "Both D1 and D2", "optd": "Neither D1 nor D2", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Both D1 and D2 are forward biased."}, {"question": "A forward voltage of 9 V is applied to a diode in series with a 1 k&ohm; load resistor. The voltage across load resistor is zero. It indicates that", "opta": "diode is short circuited", "optb": "diode is open circuited", "optc": "resistor is open circuited", "optd": "diode is either short circuited or open circuited", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since load voltage is zero, the current is zero and diode is open-circuited. If load was open-circuited, load voltage would be about 9 V."}, {"question": "Which power amplifier can deliver maximum load power?", "opta": "Class A", "optb": "Class AB", "optc": "Class B", "optd": "Class C", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Since efficiency of class C operation is high, maximum load power is delivered."}, {"question": "A CB amplifier has re = 6 &ohm;, RL = 600 &ohm; and a = 0.98. The voltage gain is", "opta": "100", "optb": "600 x 0.98", "optc": "98", "optd": "6", "ans": "C", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "A bridge rectifier circuit has input of 50 Hz frequency. The load resistance is RL and filter capacitance is C. For good output wave shape, the time constant RLC should be at least equal to", "opta": "10 ms", "optb": "20 ms", "optc": "50 ms", "optd": "100 ms", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Time constant RLC must be about 5 x 20 ms."}, {"question": "Si transistor of following figure has a = 0.9 and ICE= 0, VEE = 5 V and VCC = 13 V, then RE will be if IEQ = 1 mA", "opta": "3 k&ohm;", "optb": "4 k&ohm;", "optc": "5 k&ohm;", "optd": "4.3 k&ohm;", "ans": "D", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "In class C operation of an amplifier circuit, the collector current exists for", "opta": "360\u00b0 of input wave", "optb": "180\u00b0 of input wave", "optc": "more than 180\u00b0 of input wave", "optd": "less than 180\u00b0 of input wave", "ans": "D", "explanation": "In class C operation output is in the form of short duration pulses."}, {"question": "The 'h' parameters of the circuit shown in the figure are hib = 25 &ohm;, hfb = 0.999 and hob = 10-6&ohm; The Voltage gain is", "opta": "0.99", "optb": "1.98", "optc": "2.0", "optd": "4", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Zi = 25 + 10-6 x 0.99 x 104  25\n."}, {"question": "An exponential amplifier has diode in feedback path.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "It has resistance in feedback path."}, {"question": "DC amplifiers have a tendency to be unstable.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Due to drift."}, {"question": "A half wave diode rectifier has a capacitance input filter. If input voltage is Vm sin \u03c9t, PIV is", "opta": "Vm", "optb": "2 Vm", "optc": "3 Vm", "optd": "4 Vm", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Because capacitor charge is retained."}, {"question": "An amplifier with loop gain A\u03b2 will be more stable for value of A\u03b2 as", "opta": "0.95", "optb": "0.7", "optc": "1.2", "optd": "1.5", "ans": "B", "explanation": "A feedback amplifier is stable if loop gain is less than unity. More less, more stable, hence \u03b2 will be more stable."}, {"question": "Study the circuit of figure and examine the following statements It is an active low pass finer.It is a second order filter.The change in gain is 40 dB/decade. Which of the above statements are correct?", "opta": "1, 2 and 3", "optb": "1 and 2", "optc": "1 and 3", "optd": "2 and 3", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The circuit is a second order active low pass filter for which gain is 40 dB/decade."}, {"question": "In a circuit of figure, Vs = 10 cos(\u03c9t) power drawn by the 2&ohm; resistor is 4 watts. The power factor is", "opta": "0.3", "optb": "0.4", "optc": "0.6", "optd": "none", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Vs = 10 cos \u03c9t, \nLet I be the current, then P = I2 R \nI is the rms current.\n Prms =  I2 R  4  I2 = 4  I = 2A.\nTotal power drawn =  Vm Im cos \u03b8\n  10 x 2 cos \u03b8 = 10 cos \u03b8\nTotal power cannot be determine until value of R = 12 &ohm; is given."}, {"question": "The quiescent collector current IC, and collector to emitter voltage VCE in a CE connection are the values when", "opta": "ac signal is zero", "optb": "ac signal is low", "optc": "ac signal is negative", "optd": "either (a) or (b)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Quiescent-operation means operation when ac signal is not applied."}, {"question": "In the op-amp circuit of figure, V0 =", "opta": "Vi", "optb": "3 Vi", "optc": "5 Vi", "optd": "0.5 Vi", "ans": "C", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "Figure shows the self bias circuit for CE amplifier and its equivalent circuit. VBB and RB respectively are", "opta": "10 V and 4 k ohm", "optb": "5 V and 4 k ohm", "optc": "2 V and 4 k ohm", "optd": "2 V and 10 k ohm", "ans": "C", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "For the system in the given figure the characteristic equation is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "K(s + 1)(s + 3) = 0", "optd": "s(s + 2) = 0", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Transfer function = . \nHence characteristic equation is ."}, {"question": "Mechanical impedance is the ratio of", "opta": "rms force to rms velocity", "optb": "rms force to rms displacement", "optc": "rms velocity to rms displacement", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "In force voltage analogy force is analogous to voltage and velocity to current. Just as , force/velocity = mechanical impedance."}, {"question": "For the system in the given figure. The transfer function C(s)/R(s) is", "opta": "G1 + G2 + 1", "optb": "G1 G2 + 1", "optc": "G1 G2 + G2 + 1", "optd": "G1 G2 + G1 + 1", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Transfer function = (G1 + 1) G2 + 1 = G1 G2 + G2 + 1."}, {"question": "Whether a linear system is stable or unstable that it", "opta": "is a property of the system only", "optb": "depends on the input function only", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "either (a) or (b)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Stability is a property of the system only."}, {"question": "For the system of the given figure the transfer function =", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": ", E0(s) = [I(s)][Z2(s)] or ."}, {"question": "In the given figure shows pole-zero plot. If steady state gain is 2 the transfer function G(s) is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The zero at - 1 gives the term (s + 1) in the numerator. \nThe poles at (- 2 + j1) and (- 2 - j1) give (s2 + 4s + 5) term is the denominator. Gain is 2."}, {"question": "If a system is to follow arbitrary inputs accurately the bandwidth should be", "opta": "large", "optb": "small", "optc": "very small", "optd": "neither small nor large", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Arbitrary inputs require large bandwidth."}, {"question": "For the system of the given figure, the damping ratio of closed loop poles is", "opta": "1.5", "optb": "1", "optc": "0.5", "optd": "0.25", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The standard form of characteristic equation is . \nTherefore ."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  Potentiometers can not be used as error detectors in position control systems.Reason (R): The resolution of a potentiometer places an upper limit on its accuracy", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are correct but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is correct but R is wrong", "optd": "R is correct but A is wrong", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Potentiometers are used as error detectors."}, {"question": "For a first order system having transfer function , the unit impulse response is", "opta": "e-t/T", "optb": "T e-t/T", "optc": "", "optd": "T2 e-t/T", "ans": "C", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "For the given figure C(s)/R(s)", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "A stepper motor is", "opta": "a two phase induction motor", "optb": "is a kind of rotating amplifier", "optc": "is an electromagnetic transducer used to convert an angular position of shaft into electrical signal", "optd": "is an electromechanical device which actuates a train of step angular movements in response to a train of input pulses on one to one basis", "ans": "D", "explanation": "When input pulses are applied, the motor moves in steps."}, {"question": "In a two phase ac servomotor rotor resistance is R and rotor reactance is X. The speed curve will be linear if", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "X2 = R", "ans": "A", "explanation": "In a two phase servomotor  \u2220 < 1 so that torque speed curve is almost linear."}, {"question": "In the given figure, the input frequency is such that R = XC. Then", "opta": "v0 lags vi by 45\u00b0", "optb": "v0 lags vi by 90\u00b0", "optc": "v0 leads vi by 45\u00b0", "optd": "v0 leads vi by 90\u00b0", "ans": "A", "explanation": "R = XC, voltage drops across R and XC are equal and at 90\u00b0 with respect by each other. V0 lags Vi by 45\u00b0."}, {"question": "From the noise point of view, bandwidth should", "opta": "be large", "optb": "not be too large", "optc": "should be as large as possible", "optd": "should be infinite", "ans": "B", "explanation": "If noise is to be eliminated, bandwidth cannot be large."}, {"question": "First column elements of Routh's tabulation are 3, 5, , 2. It means that there", "opta": "is one root in left half s plane", "optb": "are two roots in left half s plane", "optc": "are two roots in right half s plane", "optd": "is one root in right half s plane", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Since there are two sign changes in the first column, hence two roots in right half plane."}, {"question": "When a unit step voltage drives a lag network the output", "opta": "remains constant at unit step value", "optb": "increases exponentially from zero to final value", "optc": "decreases exponentially from 1 to 0", "optd": "either (b) of (c) depending on values of R and C", "ans": "B", "explanation": "At t = 0 the capacitor behaves as a short-circuit and output voltage is 0. At t = \u221e capacitor behaves as an open-circuit and V0 = Vi."}, {"question": "For the given figure C(s)/R(s)", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "For the circuit in the given figure,", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "A system has its two poles on the negative real axis and one pair of poles lies on j\u03c9 axis. The system is", "opta": "stable", "optb": "unstable", "optc": "limitedly stable", "optd": "either (a) or (c)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Poles on j x-axis lead to oscillations."}, {"question": "In the given figure the input frequency is such that R << Xc, then", "opta": "v0 lags vi by 90\u00b0", "optb": "v0 leads vi by 90\u00b0", "optc": "v0 and vi are in phase", "optd": "either (b) or (c)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Voltage across capacitor lags by 90\u00b0."}, {"question": "In the given figure, of potentiometer V0 = Vi (R0/Ri) only when", "opta": "RL = 0", "optb": "RL = \u221e", "optc": "RL is neither low nor high", "optd": "RL is low but not zero", "ans": "B", "explanation": "If RL is not infinite, the voltage ratio of potentiometer depends on the value of RL. This is called loading effect."}, {"question": "A unity feedback system has open loop transfer function The closed loop transfer function is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "Bellows converts", "opta": "pressure difference into displacement", "optb": "pressure difference into voltage", "optc": "displacement into pressure difference", "optd": "either (a) or (c)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "To measure pressure, it is convenient to convert pressure into displacement and then use a displacement transducer."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  The steady state response, of a stable, linear, time invariant system, to sinusoidal input depends on initial conditions. Reason (R): Frequency response, in steady state, is obtained by replacing s in the transfer function by j\u03c9", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are correct but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is correct but R is wrong", "optd": "R is correct but A is wrong", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Steady state response does not depend on initial conditions."}, {"question": "Consider the systems with following open loop transfer functions   If unity feedback is used, the increasing order of time taken for unit step response to settle is", "opta": "1, 2, 3", "optb": "3, 1, 2", "optc": "2, 3, 1", "optd": "3, 2, 1", "ans": "C", "explanation": ". For the three systems the values of \u03be\u03c9n are 1.8, 2.5 and 2 respectively. \nHence values of T are 0.55, 0.4 and 0.5 respectively."}, {"question": "The phase margin and damping ratio have no relation.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "They are related."}, {"question": "For the transport lag G(j\u03c9) = e-j\u03c9T, the magnitude is always equal to", "opta": "0", "optb": "1", "optc": "10", "optd": "0.5", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Magnitude is 1."}, {"question": "The log magnitude curve for a constant gain K is a", "opta": "horizontal straight line", "optb": "horizontal straight line of magnitude 20 log K decibels", "optc": "an inclined line having slope K", "optd": "an inclined line having slope -K", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The factor K in the numerator of G(j\u03c9) gives is straight line at 20 log10 K in Bode plot."}, {"question": "The compensator of the given figure is a", "opta": "lag compensator", "optb": "lead compensator", "optc": "lag-lead compensator", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Obtain transfer function."}, {"question": "If error voltage is e(t), integral square error =", "opta": "e2(t) dt", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Error is squared and integrated."}, {"question": "A lag compensator is essentially a", "opta": "low pass filter", "optb": "high pass filter", "optc": "band pass filter", "optd": "either (a) or (b)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "See transfer function in the equation , \u03b2 > 1 \nwhere t1 = R1C1, t2 = R2C2 and t > 1."}, {"question": "Stepper motors find applications in", "opta": "X-Y plotters", "optb": "numerically controlled machining equipment", "optc": "printers", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Stepper motors are used in all these applications."}, {"question": "For type 2 system, the magnitude and phase angle of the term (j\u03c9)2 in the denominator, at \u03c9 = 0, are respectively", "opta": "0 and - 90\u00b0", "optb": "0 and + 90\u00b0", "optc": "infinity and - 180\u00b0", "optd": "infinity and + 180\u00b0", "ans": "C", "explanation": "If \u03c9 = 0,  has a magnitude of infinity and phase angle -180\u00b0."}, {"question": "In an integral controller", "opta": "the output is proportional to input", "optb": "the rate of change of output is proportional to input", "optc": "the output is proportional to rate of change of input", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Output is proportional to integral of input or rate of change of output is proportional to input."}, {"question": "In Bode diagram (log magnitude plot) the factor  in the transfer function gives a line having slope", "opta": "-20 dB per octave", "optb": "-10 dB per octave", "optc": "-6 dB per octave", "optd": "-2 dB per octave", "ans": "C", "explanation": "For  term the slope is -20 dB/decade or -6 dB/octave because - 20 log 2 = -6 dB."}, {"question": "In the given figure the input is x(t) = A sin \u03c9t. The steady state output y(t) =", "opta": "A sin (\u03c9t + \u03c6) where \u03c6 = tan-1 |G(j\u03c9)|", "optb": "|G(j\u03c9)| A sin [\u03c9t + \u2220G(j\u03c9)]", "optc": "|G(j\u03c9)| A sin [2\u03c9t + \u2220G(j\u03c9)]", "optd": "A G(j\u03c9) sin [\u03c9t + \u2220G(j\u03c9)]", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The magnitudes A and G(j\u03c9) are multiplied and phase angles are added."}, {"question": "In the given figure x6 =", "opta": "de(ax1 + bx2 + cx3)", "optb": "(a + b + c) (x1 + x2 + x3) (d + e)", "optc": "(ax1 + bx2 + cx3) (d + e)", "optd": "a b c d e (x1 + x2 + x3)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The input x1 is multiplied by a, x2, by b and x3 by c. The sum total is multiplied by d and e."}, {"question": "A negative feedback system has . The closed loop system is stable for", "opta": "K > 20", "optb": "15 < K < 19", "optc": "8 \u2264 K \u2264 14", "optd": "K < 6", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Find characteristic equation."}, {"question": "For the given figure,", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "For the inner loop, transfer function =  \nThen ."}, {"question": "For the control system in the given figure, the value of K for critical damping is", "opta": "1", "optb": "5.125", "optc": "6.831", "optd": "10", "ans": "B", "explanation": "since \u03b6 = 1, \u03c9n = 3.5 Hence 2 + 2k = 3.52 = 12.25 or K = 5.125 ."}, {"question": "Bode magnitude plot is drawn between", "opta": "magnitude of network function and \u03c9", "optb": "dB magnitude and log \u03c9", "optc": "dB magnitude and \u03c9", "optd": "loge (magnitude) and log \u03c9", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Frequency is plotted on log scale and magnitude is taken in dB."}, {"question": "For the system in the given figure,", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "For inner loop we have transfer function =  \nThen  = ."}, {"question": "In the given figure, if R = XC, voltage gain is", "opta": "0 dB", "optb": "3 dB", "optc": "-3 dB", "optd": "20 dB", "ans": "C", "explanation": "If R = XC, V0 = 0.5 Vi Hence gain is -3 dB."}, {"question": "For the circuit in the given figure, V2(s)/V1(s) =", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "The system in the given figure, has", "opta": "good gain and phase margin", "optb": "poor gain and phase margin", "optc": "good gain margin but poor phase margin", "optd": "poor gain margin but good phase margin", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Since the plot is very near (-1 + j0) point, gain margin is poor."}, {"question": "The given figure shows a pole zero diagram. The transfer function G(j1) is", "opta": "0.5 \u22200", "optb": "2.7 \u2220- 31\u00b0", "optc": "2 \u222045\u00b0", "optd": "2 \u2220- 67.4\u00b0", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Join j1 point with the zero and poles. Find magnitude and phase angles of all these lines."}, {"question": "For very low frequencies, v0/vi in the given figure equals", "opta": "1", "optb": "0", "optc": "\u221e", "optd": "0.5", "ans": "A", "explanation": "For low frequencies Xc is very high as compared to R. Hence ."}, {"question": "In a minimum phase system", "opta": "all poles lie in the left half plane", "optb": "all zeros lie in the left half plane", "optc": "all poles lie in the right half plane", "optd": "all except one pole or zero lie in the left half plane", "ans": "B", "explanation": "For stability poles must be in left half plane. Zeros in left half plane lead to minimum phase shift."}, {"question": "For the system of the given figure the transfer function is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Transfer function = ."}, {"question": "A cordless telephone using separate frequencies for transmission in base and portable units is known as", "opta": "duplex arrangement", "optb": "half duplex arrangement", "optc": "either (a) or (b)", "optd": "neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Separate frequencies for transmission from base and portable units allows two way transmission and is called duplex arrangement."}, {"question": "For attenuation of high frequencies we should use", "opta": "shunt capacitance", "optb": "series capacitance", "optc": "inductance", "optd": "resistance", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since Xc for high frequencies is low, the high frequencies are shunted to ground and are not transmitted."}, {"question": "A modem is classified as low speed if data rate handled is", "opta": "upto 100 bps", "optb": "upto 250 bps", "optc": "upto 400 bps", "optd": "upto 600 bps", "ans": "D", "explanation": "When data rate in bits per second is upto 600, modem is low speed."}, {"question": "VSB modulation is preferred in TV because", "opta": "it reduces the bandwidth requirement to half", "optb": "it avoids phase distortion at low frequencies", "optc": "it results in better reception", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "VSB (vestigial side band) transmission transmits one side band fully and the other side band partially thus, reducing the bandwidth requirement."}, {"question": "A woofer should be fed from the input through a", "opta": "low pass filter", "optb": "high pass filter", "optc": "band pass filter", "optd": "band stop filter", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Woofer is a low frequency loud speaker covering the range 16 Hz to 500 Hz."}, {"question": "The colour subcarrier and sidebands produced by its modulation with the chrominance signals are accommodated in the standard channel width by the process of", "opta": "frequency adjustment", "optb": "frequency interleaving", "optc": "frequency changing", "optd": "frequency amalgamation", "ans": "B", "explanation": "In frequency interleaving the space between bundles is used for colour signal."}, {"question": "In FM signal with a modulation index mf is passed through a frequency tripler. The wave in the output of the tripler will have a modulation index of", "opta": "mf", "optb": "3mf", "optc": "mf/3", "optd": "mf/9", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Frequency multiplier increase the deviation, \n."}, {"question": "In colour TV receiver, varactor diode is used for", "opta": "detection", "optb": "rectification", "optc": "tuning", "optd": "both (a) and (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "In varactor diode the applied reverse bias controls the width and therefore capacitance of depletion layer. \nThis capacitance is used for tuning."}, {"question": "The number of noise sources in a BJT are", "opta": "3", "optb": "2", "optc": "1", "optd": "4", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Shot noise, partition noise and thermal noise."}, {"question": "Energy content of atmospheric noise", "opta": "does not depend on frequency", "optb": "decreases as frequency is increased", "optc": "increases as frequency is increased", "optd": "either (a) or (c) depending on the temperature", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Atmospheric noise decreases as frequency is increased."}, {"question": "A 400 W carrier is amplitude modulated with m = 0.75. The total power in AM is", "opta": "400 W", "optb": "512 W", "optc": "588 W", "optd": "650 W", "ans": "B", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "c(t) and m(t) are used to generate an FM signal. If the peak frequency deviation of the generated FM signal is three times the transmission bandwidth of the AM signal, then the coefficient of the term cos [2p(1008 x 103t)] in the FM signal (in terms of the Bessel Coefficients) is", "opta": "5 J4(3)", "optb": "J8(3)", "optc": "J8(4)", "optd": "5 J4(6)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "As, we known FM, s(t)\n\n Frequency deviation = 3 . (AM Bandwidth) = 6 fm\n\nand \u03b2= 6 is given in (d) only.\n\u03c9c + n \u03c9m = (1008 x 103)2p \n 2p x 106 + n. 4p x 103 = (1008 x 103).2p \n n = 4\nSo, \u03b2 = 6, n = 4 hence answer is 5j4(6)."}, {"question": "Non-coherently detection is not possible for", "opta": "PSK", "optb": "ASK", "optc": "FSK", "optd": "both (a) and (c)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Tracking of extra terrestrial objects requires", "opta": "high transmitting power", "optb": "very sensitive receiver", "optc": "fully steerable antenna", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "All the three are required."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  Free space does not interfere with normal radiation and propagation of radio wavesReason (R):  Free space has no magnetic or gravitational fields.", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are correct but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is correct but R is wrong", "optd": "A is wrong but R is correct", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since free space does not have magnetic and other fields, waves can propagate without any interference."}, {"question": "In radar systems PRF stands for", "opta": "Power Return Factor", "optb": "Pulse Return Factor", "optc": "Pulse Repetition Frequency", "optd": "Pulse Response Factor", "ans": "C", "explanation": "PRF in radar systems means pulse repetition frequency."}, {"question": "Which of the following cannot be the Fourier series expansion of a periodic signal?", "opta": "x(t) = 2 cos t + 3 cos 3t", "optb": "x(t) = 2 cos pt + 7 cos t", "optc": "x(t) = cos t + 0.5", "optd": "x(t) = 2 cos 1.5pt + sin 3.5 pt", "ans": "C", "explanation": "x(t) = cos t + 0.5\nnot satisfies the Dirichlet condition. \nThe integration of constant term is \u221e."}, {"question": "Which of the following is the indirect way of FM generation?", "opta": "Reactance bipolar transistor modulator", "optb": "Armstrong modulator", "optc": "Varactor diode modulator", "optd": "Reactance FM modulator", "ans": "B", "explanation": "It generates FM through phase modulation."}, {"question": "A telephone exchange has 9000 subscribers. If the number of calls originating at peak time is 10, 000 in one hour, the calling rate is", "opta": "0.9", "optb": "10/9", "optc": "0.81", "optd": "0.1", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Calling rate is the number of calls per subscriber."}, {"question": "If C is capacity of noisy channel, (bits/s), \u03b4f is bandwidth Hz and S/N is signal to noise ratio, then", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "This is Shannon-Hartley theorem."}, {"question": "As the frequency increases, the absorption of ground wave by earth's surface", "opta": "decreases", "optb": "increases", "optc": "remains the same", "optd": "either (a) or (c)", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Because of this reason ground waves can be used for frequencies upto about 1600 kHz only."}, {"question": "The velocity of sound waves in air", "opta": "is constant at all temperatures", "optb": "varies directly as temperature", "optc": "varies inversely as absolute temperature", "optd": "varies directly as square root of absolute temperature", "ans": "D", "explanation": "v \u221d T."}, {"question": "The range of a cordless telephone is about", "opta": "1000 m", "optb": "500 m", "optc": "100 m", "optd": "10 m", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The range depends on quality of instrument and is about 100 m."}, {"question": "An earth mat for a communication tower consists of", "opta": "one or two radials extending from base of tower at a depth of about 5 cm below ground", "optb": "a large number of radials extending from base of tower at a depth of about 3 m", "optc": "a large number of radials extending from base of tower at a depth of about 30 cm", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The number of radials is large and depth is about 30 cm."}, {"question": "Degaussing in a picture tube means", "opta": "Adding magnetism in mask and mounting frame", "optb": "Removing residual magnetism in mask, shield etc...", "optc": "Increasing resistance of coils to decrease time constant", "optd": "Decreasing resistance of coils to increase time constant.", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since gauss is a unit of magnetic flux, degaussing means removal of magnetism."}, {"question": "The rate at which information can be carried through a communication channel depends on", "opta": "carrier frequency", "optb": "bandwidth", "optc": "transmission loss", "optd": "transmitted power", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Rate of information depends on bandwidth."}, {"question": "Some types of traps used in video IF amplifier of colour TV are", "opta": "shunt traps", "optb": "series traps", "optc": "absorption traps", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "All these are used."}, {"question": "Direct and reflected sound waves may interfere with each other.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "PAS use moving coil microphones."}, {"question": "A carrier is simultaneously modulated by two sine waves having modulation indices of 0.4 and 0.3. The total modulation index will be", "opta": "0.1", "optb": "0.7", "optc": "0.5", "optd": "0.35", "ans": "C", "explanation": "m1 = 0.4, m2 = 0.3\n."}, {"question": "A 1000 kHz carrier is simultaneously modulated with 300 Hz, 800 Hz and 2 kHz audio sine waves. Which of the following frequency is least likely to be present in the output?", "opta": "1002 kHz", "optb": "1000 kHz", "optc": "999.2 kHz", "optd": "998.0 kHz", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Frequency present in the sidebands is equal to = fc \u00b1 fm, fc \u00b1 2fm , fc \u00b1 3fm ."}, {"question": "In standing wave pattern on a transmission line", "opta": "voltage and current nodes coincide", "optb": "voltage and current antinodes coincide", "optc": "voltage nodes and current antinodes as well as current nodes and voltage antinodes coincide", "optd": "both (a) and (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "When standing wave is set up voltage maxima and current minima and voltage minima and current maxima coincide."}, {"question": "If the bandwidth is increased by 2, the \u03b3FM \u03b3AM (where \u03b3 is the ratio of SNR of output to SNR at input, FM is frequency modulation and AM is amplitude modulation) is increased by a factor of", "opta": "2", "optb": "3", "optc": "4", "optd": "6", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Doubling of frequency increase SNR in frequency modulation by 4. It has no effect in AM."}, {"question": "In the figure , the output y(t) will be", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "A carrier wave carries information.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Carrier does not have any information."}, {"question": "Frequency shift keying is used mostly in", "opta": "telegraphy", "optb": "telephony", "optc": "satellite communication", "optd": "radio transmission", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Frequency shift keying (FSK) is a system of frequency modulation used in telegraphy."}, {"question": "It is desired that transmission line and load should match for a range of frequencies. The best method is", "opta": "to use a balun", "optb": "to use a single stub of adjustable position", "optc": "to use a double stub", "optd": "to use a broad band amplifier", "ans": "C", "explanation": "When matching over a range of frequencies is desired, double stub is necessary."}, {"question": "Which of the following has the highest input impedance?", "opta": "CE", "optb": "CB", "optc": "CC", "optd": "Push pull", "ans": "C", "explanation": "CC connection has very high input impedance and low output impedance."}, {"question": "In a fascimile reproduction time to scan one line is 2 ms. If it has 4% blanking, the visible trace time is", "opta": "1.92 ms", "optb": "2.08 ms", "optc": "50 ms", "optd": "0.08 ms", "ans": "A", "explanation": "(2 ms) (1 - 0.04) = 1.92 ms."}, {"question": "Consider the following statements The amplitude of an FM wave is constantFM is more immune to noise than AMFM broadcasts operate in upper VHF and UHF frequency rangesFM transmitting and receiving equipments are simpler as compared to AM transmitting and receiving equipments Which of the above are correct?", "opta": "1, 2, 3, 4", "optb": "1, 2, 3", "optc": "2, 3, 4", "optd": "1, 3, 4", "ans": "B", "explanation": "FM equipments are complex as compared to AM equipments."}, {"question": "Signal to noise ratio of microphone is defined as the ratio of output when the sound pressure is __________ to the output in the absence of any sound signal.", "opta": "0.5 Pa", "optb": "0.2 Pa", "optc": "0.1 Pa", "optd": "0.01 Pa", "ans": "C", "explanation": "0.1 Pa (= 0.5 x 10-4 W/m2) is taken as standard sound pressure for defining S/N ratio of microphones."}, {"question": "A generator is feeding power to a transmission line of characteristic impedance Z0. The line is terminated in impedance ZL. Standing waves will be set up if", "opta": "ZL = Z0", "optb": "ZL < Z0", "optc": "ZL > Z0", "optd": "both (b) and (c)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Both the case, i.e., ZL > Z0 and ZL < Z0 give rise to standing waves."}, {"question": "In sound recording the degree of pre-emphasis is about 6 dB/ octave.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "It erases the matter already existing on the tape."}, {"question": "Space wave may be a direct wave or wave reflected from earth.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Strength of space wave depends on distance as it suffers attenuation."}, {"question": "Radio broadcasts are generally", "opta": "amplitude modulation", "optb": "frequency modulation", "optc": "both amplitude and frequency modulation", "optd": "neither amplitude nor frequency modulation", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Frequency modulation gives noise free reception and is used for radio broadcasts."}, {"question": "If the frequency of a wave 20 Hz, the time period is", "opta": "20 secs", "optb": "2 secs", "optc": "0.2 secs", "optd": "0.05 secs", "ans": "D", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "Which of the following is taken as reference antenna for directive gain?", "opta": "Half wave dipole", "optb": "Elementary doublet", "optc": "Isotropic", "optd": "Infinitesimal dipole", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Isotropic antenna is one which radiates equally in all directions. It is a standard reference antenna."}, {"question": "Push pull amplifier is", "opta": "voltage amplifier", "optb": "current amplifier", "optc": "power amplifier", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Push pull is a power amplifier."}, {"question": "When the channel is noisy, producing a conditional probability of error p = 0.5; the channel capacity and entropy function would be, respectively,", "opta": "1 and 1", "optb": "1 and 0.5", "optc": "0.5 and 1", "optd": "0 and 1", "ans": "D", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "In CCIR-B system, the time between start of one H syn. pulse and next is", "opta": "64 \u03bcs", "optb": "6.4 \u03bcs", "optc": "640 \u03bcs", "optd": "0.64 \u03bcs", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The frequency of H pulses is 15625 Hz. \nHence ."}, {"question": "Counterpoise is used in coils having", "opta": "high resistivity", "optb": "low resistivity", "optc": "medium resistivity", "optd": "both (b) and (c)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Counterpoise is a horizontally buried wire used to provide low grounding resistance in high resistivity soils."}, {"question": "The resolution of an n bit DAC with a maximum input of 5 V is 5 mV. The value of n is", "opta": "8", "optb": "9", "optc": "10", "optd": "11", "ans": "C", "explanation": "1000 = 5 or N = 10."}, {"question": "2's complement of binary number 0101 is", "opta": "1011", "optb": "1111", "optc": "1101", "optd": "1110", "ans": "A", "explanation": "1's complement of 0101 is 1010 and 2's complement is 1010+1 = 1011."}, {"question": "An OR gate has 4 inputs. One input is high and the other three are low. The output", "opta": "is low", "optb": "is high", "optc": "is alternately high and low", "optd": "may be high or low depending on relative magnitude of inputs", "ans": "B", "explanation": "In OR any input high means high output."}, {"question": "Decimal number 10 is equal to binary number", "opta": "1110", "optb": "1010", "optc": "1001", "optd": "1000", "ans": "B", "explanation": "1010 = 8 + 2 = 10 in decimal."}, {"question": "Both OR and AND gates can have only two inputs.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Any number of inputs are possible."}, {"question": "A device which converts BCD to seven segment is called", "opta": "encoder", "optb": "decoder", "optc": "multiplexer", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Decoder converts binary/BCD to alphanumeric."}, {"question": "In 2's complement representation the number 11100101 represents the decimal number", "opta": "+37", "optb": "-31", "optc": "+27", "optd": "-27", "ans": "D", "explanation": "A = 11100101. Therefore A = 00011010 and A' = A + 1 = 00011011 = 16 + 8 + 2 + 1 = 27. Therefore A = -27."}, {"question": "A decade counter skips", "opta": "binary states 1000 to 1111", "optb": "binary states 0000 to 0011", "optc": "binary states 1010 to 1111", "optd": "binary states 1111 to higher", "ans": "C", "explanation": "A decade counter counts from 0 to 9. It has 4 flip-flops. The states skipped are 10 to 15 or 1010 to 1111."}, {"question": "BCD input 1000 is fed to a 7 segment display through a BCD to 7 segment decoder/driver. The segments which will lit up are", "opta": "a, b, d", "optb": "a, b, c", "optc": "all", "optd": "a, b, g, c, d", "ans": "C", "explanation": "1000 equals decimal 8 Therefore all segments will lit up."}, {"question": "A ring counter with 5 flip flops will have", "opta": "5 states", "optb": "10 states", "optc": "32 states", "optd": "infinite states", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For the gate in the given figure the output will be", "opta": "0", "optb": "1", "optc": "A", "optd": "A", "ans": "D", "explanation": "If A = 0, Y = 1 and A = 1, Y = 0 Therefore Y = A."}, {"question": "In the expression A + BC, the total number of minterms will be", "opta": "2", "optb": "3", "optc": "4", "optd": "5", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The min terms are ABC + ABC + AB C + ABC + ABC."}, {"question": "The circuit in the given figure is", "opta": "positive logic OR gate", "optb": "negative logic OR gate", "optc": "negative logic AND gate", "optd": "positive logic AND gate", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since V(1) is lower state than V(0) it is a negative logic circuit. Since diodes are in parallel, it is an OR gate."}, {"question": "Which of the following is non-saturating?", "opta": "TTL", "optb": "CMOS", "optc": "ECL", "optd": "Both (a) and (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Since it is non-saturating, ECL has low propagation delay."}, {"question": "The number of digits in octal system is", "opta": "8", "optb": "7", "optc": "9", "optd": "10", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The octal system has 8 digits 0 to 7."}, {"question": "The access time of a word in 4 MB main memory is 100 ms. The access time of a word in a 32 kb data cache memory is 10 ns. The average data cache bit ratio is 0.95. The efficiency of memory access time is", "opta": "9.5 ns", "optb": "14.5 ns", "optc": "20 ns", "optd": "95 ns", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Access time = 0.95 x 10 + 0.05 x 100."}, {"question": "The expression Y = pM (0, 1, 3, 4) is", "opta": "POS", "optb": "SOP", "optc": "Hybrid", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "This is product of sums expression."}, {"question": "An 8 bit DAC has a full scale output of 2 mA and full scale error of \u00b1 0.5%. If input is 10000000 the range of outputs is", "opta": "994 to 1014 \u03bcA", "optb": "990 to 1020 \u03bcA", "optc": "800 to 1200 \u03bcA", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "10000000 = 128, 11111111 = 255 \nIf there is no error, output =  = 1004\u03bcA. \nMaximum error =  \nHence range of output 994 to 1014 \u03bcA."}, {"question": "Decimal 43 in hexadecimal and BCD number system is respectively.", "opta": "B2, 01000011", "optb": "2B, 01000011", "optc": "2B, 00110100", "optd": "B2, 01000100", "ans": "B", "explanation": "(43)10 = (2B)16\n(43)10 = (01000011)2 ."}, {"question": "The circuit of the given figure realizes the function", "opta": "Y = (A + B) C + DE", "optb": "Y = A + B + C + D + E", "optc": "AB + C +DE", "optd": "AB + C(D + E)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "or \nY = (A + B)C + DE."}, {"question": "An AND gate has two inputs A and B and one inhibit input 3, Output is 1 if", "opta": "A = 1, B = 1, S = 1", "optb": "A = 1, B = 1, S = 0", "optc": "A = 1, B = 0, S = 1", "optd": "A = 1, B = 0, S = 0", "ans": "B", "explanation": "All AND inputs must be 1 and inhibit 0 for output to be 1."}, {"question": "The greatest negative number which can be stored is 8 bit computer using 2's complement arithmetic is", "opta": "- 256", "optb": "- 128", "optc": "- 255", "optd": "- 127", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The largest negative number is 1000 0000 = -128."}, {"question": "A JK flip flop has tpd= 12 ns. The largest modulus of a ripple counter using these flip flops and operating at 10 MHz is", "opta": "16", "optb": "64", "optc": "128", "optd": "256", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Number of flip-flops =  = 8.333 say 8 \nModulus = 28 = 256."}, {"question": "The basic storage element in a digital system is", "opta": "flip flop", "optb": "counter", "optc": "multiplexer", "optd": "encoder", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Storing can be done only in memory and flip-flop is a memory element."}, {"question": "In a ripple counter,", "opta": "whenever a flip flop sets to 1, the next higher FF toggles", "optb": "whenever a flip flop sets to 0, the next higher FF remains unchanged", "optc": "whenever a flip flop sets to 1, the next higher FF faces race condition", "optd": "whenever a flip flop sets to 0, the next higher FF faces race condition", "ans": "A", "explanation": "In a ripple counter the effect ripples through the counter."}, {"question": "A 12 bit ADC is used to convert analog voltage of 0 to 10 V into digital. The resolution is", "opta": "2.44 mV", "optb": "24.4 mV", "optc": "1.2 V", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "For the truth table of the given figure Y =", "opta": "A + B + C", "optb": "A + BC", "optc": "A", "optd": "B", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Y = A B C + A B C + AB C + A B C = A B (C + C) + A B (C + C) = A B + AB = B(A + A) = B."}, {"question": "A full adder can be made out of", "opta": "two half adders", "optb": "two half adders and a OR gate", "optc": "two half adders and a NOT gate", "optd": "three half adders", "ans": "B", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "If the functions w, x, y, z are as follows.w = R + PQ + RS , x = PQR S + PQR S + PQ R SThen", "opta": "w = z x = z", "optb": "w = z, x = y", "optc": "w = y", "optd": "w = y = z", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Use k-map, then it will be easy."}, {"question": "The output of a half adder is", "opta": "SUM", "optb": "CARRY", "optc": "SUM and CARRY", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Minimum number of 2-input NAND gates required to implement the function F = (x + y) (Z + W) is", "opta": "3", "optb": "4", "optc": "5", "optd": "6", "ans": "B", "explanation": "F = (x + y) (z + w) = xy.(z + w)\n= xyz + xyw\n=  minimum no. of 2 input NAND gate."}, {"question": "Which device has one input and many outputs?", "opta": "Multiplexer", "optb": "Demultiplexer", "optc": "Counter", "optd": "Flip flop", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Demultiplexer takes data from one line and directs it to any of its N output depending on the status of its select lines."}, {"question": "A carry look ahead adder is frequently used for addition because", "opta": "it costs less", "optb": "it is faster", "optc": "it is more accurate", "optd": "is uses fewer gates", "ans": "B", "explanation": "In look ahead carry adder the carry is directly derived from the gates when original inputs are being added. Hence the addition is fast. This process requires more gates and is costly."}, {"question": "The counter in the given figure is", "opta": "Mod 3", "optb": "Mod 6", "optc": "Mod 8", "optd": "Mod 7", "ans": "B", "explanation": "When counter is 110 the counter resets. Hence mod 6."}, {"question": "In register index addressing mode the effective address is given by", "opta": "index register value", "optb": "sum of the index register value and the operand", "optc": "operand", "optd": "difference of the index register value and the operand", "ans": "B", "explanation": "4 = 22, in up scaling digit will be shifted by two bit in right direction."}, {"question": "7BF16 = __________ 2", "opta": "0111 1011 1110", "optb": "0111 1011 1111", "optc": "0111 1011 0111", "optd": "0111 1011 0011", "ans": "B", "explanation": "7BF16 = 7 x 162 + 11 x 161 + 15 x 160 = 1983 in decimal = 0111 1011 1111 in binary."}, {"question": "For the minterm designation Y = \u2211 m (1, 3, 5, 7) the complete expression is", "opta": "Y = A BC + A B C", "optb": "Y = A B C + A B C + ABC + A BC", "optc": "Y = A B C + A B C + ABC + A BC", "optd": "Y = A B C + ABC + A BC + A BC", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Decimal number 1 = binary number 001 = A BC Decimal number 7 = binary number 111= ABC, Decimal number 3 = binary number 011= ABC Decimal number 5 = binary number 101= ABC . Hence result."}, {"question": "Zero suppression is not used in actual practice.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Zero suppression is commonly used."}, {"question": "A counter type A/D converter contains a 4 bit binary ladder and a counter driven by a 2 MHz clock. Then conversion time", "opta": "8 \u03bc sec", "optb": "10 \u03bc sec", "optc": "2 \u03bc sec", "optd": "5 \u03bc sec", "ans": "A", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "The hexadecimal number (3E8)16 is equal to decimal number", "opta": "1000", "optb": "982", "optc": "768", "optd": "323", "ans": "A", "explanation": "3 x 162 + 14 x 161 + 8 = 1000."}, {"question": "The number of distinct Boolean expression of 4 variables is", "opta": "16", "optb": "256", "optc": "1024", "optd": "65536", "ans": "D", "explanation": "22n = 224 = 216 ."}, {"question": "The fixed count that should be used so that the output register will represent the input for a 6 bit dual slope A/D converter uses a reference of -6v and a 1 MHz clock. It uses a fixed count of 40 (101000).", "opta": "000110", "optb": "0010", "optc": "1111", "optd": "011101", "ans": "A", "explanation": "If  is made to be unity, the O/P count N2 = ei,  N1 = 6 = 000110."}, {"question": "For the K map in the given figure the simplified Boolean expression is", "opta": "A C + A D + ABC", "optb": "A C + A D + ABC", "optc": "A C + A D + ACD", "optd": "A C + A D + AB C", "ans": "A", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "A memory system of size 16 k bytes is to be designed using memory chips which have 12 address lines and 4 data lines each. The number of such chips required to design the memory system is", "opta": "2", "optb": "4", "optc": "8", "optd": "18", "ans": "C", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "In a 7 segment display, LEDs b and c lit up. The decimal number displayed is", "opta": "9", "optb": "7", "optc": "3", "optd": "1", "ans": "D", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "AB + AB =", "opta": "B", "optb": "A", "optc": "1", "optd": "0", "ans": "B", "explanation": "AB + AB = A(B + B) = A . 1 = A."}, {"question": "In a BCD to 7 segment decoder the minimum and maximum number of outputs active at any time is", "opta": "2 and 7", "optb": "3 and 7", "optc": "1 and 6", "optd": "3 and 6", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Minimum number of outputs when input is decimal 1 and maximum number of outputs when input is decimal 8."}, {"question": "A three state switch has three outputs. These are", "opta": "low, low and high", "optb": "low, high, high", "optc": "low. floating, low", "optd": "low, high, floating", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Third state is floating."}, {"question": "Maxterm designation for A + B + C is", "opta": "M0", "optb": "M1", "optc": "M3", "optd": "M4", "ans": "A", "explanation": "A + B + C = 000 = M0 ."}, {"question": "1's complement of 11100110 is", "opta": "00011001", "optb": "10000001", "optc": "00011010", "optd": "00000000", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Replace 1 by 0 and 0 by 1."}, {"question": "ZL = 200 &ohm; and it is desired that Zi = 50 &ohm; The quarter wave transformer should have a characteristic impedance of", "opta": "100 &ohm;", "optb": "40 &ohm;", "optc": "10000 &ohm;", "optd": "4 &ohm;", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Z0 = Zi . ZL"}, {"question": "A broadside array consisting of 200 cm wavelength with 10 half-wave dipole spacing 10 cm. And if each array element feeding with 1 amp. current and operating at same frequency then find the half power beamwidth", "opta": "4\u00b0", "optb": "2\u00b0", "optc": "10\u00b0", "optd": "15\u00b0", "ans": "B", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "Refractive index of glass is 1.5. Find the wavelength of a beam of light with a frequency of 1014 Hz in glass. Assume velocity of light is 3 x 108 m/sec in vacuum.", "opta": "4 \u03bcm", "optb": "3 \u03bcm", "optc": "2 \u03bcm", "optd": "1 \u03bcm", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Given, \u03bc = 1.6, f = 1014 Hz, v = 3 x 108 m/sec."}, {"question": "The function f(x - vot) represent which of the following?", "opta": "A stationary wave", "optb": "A wave motion in forward direction", "optc": "A wave motion in reverse direction", "optd": "None of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "f(x - vot) represents in +ve direction while f(x + vot) represents a progressive wave in -ve direction."}, {"question": "A broadside array operating at 100 cm wavelength consist of 4 half-wave dipoles spaced 50 cm apart. Each element carries radio frequency current in the same phase and of magnitude 0.5 A. The radiated power will be", "opta": "196 W", "optb": "73 W", "optc": "36.5 W", "optd": "18.25 W", "ans": "A", "explanation": "P = n . I2 . Rr, where Rr = 80p2  &ohm;.\nn = 4."}, {"question": "The input impedance of short-circuited line of length l where \u03bb/4 < l < \u03bb/2, is", "opta": "resistive", "optb": "inductive", "optc": "capacitive", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "l < \u03bb/4, ZL = 0\n, if Zd comes +j kZC then inductive, \nIf Zd comes -j kZC then capacitive.\nfor 0 \u2264 l \u2264 1/4, \u03bb \u2264 l \u2264 3\u03bb/4 will be inductive."}, {"question": "A wave is propagated in a waveguide at frequency of 9 GHz and separation is 2 cm between walls find cut off wavelength for dominant mode.", "opta": "4 cm", "optb": "1 cm", "optc": "2 cm", "optd": "8 cm", "ans": "A", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "Find the radiation resistance of an antenna of length \u03bb/10 meter?", "opta": "8 &ohm;", "optb": "780 &ohm;", "optc": "7.8 &ohm;", "optd": "78 &ohm;", "ans": "C", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "Charge needed within a unit sphere centred at the origin for producing a potential field,", "opta": "12 pc", "optb": "60 pc", "optc": "120 pc", "optd": "180 pc", "ans": "C", "explanation": "q = 120p coulomb, r = 1 meter."}, {"question": "A rectangular metal waveguide filled with a dielectric of relative permittivity \u03b5r = 4, has the inside dimensions 3 x 1.2 cm, the cut off frequency for the dominant mode is", "opta": "2.5 GHz", "optb": "5 GHz", "optc": "10 GHz", "optd": "12.5 GHz", "ans": "B", "explanation": "for dominant mode."}, {"question": "A wave is propagated in a waveguide at frequency of 9 GHz and separation is 2 cm between walls Calculate group velocity for dominant mode.", "opta": "1.8 x 108 m/sec", "optb": "5 x 108 m/sec", "optc": "3 x 108 m/sec", "optd": "1.5 x 108 m/sec", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Vg . Vp = C2\nwhere \n."}, {"question": "For F1 layer the maximum ionic density is 2.3 x 104 electrons per cc. The critical frequency for this layer will be", "opta": "1.36 MHz", "optb": "13.6 MHz", "optc": "136 MHz", "optd": "1360 MHz", "ans": "B", "explanation": "fc = 9Nmax ."}, {"question": "Which one of the following does represents the electric field lines for the TE02 mode in the cross section of a hollow rectangular metallic waveguide?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "TE02  m = 0, n = 2\nin x direction no propagation, only in y, and normal to the waveguide, tangential component is continuous."}, {"question": "The velocity of electromagnetic wave in a good conductor is", "opta": "3 x 108 m/s", "optb": "more than 3 x 108 m/s", "optc": "very low", "optd": "high", "ans": "C", "explanation": ", for good conductor \u03b5r >> 1."}, {"question": "Radiation intensity of a dipole depends strongly on frequency. If at a frequency f, the intensity of radiation is 'I'. Then at a frequency of f/2, the intensity will be", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "I \u221d f."}, {"question": "Consider a 300 &ohm;, quarter wave long at 1 GHz transmission line as shown in figure. It is connected to a 10 V, 50 &ohm; source at one end is left open circuited at the other end. The magnitude of the voltage at the open circuit end of the line is", "opta": "10 V", "optb": "5 V", "optc": "60 V", "optd": "60/7 volt", "ans": "A", "explanation": "\u03b3 = a + j\u03b2 a = 0  \u03b3 = j\u03b2\nPropagating wave\nv = VI e-rz + VR erz\nNo change in the voltage at the open end it will same, \nvr = 10 volt."}, {"question": "The phase angle corresponding to \u03bb/4 in a standing-wave pattern is", "opta": "30\u00b0", "optb": "90\u00b0", "optc": "135\u00b0", "optd": "180\u00b0", "ans": "B", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "A hollow rectangular waveguide has dimensions a = 2b. Calculate the amount of attenuation, if the frequency is 3 GHz, and b = 1 cm.", "opta": "49", "optb": "47.33", "optc": "50.33", "optd": "50", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since, wave is attenuated hence \u03b2 = 0\nand  Take, dominant mode m = 1, \nn = 0\n ."}, {"question": "Calculate the directivity of an antenna for \u03b8E = 30\u00b0, \u03b8H = 60", "opta": "46", "optb": "23", "optc": "50", "optd": "100", "ans": "B", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "Most antenna consisting of a 50 meter long vertical conductor operates over a perfectly conducting ground plane. It is base fed at a frequency of 600 kHz. The radiation resistance of the antenna in ohms is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "20p2", "ans": "C", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "A (75 - j 40) W load is connected to a co-axial line of z0 = 75\u03c9 at 6 MHz. The load matching on the line can be accomplished by connecting", "opta": "a short circuit stub at the load", "optb": "an inductance at the load", "optc": "a short circuit stub at a specific distance from the load", "optd": "a capacitance at a specific distance from the load", "ans": "B", "explanation": "ZL = 75 - J . 40, ZC = 75 W, f = 6 mHz\nGiven ZL is capacitive, so proper matching, load must be inductive."}, {"question": "A plane wave is characterized by  the wave is", "opta": "linearly polarized", "optb": "circularly polarized", "optc": "elliptically polarized", "optd": "unpolarized", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Because, magnitude is different (0.5, 1) and phase is 90\u00b0"}, {"question": "The electric field on the surface of a perfect conductor is 2V/m. The conductor is immersed in water with \u03b5 = 80 \u03b50. The surface charge density on the conductor is ((\u03b50 = 10-9/36p)F/m)", "opta": "0 c/m2", "optb": "2 c/m2", "optc": "1.8 x 10-11 c/m2", "optd": "1.14 x 10-9 c/m2", "ans": "D", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "A wave is propagated in a waveguide at frequency of 9 GHz and separation is 2 cm between walls calculate the phase velocity for dominant mode.", "opta": "3 x 108 m/sec", "optb": "5 x 108 m/sec", "optc": "1.5 x 108 m/sec", "optd": "9 x 108 m/sec", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Vg . Vp = C2\nwhere ."}, {"question": "A plane electromagnetic wave travels in dielectric medium of relative permittivity 9. Relative to free space, the velocity of propagation in the dielectric is", "opta": "increased by a factor of 9", "optb": "increased by a factor of 3", "optc": "unchanged", "optd": "reduced by a factor of 1/3", "ans": "D", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "Consider a loss less antenna with a directive gain of + 6 dB. If 1 mW of power is fed to it the total power radiated by the antenna will be", "opta": "4 mW", "optb": "1 mW", "optc": "7 mW", "optd": "1/4 mW", "ans": "A", "explanation": "6 dB = 10 log10 \n = 100.6  3.98\nPr = 3.98 mW."}, {"question": "A uniform plane wave is one in which", "opta": "x  = 0", "optb": ".", "optc": "and  are perpendicular", "optd": "and  lie in a plane", "ans": "D", "explanation": "For uniform plane wave, E and H must be in a plane but perpendicular to each other."}, {"question": "The electric field of the incident wave is , where \u03c9 = 3 x 109p and \u03b2 = 10 p. The electric field of the transmitted wave Et is given by", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "In, question, it is not mentioned, about medium; dielectric etc.\nEi = Et + Er \n Et = Er \n Et =  Ei."}, {"question": "A short circuited stub is shunt connected to a transmission line as shown in the figure is, if z0 = 500 ohms, the admittance y seen at the function of the stub and the transmission line is", "opta": "(0.01 - j 0.02) mho", "optb": "(0.02 - j 0.01) mho", "optc": "(0.04 - j 0.02) mho", "optd": "(0.02 + j 0) mho", "ans": "A", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Which of the following should dominant wave have?", "opta": "Lowest cut off frequency", "optb": "Highest cut off frequency", "optc": "No attenuation", "optd": "No phase shift", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Lowest cut off frequency or highest wave-length in a waveguide gives dominant modes."}, {"question": "Calculate the wave impedance for TM mode in rectangular waveguide for dominant mode at 3 GHz having", "opta": "(120p) &ohm;", "optb": "377 &ohm;", "optc": "226 &ohm;", "optd": "629 &ohm;", "ans": "C", "explanation": "\u03b7 = 226 &ohm;."}, {"question": "The divergence of the electric field intensity at any point equals", "opta": "1/4 p\u03b50 times the volume charge density", "optb": "l/\u03b50 times the volume charge density at that point", "optc": "\u03b50 times the volume charge density at that point", "optd": "the volume charge density at that point", "ans": "B", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "For a 400 kHz transmission line having L = 0.5 mH/km, C = 0.08 mF and negligible R and G, the value of propagation constant P will be", "opta": "15.9 radians/km", "optb": "31.8 radians/km", "optc": "63.6 radians/km", "optd": "105.4 radians/km", "ans": "A", "explanation": "\u03b3 = a + j\u03b2, a = 0 \u03b2 = \u03c9LC."}, {"question": "The Depth of penetration of EM wave in medium having conductivity \u03c3 at a frequency of 1 MHz is 25 cm. The depth of penetration at a frequency of 4 MHz will be", "opta": "6.25 cm", "optb": "12.50 cm", "optc": "50 cm", "optd": "100 cm", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Skin depth \n\n \u03b42 = \u03b41/2 ."}, {"question": "What is the characteristic impedance at 10 MHz?", "opta": "547.7 &ohm;", "optb": "54.7 &ohm;", "optc": "5.47 &ohm;", "optd": ".547 &ohm;", "ans": "A", "explanation": ", not depend upon frequency."}, {"question": "The torque (in mm) acting on a circular current loop of radius 1 mm in the xy plane, connected at the origin and with current 0.1 A, flowing in the sense of increasing in a magnetic field  is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "10-12p", "optd": "- 10-12p", "ans": "B", "explanation": "t = M x B"}, {"question": "Which one of the following potential does not satisfy Laplace's equations?", "opta": "v = 10 xy", "optb": "v = p cos \u03c6", "optc": "", "optd": "v = f cos \u03c6 + 10", "ans": "B", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "A rectangular waveguide measures 3 x 4.5 cm internally and has a 10 GHz signal propagated in it. Calculate the wave impedance for dominant mode.", "opta": "130 p", "optb": "1.3 p", "optc": "120 p", "optd": "12 p", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Wave impedance  \n."}, {"question": "Calculate wave impedance for TE mode", "opta": "(377)&ohm;", "optb": "226 &ohm;", "optc": "\u221e", "optd": "629 &ohm;", "ans": "D", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "In a 100 turn coil, if the flux through each turn is (t3 - 2t)mWb, the magnitude of the induced emf in the coil at a time of 4 sec is", "opta": "46 mV", "optb": "56 mV", "optc": "4.6 V", "optd": "5.6 V", "ans": "C", "explanation": "E = 100 (3t2 - 2)  100(46)  4600 mV\n 4.6 V."}, {"question": "A transmission line is feeding 1 watt of power to a horn antenna having a gain of 10 dB. The antenna is matched to the transmission line. The total power radiated by the horn antenna into the free space is", "opta": "10 watts", "optb": "1 watt", "optc": "0.1 watt", "optd": "0.01 watt", "ans": "A", "explanation": "= 101  Pr = 10 watt."}, {"question": "A parallel polarized wave is incident from air into paraffin having relative permittivity 3, the value of its Brewster angle is", "opta": "0\u00b0", "optb": "30\u00b0", "optc": "45\u00b0", "optd": "60\u00b0", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Brewster angle \u03b8 = tan-1 ."}, {"question": "In a conductor which of the following relations hold good?", "opta": "\u2207 x D = r", "optb": "\u2207 . D = r", "optc": "\u2207 x D = 0", "optd": "\u2207 . D = 0", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Inside a conductor free charge is zero, hence, \u2207 x D = 0."}, {"question": "The radiation resistance of a \u03bb/16 wire dipole in free space will be nearly", "opta": "1 &ohm;", "optb": "3 &ohm;", "optc": "13 &ohm;", "optd": "30 &ohm;", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Rr = 80p2."}, {"question": "Two identical antennas are placed in the \u03b8 = p/2 plane as shown in the figure. The elements have equal amplitude excitation with 180\u00b0 polarity difference, operating of the far-zone resultant electric field strength normalized with that of a single element, both computed for \u03c6 = 0, is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Normalised array factor = n cos \n\nwhere \u03c6 is the phase difference.\n \u03c6 = (\u03b2d sin \u03b8 cos \u03c6 + \u03b81)\nand \u03b8 = 90\u00b0, \u03c6 = 45\u00b0"}, {"question": "Find the noise factor for an antenna at 27\u00b0C with equivalent noise temperature 30\u00b0K", "opta": "20", "optb": "100", "optc": "300", "optd": "1.1", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Te = T0(F - 1)\n ."}, {"question": "The displacement flux density at a point on the surface of a perfect conductor is  = 2(ax - 3 az)c/m2 pointing away from the surface. The charge density at that point c/m2 will be", "opta": "2", "optb": "- 2", "optc": "4", "optd": "- 4", "ans": "C", "explanation": "\u2207 . D = r."}, {"question": "Characteristic impedance of a transmission line is 50 &ohm;. Input impedance of the open circuited line. Zoc = 100 + J150 &ohm;. When transmission line is short circuited, then value of the input impedance will be", "opta": "50 &ohm;", "optb": "100 + J150 &ohm;", "optc": "7.69 + J11.54&ohm;", "optd": "7.69 - J11.54 &ohm;", "ans": "D", "explanation": "ZC = ZOC - ZSC  50 = (100 + j150)(ZSC) ."}, {"question": "At room temperature the current in an intrinsic semiconductor is due to", "opta": "holes", "optb": "electrons", "optc": "ions", "optd": "holes and electrons", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Intrinsic material has equal number of holes and electrons."}, {"question": "Work function is the maximum energy required by the fastest electron at 0 K to escape from the metal surface.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Work function is the minimum energy required by the fastest electron at 0 K to escape from the metal surface."}, {"question": "The most commonly used semiconductor material is", "opta": "silicon", "optb": "germanium", "optc": "mixture of silicon and germanium", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Germanium is rarely used."}, {"question": "In which of these is reverse recovery time nearly zero?", "opta": "Zener diode", "optb": "Tunnel diode", "optc": "Schottky diode", "optd": "PIN diode", "ans": "C", "explanation": "In schottky diode there is no charge storage and hence almost zero reverse recovery time."}, {"question": "A transistor has a current gain of 0.99 in the CB mode. Its current gain in the CC mode is", "opta": "100", "optb": "99", "optc": "1.01", "optd": "0.99", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Current gain = 1 + \u03b2 = 100."}, {"question": "In p-n-p transistor the current IE has two components viz. IEP due to injection of holes from p-region to n-region and IE due to injection of electrons from n-region to p-region. Then", "opta": "IEp and IEn are almost equal", "optb": "IEp >> IEn", "optc": "IEn >> IEp", "optd": "either (a) or (c)", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Emitter is p-type in p-n-p transistor. \n\nTherefore holes are majority carriers."}, {"question": "In an n channel JFET, the gate is", "opta": "n type", "optb": "p type", "optc": "either n or p", "optd": "partially n & partially p", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since channel is n type gate must be p type."}, {"question": "The amount of photoelectric emission current depends on", "opta": "frequency of incident radiation", "optb": "intensity of incident radiation", "optc": "both frequency and intensity of incident radiation", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Only the intensity of incident radiation governs the amount of photoelectric emission."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  A p-n junction has high resistance in reverse direction.\nReason (R):  When a reverse bias is applied to p-n junction, the width of depletion layer increases.", "opta": "Both A and R are true and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are true but R is not a correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true but R is false", "optd": "A is false but R is true", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The increase in reverse resistance is due to widening of depletion layer."}, {"question": "In the circuit of figure the function of resistor R and diode D are", "opta": "to limit the current and to protect LED against over voltage", "optb": "to limit the voltage and to protect LED against over current", "optc": "to limit the current and protect LED against reverse breakdown voltage.", "optd": "none of the above.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Resistance limits current and diode is reverse connected and therefore protects LED against reverse breakdown."}, {"question": "At very high temperatures the extrinsic semi conductors become intrinsic because", "opta": "drive in diffusion of dopants and carriers", "optb": "band to band transition dominants over impurity ionization", "optc": "impurity ionization dominants over band to band transition", "optd": "band to band transition is balanced by impurity ionization", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Covalent bonds are broken."}, {"question": "When a voltage is applied to a semiconductor crystal then the free electrons will flow.", "opta": "towards positive terminal", "optb": "towards negative terminal", "optc": "either towards positive terminal or negative terminal", "optd": "towards positive terminal for 1 \u03bcs and towards negative terminal for next 1 \u03bcs", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since electrons are negatively charged they will flow towards positive terminal."}, {"question": "Ferrite have", "opta": "low copper loss", "optb": "low eddy current loss", "optc": "low resistivity", "optd": "higher specific gravity compared to iron", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Ferrite is a low density material of composition with Fe2O3 x O, where x is a bivalent metal, such as Cobart, Ni, Mn. These magnetic materials having very low loss of current and used in high frequency circuit."}, {"question": "In a p type material the Fermi level is 0.3 eV above valence band. The concentration of acceptor atoms is increased. The new position of Fermi level is likely to be", "opta": "0.5 eV above valence band", "optb": "0.28 eV above valence band", "optc": "0.1 eV above valence band", "optd": "below the valence band", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Addition of acceptor atom brings Fermi level closer to valence band."}, {"question": "In an n-p-n transistor, the majority carriers in the base are", "opta": "electrons", "optb": "holes", "optc": "both holes and electrons", "optd": "either holes or electrons", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Emitter is n type and emits electrons which diffuse through the base."}, {"question": "An LED has a rating of 2 V and 10 mA. It is used along with 6V battery. The range of series resistance is", "opta": "0 to 200 &ohm;", "optb": "200 - 400 &ohm;", "optc": "200 &ohm; and above", "optd": "400 &ohm; and above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "R =  = 400&ohm;. \n\nR must be at least 400&ohm; so that current in LED does not exceed 10 mA."}, {"question": "The number of doped regions in PIN diode is", "opta": "1", "optb": "2", "optc": "3", "optd": "1 or 2", "ans": "B", "explanation": "A PIN diode has p and n doped regions separated by intrinsic layer."}, {"question": "A transistor has two p-n junctions. The batteries should be connected such that", "opta": "both junctions are forward biased", "optb": "both junctions are reverse biased", "optc": "one junction is forward biased and the other is reverse biased", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Emitter-base junction is forward biased and base collector junction is reverse biased."}, {"question": "A silicon (PN) junction at a temperature of 20\u00b0C has a reverse saturation current of 10 pico Ampere. The reverse saturation current at 40\u00b0C for the same bias is approximately.", "opta": "30 pA", "optb": "40 pA", "optc": "50 pA", "optd": "60 pA", "ans": "B", "explanation": "By increasing of temperature by 10\u00b0C, Io become double so by increasing temperature 20\u00b0C, Io become 4 time than initial value... and it is 40 PA."}, {"question": "In a bipolar transistor the barrier potential", "opta": "0", "optb": "a total of 0.7 V", "optc": "0.7 V across each depletion layer", "optd": "0.35 V", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Since there are two p-n junctions, there are two depletion layers and 0.7 V across each layer."}, {"question": "Recombination produces new electron-hole pairs", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Due to recombination the number of electron-hole pairs is reduced."}, {"question": "An amplifier without feedback has a voltage gain of 50, input resistance of 1 k&ohm; and output resistance of 2.5 k&ohm;. The input resistance of the current shunt -ve feedback amplifier using the above amplifier with a feedback factor of 0.2 is", "opta": "1/11 k&ohm;", "optb": "1/5 k&ohm;", "optc": "5 kW", "optd": "11 kW", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Input Resistance with feedback for current shunt, ."}, {"question": "As compared to an ordinary semiconductor diode, a Schottky diode", "opta": "has lower cut in voltage", "optb": "has higher cut in voltage", "optc": "lower reverse saturation current", "optd": "both (b) and (c)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Cut in voltage in Schottky diode is about 0.3 V as compared to 0.7 V in ordinary semiconductor diode."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  When a high reverse voltage is applied to a p-n junction the diode breaks down. \nReason (R):  High reverse voltage causes Avalanche effect.", "opta": "Both A and R are true and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are true but R is not a correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true but R is false", "optd": "A is false but R is true", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Avalanche breakdown occurs at high reverse voltage."}, {"question": "As compared to an ordinary semiconductor diode, a Schottky diode", "opta": "has higher reverse saturation current", "optb": "has higher reverse saturation current and higher cut in voltage", "optc": "has higher reverse saturation current and lower cut in voltage", "optd": "has lower reverse saturation current and lower cut in voltage", "ans": "C", "explanation": "This is due to high electron concentration in metals."}, {"question": "Crossover distortion behaviour is characteristic of", "opta": "class A O/P stage", "optb": "class B O/P stage", "optc": "class AB output stage", "optd": "common pulse O/P state", "ans": "B", "explanation": "It is a characteristics of class B output stage as the amplifier is biased in cut-off region.\n\nIn class B amplifier, two transistor are operated in such a way that one is amplify the half cycle and second is amplify -ve half cycle."}, {"question": "If aac for transistor is 0.98 then \u03b2ac is equal to", "opta": "51", "optb": "49", "optc": "47", "optd": "45", "ans": "B", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  The conductivity of p type semiconductor is higher than that of intrinsic semiconductor.\nReason (R):  The addition of donor impurity creates additional energy levels below conduction band.", "opta": "Both A and R are true and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are true but R is not a correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true but R is false", "optd": "A is false but R is true", "ans": "B", "explanation": "A refers to type semiconductor while R refers to n type semiconductor. Both A and R are correct but independent."}, {"question": "In an n-p-n transistor biased for operation in forward active region", "opta": "emitter is positive with respect to base", "optb": "collector is positive with respect to base", "optc": "base is positive with respect to emitter and collector is positive with respect to base", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "In forward active mode emitter base junction is forward biased and base collector junction is reverse biased."}, {"question": "An increase in temperature increases the width of depletion layer.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "With increase in temperature width of depletion layer decreases."}, {"question": "A zener diode is used in", "opta": "voltage regulator circuit", "optb": "amplifier circuits", "optc": "both voltage regulator and amplifier circuit", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Zener diode is used only in voltage regulator circuits."}, {"question": "A particular green LED emits light of wavelength 5490, \u00c5, the energy bandgap of the semiconductor material used there is .. h = 6.6 x 10-34 J sec.", "opta": "2.26 eV", "optb": "1.98 eV", "optc": "1.17 eV", "optd": "0.74 eV", "ans": "A", "explanation": "From Plank equation  joule \n\nto convert it into electron volt it will be divided by 1.6 x 10-19."}, {"question": "In a zener diode", "opta": "the forward current is very high", "optb": "sharp breakdown occurs at a certain reverse voltage", "optc": "the ratio v-i can be negative", "optd": "there are two p-n junctions", "ans": "B", "explanation": "When reverse voltage equals breakdown value it starts conducting and voltage does not increase further."}, {"question": "In a bipolar transistor which current is largest", "opta": "collector current", "optb": "base current", "optc": "emitter current", "optd": "base current or emitter current", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Emitter current is larger, collector current is slightly less than emitter current and base current is very small."}, {"question": "The v-i characteristics of a FET is shown in figure. In which region is the device biased for small signal amplification", "opta": "AB", "optb": "BC", "optc": "CD", "optd": "BD", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Small signal amplifier operation is in constant current region of characteristics."}, {"question": "Secondary emission is always decremental.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Sometimes it can be useful also."}, {"question": "In a degenerate n type semiconductor material, the Fermi level,", "opta": "is in valence band", "optb": "is in conduction band", "optc": "is at the centre in between valence and conduction bands", "optd": "is very near valence band", "ans": "B", "explanation": "This is due to high level of doping."}, {"question": "The types of carriers in a semiconductor are", "opta": "1", "optb": "2", "optc": "3", "optd": "4", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Holes and electrons."}, {"question": "A potential of 7 V is applied to a silicon diode. A resistance of 1 K ohm is also in series with the diode. The current is", "opta": "7 mA", "optb": "6.3 mA", "optc": "0.7 mA", "optd": "0", "ans": "B", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  The reverse saturation current in a semiconductor diode is 4nA at 20\u00b0C and 32 nA at 50\u00b0C.\nReason (R):  The reverse saturation current in a semiconductor diode doubles for every 10\u00b0C rise in temperature.", "opta": "Both A and R are true and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are true but R is not a correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true but R is false", "optd": "A is false but R is true", "ans": "A", "explanation": "At 20\u00b0C, 4 nA, at 30\u00b0C, 8 nA, at 40\u00b0C, 16 nA, at 50\u00b0C, 32 nA."}, {"question": "Calculate the stability factor and change in IC from 25\u00b0C to 100\u00b0C for, \u03b2 = 50, RB/ RE = 250, \u0394IC0 = 19.9 nA for emitter bias configuration.", "opta": "42.53, 0.85 \u03bcA", "optb": "40.91, 0.58 \u03bcA", "optc": "40.91, 0.58 \u03bcA", "optd": "41.10, 0.39 \u03bcA", "ans": "A", "explanation": "SICO = (1 + \u03b2).\n\n 51. = 42.53\n\n\u0394IC = (SICO).\u0394ICO\n\n= 42.53 x 19.9 nA\n\n= 0.85 \u03bcA."}, {"question": "A periodic voltage has following value for equal time intervals changing suddenly from one value to next... 0, 5, 10, 20, 50, 60, 50, 20, 10, 5, 0, -5, -10 etc. Then rms value of the waveform is", "opta": "31 V", "optb": "32 V", "optc": "insufficient data", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "RMS value = 965 = 31.064 Volt."}, {"question": "Work function of oxide coated cathode is much lower than that of tungsten cathode.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Therefore emission current from oxide coated cathode is more."}, {"question": "The word enhancement mode is associated with", "opta": "tunnel diode", "optb": "MOSFET", "optc": "JFET", "optd": "photo diode", "ans": "B", "explanation": "MOSFET may be depletion mode or enhancement mode."}, {"question": "In which region of a CE bipolar transistor is collector current almost constant?", "opta": "Saturation region", "optb": "Active region", "optc": "Breakdown region", "optd": "Both saturation and active region", "ans": "B", "explanation": "It is used as amplifier when it operates in this region."}, {"question": "A p-n junction diode has", "opta": "low forward and high reverse resistance", "optb": "a non-linear v-i characteristics", "optc": "zero forward current till the forward voltage reaches cut in value", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "A p-n Junction has all these features."}, {"question": "Which of the following is true as regards photo emission?", "opta": "Velocity of emitted electrons is dependent on light intensity", "optb": "Rate of photo emission is inversely proportional to light intensity", "optc": "Maximum velocity of electron increases with decreasing wave length", "optd": "Both holes and electrons are produced", "ans": "C", "explanation": "As wavelength decreases, frequency increases and maximum velocity of electron increases."}, {"question": "The power dissipation in a transistor is the product of", "opta": "emitter current and emitter to base voltage", "optb": "emitter current and collector to emitter voltage", "optc": "collector current and collector to emitter voltage", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Maximum power dissipation occurs at collector junction."}, {"question": "The normal operation of JFET is", "opta": "constant voltage region", "optb": "constant current region", "optc": "both constant voltage and constant current regions", "optd": "either constant voltage or constant current region", "ans": "B", "explanation": "In major portion of drain characteristics ID is constant."}, {"question": "The minority carrier life time and diffusion constant in a semiconductor material are respectively 100 microsecond and 100 cm2/sec. The diffusion length is", "opta": "0.1 cm", "optb": "0.01 cm", "optc": "0.0141 cm", "optd": "1 cm", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Diffusion length = ."}, {"question": "In the following non planar graph number of independent loop equations are", "opta": "8", "optb": "12", "optc": "7", "optd": "5", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Number of independent loop equations are given by, \nL = B - N + 1\nwhere L : No. of loop equations\nB : No. of branches = 12\nN : No. of nodes = 8\nL = 12 - 8 + 1 = 5."}, {"question": "A transmission line has a characteristic impedance of 50 \u03a9 and a resistance of 0.1 \u03a9/m, if the line is distortion less, the attenuation constant (in Np/m) is", "opta": "500", "optb": "5", "optc": "0.014", "optd": "0.002", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Distortion less \na = RG and Z0 = RG \u2192 \n."}, {"question": "A certain 8 bit uniform quantization PCM system can accommodate a signal ranging from - 1 V to + V. The rms value of the signal is V . The signal to quantization noise ratio is:", "opta": "30 dB", "optb": "46.91 dB", "optc": "40 dB", "optd": "49.92 dB", "ans": "D", "explanation": "(SNR)dB = 1.76 + 6.02n\nn = 8\nThus (SNR)dB = 1.76 + 6.02 x 8 = 49.92 dB."}, {"question": "A rectangular waveguide, in dominant TE mode, has dimensions 10 cm x 15 cm. The cut off frequency is", "opta": "10 GHz", "optb": "1 GHz", "optc": "15 GHz", "optd": "25 GHz", "ans": "B", "explanation": "For TE10 mode"}, {"question": "A radar receiver has a noise figure of 10 dB at 300 K having a bandwidth of 2.5 MHz. The minimum power it can receive is", "opta": "3.45 x 10-15 W", "optb": "1.38 x 10-15 W", "optc": "7.5 x 10-15 W", "optd": "93.15 x 10-15 W", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Pm = kT0\u0394f(F - 1) = 93.15 x 10-15 W."}, {"question": "In the circuit shown, in switch S is open for a long time and is closed at t = 0. The current i(t) for t \u2265 0+ is", "opta": "i(t) = 0.5 - 0.125e-1000t A", "optb": "i(t) = 1.5 - 0.125e-1000t A", "optc": "i(t) = 0.5 - 0.5e-1000t A", "optd": "i(t) = 0.375e-1000t A", "ans": "A", "explanation": "i(f) = 0.5, i(i) = 0.75\ni(t) = Vr + (ii - ij)e-1/p = 0.5 - 0.125e-1000t ."}, {"question": "In a semiconductor material. The hole concentration is found to be 2 x 2.5 x 1015 cm-3. If mobility of carriers is 0.13 m2/ v-s. Then find the current density if electric field intensity is 3.62 x 10-19", "opta": "7.6237 x 10-4 A/cm2", "optb": "7.6237 x 10-5 A/cm2", "optc": "7.6237 x 10-3 A/cm2", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Current density J = \u03c3E \nWhere \u03c3 = conductivity \nGiven -> \u03bc = 0.13 m2/v-s = 0.13 x 104 cm2/V sec \nP = 2.25 x 1015/cm3 \nWe have, \u2234 ni = 1.5 x 1010 \nAlso n.p. = \n\u2234 n = /p \n \n \n= (1.6 x 10-19 x 0.13 x 104 x 2.25 x 1015) x \n= (0.468) (4.5 x 1015) \n\u03c3 = 2.106 x 1015 \u03bc/cm \nJ = \u03c3E \n\u2234 Current density = 2.106 x 1015 x 3.620 x 10-19 \n= 7.6237 x 10-4 A/m2."}, {"question": "Consider the system  with  and where p and q are arbitrary real numbers. Which of the following statements about the controllability of the system is true?", "opta": "The system is completely state controllable for any non zero values p and q", "optb": "Only p = 0 and q = 0 result in controllability", "optc": "The system is uncontrollable for all values of p and q", "optd": "We cannot conclude about controllability from the given data", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Use the condition of controllability."}, {"question": "A MOSFET has a threshold voltage of 1 V and oxide thickness of 500 x 10-8 [\u03b5r = 3.9; \u03b50 = 8.85 x 10-14 F/cm, q = 1.6 x 10-19 c]. The region under the gate is ion implanted for threshold voltage tailoring. The base and type of impant required to shift threshold voltage to - 1 V are __________ .", "opta": "8.6 x 1011/cm2, p-type", "optb": "8.6 x 1011/cm2, n-type", "optc": "0.86 x 109/cm2, p-type", "optd": "1.02 x 1012/cm2, n-type", "ans": "A", "explanation": "VT(new) = VT(odd) +\n \n= 6.903 x 10-8 \n\u2234  \n\u2234  \nfB = - 8.6 x 1011 \nThe threshold voltage is always negative for p-channel and hence implant is of p-type."}, {"question": "What is the propagation constant for air filled wave guide with dimensions a = 1.59\" and b = 0.795\" at 4.95 GHz?", "opta": "0.6698", "optb": "0.7698", "optc": "0.503", "optd": "0.6598", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Here, \na = 1.59'' = 40.386 mm = 4.04 cm\n\u2234 ."}, {"question": "Radiation resistance of an antenna is 54 &ohm; and loss resistance is 6 &ohm;. If antenna has power gain of 10, then directivity is:", "opta": "9", "optb": "11.11", "optc": "data not sufficient", "optd": "10", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Efficiency of antenna \n\nPower gain = 10\n\nThus directivity ."}, {"question": "If the power spectral density of stationary random process is a sine-squared function of frequency, the shape of its autocorrelation is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since autocorrelation function and power spectral density bears a Fourier transform relation, then since required in frequency domain will five rectangular convolutions in time domain thus it is triangular function."}, {"question": "The inverse of given Laplace transform is", "opta": "sin t", "optb": "cos t", "optc": "et", "optd": "e2t", "ans": "B", "explanation": "s = x2 - ex\n\nx(t) = cos t."}, {"question": "Consider the amplitude modulated (AM) signal Ac cos \u03c9ct + 2 cos \u03c9mt cos \u03c9ct For demodulating the signal using envelope detector, the minimum value of Ac should be", "opta": "2", "optb": "1", "optc": "0.5", "optd": "0", "ans": "A", "explanation": "AC cos \u03c9ct + 2 cos \u03c9mt cos \u03c9ct\nAC cos\u03c9ct\nfor envelope detection \u03bc < 1 &Rightarrow;  < 1 &Rightarrow; Ac should be at least-2."}, {"question": "In a 4 bit weighted resistor D/A converter, the resistor value corresponding to LSB is 32 k\u03a9. The resistor value corresponding to MSB will be", "opta": "32 K\u03a9", "optb": "16 K\u03a9", "optc": "8 K\u03a9", "optd": "4 K\u03a9", "ans": "D", "explanation": "2n - 1 R = 32 K&Omeg;\nn = 4\n&Rightarrow; 8R = 32\nR = 4 K\u03a9."}, {"question": "Find 'X' in the circuit below :f1(A, B, C, D) = \u03a3(6, 7, 13, 14);f2(A, B, C, D) = \u03a3(3, 6, 7);f3(A, B, C, D) = \u03a3(5, 6, 7, 14, 15)", "opta": "p(0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 15)", "optb": "0", "optc": "\u03a3(14)", "optd": "1", "ans": "C", "explanation": "f1(A, B, C, D) = \u2211(6, 7, 13, 14)\nf2(A, B, C, D) = \u2211(3, 6, 7)\nf1 \u2295 f2 = \u2211(3, 13, 14)\nf3 x (f1 \u2295 f2) = \u2211(14) = y\nX = f1 x y &Rightarrow; \u221114."}, {"question": "Suppose that the modulating signal is m(t) = 2cos (2pfmt) and the carrier signal is xC(t) = AC cos(2pfct), which one of the following is a conventional AM signal without over modulation?", "opta": "x(t) = Acm(t)cos(2pfct)", "optb": "x(t) = Ac [1 + m(t)]cos (2pfct)", "optc": "", "optd": "x(t) = Accos(2pfmt)cos(2pfct) + Acsin(2pfmt)sin(2pfct)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "(C) is without over modulation."}, {"question": "What are the values of Emax and Emin displayed on the oscilloscope, when a 1 kV P-P carries is modulated to 50%?", "opta": "2 kV, 0.5 kV", "optb": "1 kV, 0.5 kV", "optc": "0.75 kV, 0.25 kV", "optd": "0.5 kV, 1.5 kV", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Emax - Emin = 0.5 x 1 kV = 0.5 kV\n2Emax = 1.5 kVi, Emax = 0.75 kV\nEmin = 0.25 kV."}, {"question": "Consider the common emitter amplifier shown below with the following circuit parameters: \u03b2 = 100, gm = 0.3861 A/V, r0 = \u221e rp = 259 \u03a9, Rs = 1 k\u03a9, RB = 93 k\u03a9, RC = 250 \u03a9, RL = 1 kW, C1 = \u221e and C2 = 4.7mF.The resistance seen by the source Vs is", "opta": "258 \u03a9", "optb": "1258 \u03a9", "optc": "93 k\u03a9", "optd": "\u221e", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Zs = Rs + (RB || Brs)\nrc = 2.475 = 1.258 kV"}, {"question": "As the temperature increases the mobility of electrons __________ .", "opta": "decreases because the number of carries increases with increased collisions", "optb": "increases because the number of carries decreases with decreased collisions", "optc": "remains same", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Mobility of electrons \nm = 2.5 for electrons and 2.7 for holes in Si."}, {"question": "Consider the following Maximum energy of electrons liberated photoelectrically is independent of light intensityMaximum energy of electrons liberated photoelectrically varies nonlinearly with frequency of incident light.", "opta": "(1) is true and (2) is false", "optb": "(1) and (2) both are true", "optc": "(1) is false and (2) is true", "optd": "(1) and (2) both are false", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Statement (ii) is false because maximum energy of photons varies linearly with frequency of incident light. It can be shown as follows : \n \nF1 > F2 > F3 \nj = light intensity = constant \nPhotocurrent Vs Anode voltage with frequency and incident light as a parameter. \nThe light intensity is constant."}, {"question": "When phase-lag compensation is used in a system, then gain cross over frequency, bandwidth and undamped frequency are respectively", "opta": "Increased, Increased, Increased", "optb": "Increased, Increased, Decreased", "optc": "Increased, Decreased, Decreased", "optd": "Decreased, Decreased, Decreased", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Phase lag is delay between a correcting signal of control system and response to it."}, {"question": "The equivalent form of the logical expression ABC + A BC + ABC + ABC + AB C is", "opta": "C + (A \u2295 B)", "optb": "(A + B + C)(A + B + C)", "optc": "(A + B + C)(A + B + C)(A + B + C)", "optd": "(A + B + C)(A + B + C)(A + B + C)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "This can be solve by using Boolean identity but using k map it will be more easy\n\n(A + B + C) (A + B + C) (A + B + C)."}, {"question": "The gradient of any scalar field always yields __________ .", "opta": "a solenoidal field", "optb": "a conservative field", "optc": "an irrotational field", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Dot product is conservative. Gradient is nothing but dot product."}, {"question": "In a flash type ADC, employing 15 comparators resolution with 10 volts reference; is expected to be :", "opta": "0.625 V", "optb": "0.656 V", "optc": "0.525 V", "optd": "insufficient data", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since number of comparators = 2n - 1 = 15; \nThen number of bits are '4'\nResolution"}, {"question": "Consider the signal flow graph shown in figure below. The gain  is :", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "P1 = abcd\nL1 = be, L2 = cf, L3 = dg\n\u03941 = 1\n\n."}, {"question": "During transmission over a communicate channel, bit errors occur independently with probability . If a block of 3 bits are transmitted, the probability of at most one bit error is equal to", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "none", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Probability of no-error + probability one error\n\n."}, {"question": "If x1[n]  x1(z) with ROC = R1 and x2[n]  x2(z) with ROC = R2 then ROC for x1[n] + x2[n] will be __________ (where Ri \u2192 Region of convergence and x1[n] and x2[n] are causal).", "opta": "R1 \u2229 R2", "optb": "R1 \u222a R2", "optc": "(R1 \u222a R2) \u2229 (R1)", "optd": "(R1 \u2229 R2) \u222a (R1)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "R1 \u2229 R2, Suppose R1 for x1(n) be\n\nThen ROC for x1(n) + x2(n) \nR1 \u2229 R2 (R1 < R2)\nThen ROC for x1(n) + x2(n)\nR1 \u2229 R2(R1 < R2)"}, {"question": "Consider a unity feedback control system with open-loop transfer function  The steady state error of the system due to a unity step input is :", "opta": "zero", "optb": "K", "optc": "1/K", "optd": "infinite", "ans": "A", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "The analog signal given below is sampled at 1200 samples per second. m(t) = 2 sin 120 pt + 3 sin 240 pt + 4 sin 360 pt + 5 sin 480 pt + 6 sin 600 pt + 7 sin 720 pt. The folding (maximum) frequency is __________ .", "opta": "300 Hz", "optb": "360 Hz", "optc": "600 Hz", "optd": "480 Hz", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Folding frequency (max.) = = 600 Hz."}, {"question": "If the system T.F. is  The differential equation representing the system is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "(s3 + 2s2 + 5s + 6)y(s) = (s2 + 4) x (s)\ns3y(s) + 2s2y(s) + 5sy(s) + 6y(s) = s2 x (s) + 4 x (s) \nReplacing s by  and y(s) by y(t) and x(s) by x(t) we get \ny(t) + 2y(t) + 5y(t) + 6y(t)\n = x(t) + 4x(t) \n + 2 + 5 + 6 =  + 4x \nThis is required differential equation."}, {"question": "In the circuit below, delay of the EXOR and ANDLogic gates are 20 \u03bcs and 10 \u03bcs respectively, then the wave y' and y (with initial condition y = 1) will be :", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since y is at logic '1' initially, y' must be at logic '1'. \nAlso, one input of the EXOR gate is tied to zero therefore 'f' will be directly transferred to the output. \nThe logic gates will introduce gate delays which will lead to the answer ."}, {"question": "The antenna current of an AM transmitter is 8 A, when only the carrier is sent, but it increases to 8.93 A when the carrier is modulated by a single sine wave. Determine the antenna current when the percent of modulation changes to 0.8", "opta": "9.19 A", "optb": "9.91 A", "optc": "10.56 A", "optd": "8.61 A", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Ic = 8 A \nm = 0.8 \n\n \n= 8 x 1.149 = 9.19 A."}, {"question": "A noiseless 3 KHz channel can transmit binary at the rate __________ .", "opta": "12000 bps", "optb": "10000 bps", "optc": "6000 bps", "optd": "3000 bps", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Maximum data rate for noiseless channel is given by Nyquist Theorem \n= 2H log2 V bits/sec \nV - discrete levels (Here Binary i.e. 2) \nH - Bandwidth \n\u2234 Maximum data rate = 2H log2 V \n= 2(3 KHz) log2 2 = 2 x 3 x 103 x 1 \n= 6 x 103 = 6000 bps."}, {"question": "Find Vx Vy Vz", "opta": "Vx = -6 Vy = 3 Vz = -3", "optb": "Vx = -6 Vy = -3 Vz = 1", "optc": "Vx = 6 Vy = 3 Vz = 3", "optd": "Vx = 6 Vy = 1 Vz = 3", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Apply Mesh analysis\n\nApply KVL to mesh 2\n-2 + Vy + 1 = 0\n\u2234 Vy = 1\nApply KVL to mesh 1\n\u2234 -8 + Vx + 2 = 0\n\u2234 Vx = 6 V\nApply KVL to mesh 3\n-1 + Vz -2 = 0\n\u2234 Vz = 3 V."}, {"question": "If x[n]  then the sequence x[n] is", "opta": "non-periodic", "optb": "periodic", "optc": "depends on n", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Consider \nNumber of samples per period = 10p\nThis is not a rational number. Hence signal is non periodic."}, {"question": "The impulse response and the excitation function of a linear time invariant causal system are shown in figure (a) and (b) respectively. The output of the system at t = 2 sec is equal to", "opta": "0", "optb": "2", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The area of the shaded region \n."}, {"question": "Consider a stable and causal system with impulse response h(t) and system function H(S). Suppose H(S) is rational, contains a pole at S = - 2, and does not have a zero at the origin. The location of all other poles and zero is unknown for each of the following statements. Let us determine whether statement is true or false. f[h(t) e-3t] convergesh(t) has finite durationH(s) = H(- s) Choose correct option.", "opta": "1 - True, 2 - False, 3 - True, 4 - False", "optb": "1 - False, 2 - False, 3 - False, 4 - True", "optc": "1 - False, 2 - False, 3 - False, 4 - False", "optd": "1 - True, 2 - can't say, 3 - True, 4 - can't say", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Statement 1 is false, since f{h(t)e3t} corresponds to the value of the Laplace transform of h(t) at s = 3. \nIf this converges, it implies that s = - 3 is in the ROC. \nA casual and stable system must always have its ROC to the right of all its poles. However, s = - 3 is not to the right of the pole at s = - 2. \nStatement 2 is false, because it is equivalent to stating that H(0) = 0. This contradicts the fact that H(s) does not have a zero at the origin. \nStatement 3 is false. If h(t) is of finite duration, then if its Laplace transform has any points in its ROC, ROC must be the entire s-plane. \nHowever, this is not consistent with H(s) having a pole at s = - 2. \nStatement 4 is false. If it were true, then H(s) has a pole at s = - 2, it must also have a pole at s = 2. \nThis is inconsistent with the fact that all the poles of a causal and stable system must be in the left half of the s-plane."}, {"question": "The specific gravity of tungsten is 13.8 and its atomic weight is 184.0 Assume that there are two free elements per atom. Then the Fermi level or characteristic energy for the crystal in eV will be", "opta": "8.95 eV", "optb": "-8.95 eV", "optc": "7.326 eV", "optd": "-7.326 eV", "ans": "C", "explanation": "A quantity of any substance equal to its molecular weight in grams is a mole of that substance contains the same number of molecules as one mole of any other substance. This Avogadro's number and equals 6.02 x 1023 molecules per mole. Thus\n\n\n \n= 9.03 x 1028 electrons/m3\nSince for tungsten the atomic and the molecular weights are the same. Therefore for tungsten \nEF = 3.64 x 10-19(\u03b7)2/3 \n= 3.64 x 10- 19(9.03 x 1028)2/3 \nEF = 7.326 eV."}, {"question": "An air-filled rectangular waveguide has dimensions 8cm x 10cm . The phase velocity of guided wave at frequency of 3 GHz for TE10 mode is", "opta": "1.5 x 108 m/s", "optb": "5.5 x 108 m/s", "optc": "3.46 x 108 m/s", "optd": "0.18 x 107 m/s", "ans": "C", "explanation": "\u2234 VP = 3.46 x 108 m/s."}, {"question": "For a = - 1, find the value of V2", "opta": "\u221e", "optb": "0", "optc": "V1", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "V1 = i1R1 + i2R2 \ni1 + ai1 = i2 \nV2 = i2R2\n\n\n \nPutting a = - 1 \n = 0 V."}, {"question": "A unity-feedback control system has the open loop transfer function . If the input system is a unit ramp, the steady state error will be", "opta": "0", "optb": "0.5", "optc": "2", "optd": "infinity", "ans": "C", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "For a given voltage, four heating coils will produce maximum heat when connected", "opta": "all in parallel", "optb": "all in series", "optc": "with two parallel pairs in series", "optd": "one pair in parallel with the other two in series", "ans": "A", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "Denominator polynomial of a transfer function of certain network is: s3 + s2 + 2s + 24 Then the network is:", "opta": "stable", "optb": "oscillatory", "optc": "unstable", "optd": "depends on numerator polynomial", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Routh array\n\n\n\nThere is negative number present in first column. Thus network is unstable."}, {"question": "A TV picture is to be transmitted over a channel of 6 MHz bandwidth at a 35 dB S/N ratio. The capacity of the channel is", "opta": "50 Mbps", "optb": "100 Mbps", "optc": "36 Mbps", "optd": "72 Mbps", "ans": "D", "explanation": "W = B = Bandwidth\n\nC = 6 x 106 x 12 = 72 Mbps."}, {"question": "The ratio of the diffusion coefficient in a semiconductor has the units", "opta": "V-1", "optb": "em.V-1", "optc": "V.cm-1", "optd": "V.s", "ans": "A", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "Consider the probability density f(x) = ae-b|x| where x is a random variable whose allowable values range from x = - \u221e to x = + \u221e. P(1 \u2264 x \u2264 2)", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "(e-b - e-2b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "P(x) =  ae-b|x|dx\nto get  apply aebxdx + ae-bxdx, \nwe get  = ."}, {"question": "The amplitude of a pair of composite sinusoidal signal y(n) = x1(n) + x2(n) with x1(n) = sin (5pn) x2(n) = 3 sin (5pn) is __________ .", "opta": "2", "optb": "3", "optc": "4", "optd": "1", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Amplitude = ."}, {"question": "The amplifier circuit shown below uses a silicon transistor. The capacitors Cc and CE can be assumed to be short at signal frequency and the effect of output resistance r0 can be ignored. If CE is disconnected from the circuit, which one of the following statements is TRUE?", "opta": "The input resistance Ri increases and the magnitude of voltage gain Av decreases", "optb": "The input resistance Ri decreases and the magnitude of voltage gain Av decreases", "optc": "Both input resistance Ri and the magnitude of voltage gain Av decrease", "optd": "Both input resistance Ri and the magnitude of voltage gain Av increase", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Given circuit after removing CE will behave as current-series feedback. \nOverall voltage gain will decrease as feedback signal comes into picture and since it is current-series feedback, input impedance increases."}, {"question": "A n-channel JFET has IDSS = 2 mA, Gate to source voltage VGS = - 2 V and trans-conductance is 0.5 mW then pinch-off voltage is __________ .", "opta": "- 2 V", "optb": "2 V", "optc": "- 4 V", "optd": "4 V", "ans": "C", "explanation": "\u2234  \n\u2234  = - 8VP - 16 \n\u2234  + 8VP + 16 = 0 \n\u2234 (VP + 4)2 = 0 \n\u2234 VP = -4 V."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I  List II A.RC coupled amplifier1.Very low driftB.Tuned amplifier2.Flat frequency response from zero frequency onwardsC.Chopper stabilized amplifier3.Flat frequency response with upper and lower cut off frequencyD.DC amplifier4.Peak in gain frequency response", "opta": "A-4, B-3, C-1, D-2", "optb": "A-3, B-4, C-2, D-1", "optc": "A-3, B-4, C-1, D-2", "optd": "A-4, B-3, C-2, D-1", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: Microwave Measuring Instruments Measurements EffectedA.Bolometer1.Reflection coefficientsB.VSWR meter2.Half power beam widthsC.Cavity wave meter3.Microwave powerD.Pattern recorder4.Microwave frequency", "opta": "A-2, B-1, C-4, D-3", "optb": "A-3, B-1, C-4, D-2", "optc": "A-2, B-4, C-1, D-3", "optd": "A-3, B-4, C-1, D-2", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I (Circuit)  List II (Characteristics) A.Darlington pair1.uses pnp and npn transistors used as power amplifierB.CB amplifier2.Voltage gain nearly 1 and high input impedanceC.Cascade amplifier3.low input impedance used for high frequency isolation", "opta": "A-1, B-2, C-3", "optb": "A-2, B-3, C-1", "optc": "A-2, B-1, C-3", "optd": "A-3, B-1, C-2", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I (FET Parameters)  List II (Typical Values) A.gm for JFET1.25 kWB.rd for JFET2.0.01 siemenC.rd for MOSFET3.0.5 mWD.gg for JFET4.10-8 siemen", "opta": "A-1, B-2, C-3, D-4", "optb": "A-2, B-3, C-1, D-4", "optc": "A-4, B-2, C-3, D-1", "optd": "A-4, B-3, C-2, D-1", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I  List II A.Word wrap1.interleaved execution of two or more programs by the same computerB.Client2.automatically moves a word to the next line if it does not fit in the current lineC.Multitasking3.an application receiving dataD.Landscape4.orientation of worksheet", "opta": "A-1, B-2, C-3, D-4", "optb": "A-2, B-3, C-4, D-1", "optc": "A-4, B-3, C-2, D-1", "optd": "A-2, B-3, C-1, D-4", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I (Camera pick up tubes)  List II (Developed by) A.CCD charger1.ToshibaB.New vicon2.PhilipsC.Plumbicon3.MatushitaD.Chalnicon4.RCA", "opta": "A-3, B-4, C-1, D-2", "optb": "A-4, B-3, C-2, D-1", "optc": "A-4, B-3, C-1, D-2", "optd": "A-1, B-2, C-3, D-4", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I (DOS commands)  List II (Meaning) A.ATTRIB1.Displays all directories and subdirectoriesB.SCAN DISK2.Moves files to another directorC.MOVE3.Checks the status of discD.TREE4.Hides a file", "opta": "A-1, B-2, C-3, D-4", "optb": "A-3, B-4, C-2, D-1", "optc": "A-2, B-3, C-4, D-1", "optd": "A-4, B-3, C-2, D-1", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I  List II A.1.ZeroB.2.0.2C.3.ActuatorD.4.infinity", "opta": "A-1, B-2, C-3, D-4", "optb": "A-1, B-3, C-2, D-4", "optc": "A-4, B-3, C-2, D-1", "optd": "A-4, B-2, C-3, D-1", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I  List II A.Horn antenna1.High directivityB.Parabolic antenna2.Very high directivityC.Lens antenna3.Moderate directivity", "opta": "A-1, B-2, C-3", "optb": "A-3, B-2, C-1", "optc": "A-3, B-1, C-2", "optd": "A-1, B-3, C-2", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I  List II A.TV1.1 kHzB.Radio2.3 kHzC.Telephony3.9 kHzD.Telegraphy4.5 MHz", "opta": "A-4, B-1, C-2", "optb": "A-4, B-3, C-2", "optc": "A-2, B-1, C-3", "optd": "A-1, B-2, C-3", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I (fk) List II [F(z)] A.11.B.kn2.(1 - az-1)-1C.ak3.- ln (1 - z-1)-1D.4.(1 - z-1)-1", "opta": "A-1, B-4, C-2, D-3", "optb": "A-2, B-3, C-1, D-4", "optc": "A-4, B-1, C-2, D-3", "optd": "A-1, B-4, C-3, D-2", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I  List II A.p type semiconductor1.siliconB.n type semiconductor2.holes are majority carriersC.Intrinsic semiconductor3.electrons are majority carriersD.Tungsten4.is a metal", "opta": "A-2, B-3, C-1, D-4", "optb": "A-1, B-2, C-3, D-4", "optc": "A-4, B-3, C-2, D-1", "optd": "A-3, B-1, C-2, D-4", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I  List II A.Resistance1.M-1L-2T2I2B.Inductance2.ML2T-2I-2C.Capacitance3.M-1L-2T4I2D.Reluctance4.ML2T-3I-2", "opta": "A-1, B-2, C-3, D-4", "optb": "A-2, B-1, C-3, D-4", "optc": "A-4, B-2, C-3, D-1", "optd": "A-2, B-4, C-3, D-1", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I (Octal)  List II (Decimal number)A.351.53B.652.62C.543.29D.764.44", "opta": "A-4, B-3, C-2, D-1", "optb": "A-1, B-2, C-3, D-4", "optc": "A-2, B-3, C-1, D-4", "optd": "A-3, B-1, C-4, D-2", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I (Instrument)  List II (Measured quantity) A.Hot wire1.only voltageB.PMMC2.phaseC.Electrostatic3.true RMS valueD.Lock in Amplifier4.dc value", "opta": "A-3, B-2, C-1, D-4", "optb": "A-1, B-4, C-2, D-3", "optc": "A-3, B-4, C-1, D-2", "optd": "A-2, B-3, C-4, D-1", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I (Laws of Boolean)  List II (Relation algebra) A.Distributive law1.x + x = xB.DeMorgans law2.x(y + z) = xy + xzC.Idempotent law3.(x) = xD.Involution law4.(x + y) = xy", "opta": "A-1, B-2, C-3, D-4", "optb": "A-2, B-4, C-1, D-3", "optc": "A-3, B-4, C-1, D-2", "optd": "A-4, B-1, C-2, D-3", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I (Library function in Pascal)  List II (Type of argument)A.ROUND X1.X in radiansB.ABS X2.X realC.SQR X3.X real or integerD.SIN X", "opta": "A-2, B-3, C-3, D-1", "optb": "A-2, B-3, C-1, D-3", "optc": "A-3, B-2, C-2, D-1", "optd": "A-2, B-3, C-2, D-1", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I f(t) List II F (s)A.cos \u03c9t1.B.sin \u03c9t2.C.cosh \u03c9t3.D.sinh \u03c9t4.", "opta": "A-1, B-3, C-2, D-4", "optb": "A-4, B-2, C-1, D-3", "optc": "A-4, B-3, C-1, D-2", "optd": "A-3, B-2, C-1, D-4", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I  List II A.Resistance1.Current noiseB.Diode2.Partition noiseC.Triode3.Shot noiseD.p-n junction4.Atmospheric noise  5.Johnson noise", "opta": "A-5, B-3, C-2, D-1", "optb": "A-1, B-2, C-3, D-5", "optc": "A-3, B-5, C-1, D-2", "optd": "A-3, B-5, C-2, D-1", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I (Command in WORD)  List II (Meaning) A.END1.The bar displays the current position of cursorB.HOME2.Moves cursor to the beginning of current lineC.Status3.Moves cursor to end of document", "opta": "A-1, B-2, C-3", "optb": "A-3, B-1, C-2", "optc": "A-2, B-3, C-1", "optd": "A-3, B-2, C-1", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I (Operator in C)  List II (Priority of Operation) A.!1.1B.< >2.2C.\u22173.3D.=4.4", "opta": "A-1, B-2, C-3, D-4", "optb": "A-1, B-3, C-2, D-4", "optc": "A-4, B-3, C-2, D-1", "optd": "A-3, B-2, C-1, D-4", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I (Oscillator)  List II (Features) A.Wien Bridge1.RF oscillator, uses two inductors and one capacitorB.Colpitt's2.LC oscillator for radio frequencies uses three capacitances and one inductanceC.Hartley3.RC oscillator for audio frequenciesD.Clapp4.RF oscillator, uses two capacitances and one inductance", "opta": "A-2, B-1, C-4, D-3", "optb": "A-2, B-4, C-1, D-3", "optc": "A-3, B-4, C-1, D-2", "optd": "A-3, B-1, C-4, D-2", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I (Symbol in java)  List II (Meaning)A.&1.Logical ANDB.\u02c62.ANDC.| |3.XORD.& &4.Logical OR", "opta": "A-1, B-2, C-3, D-4", "optb": "A-2, B-3, C-1, D-4", "optc": "A-4, B-2, C-3, D-1", "optd": "A-2, B-3, C-4, D-1", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I  List II A.RT1.A = DB.Rh2.h12 = h21C.ST3.AD - BC = 1D.Sh4.h21 = - h21  5.B = C  6.\u0394h = 1", "opta": "A-3, B-4, C-1, D-6", "optb": "A-3, B-2, C-5, D-4", "optc": "A-5, B-4, C-1, D-2", "optd": "A-5, B-4, C-1, D-6", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I (Network parameter)  List II (Measured under open-circuit conditions) A.Z111.B.A2.C.C3.D.Z224.", "opta": "A-1, B-4, C-2, D-3", "optb": "A-3, B-4, C-2, D-1", "optc": "A-1, B-2, C-4, D-3", "optd": "A-3, B-2, C-4, D-1", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I  List II A.SSB Modulation1.Transmission lineB.\u0394 . B = 02.Hilbert transformC.Model dispersion3.Faraday's law  4.Absence of magnetic monopoles  5.Waveguides  6.Phase locked loop", "opta": "A-1, B-3, C-5", "optb": "A-5, B-4, C-2", "optc": "A-6, B-4, C-5", "optd": "A-2, B-4, C-5", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I  List II A.1.B.2.C.3.D.4.", "opta": "A-1, B-2, C-3, D-4", "optb": "A-3, B-4, C-2, D-1", "optc": "A-4, B-3, C-2, D-1", "optd": "A-3, B-4, C-1, D-2", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I (type of controller) List II (Operation)A.Pneumatic controller1.Flexible operationB.Hydraulic controller2.High torque high speed operationC.Electronic controller3.Fire and explosion proof operation", "opta": "A-1, B-3, C-2", "optb": "A-1, B-2, C-3", "optc": "A-3, B-1, C-2", "optd": "A-3, B-2, C-1", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I f(t)  List II F(s) A.t1.B.eat2.C.u(t)3.D.cos \u03c9t4.", "opta": "A-1, B-3, C-2, D-4", "optb": "A-1, B-4, C-2, D-3", "optc": "A-2, B-4, C-1, D-3", "optd": "A-4, B-3, C-1, D-2", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I  List II A.DIAC1.B.TRIAC2.C.SIT3.D.LASCR4.", "opta": "A-4, B-2, C-3, D-1", "optb": "A-1, B-2, C-3, D-4", "optc": "A-1, B-4, C-2, D-3", "optd": "A-3, B-2, C-1, D-4", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I (Comm.services) List II (Bandwidth) A.AM broadcast1.10 kHzB.Telephone2.4 kHzC.wide-band FM3.200 kHzD.TV4.7 MHz", "opta": "A-1, B-2, C-3, D-4", "optb": "A-3, B-4, C-1, D-2", "optc": "A-1, B-4, C-3, D-2", "optd": "A-3, B-2, C-1, D-4", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I (Logic family)  List II (Characteristic of logic family) A.TTL1.Maximum power ConsumptionB.ECL2.Highest Packing DensityC.NMOS3.Least Power ConsumptionD.CMOS4.Saturated Logic", "opta": "A-1, B-4, C-2, D-3", "optb": "A-1, B-4, C-3, D-2", "optc": "A-4, B-1, C-2, D-3", "optd": "A-4, B-1, C-3, D-2", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I  List II A.Penetration frequency1.Lowest frequency at which charged particles spiral in fixed magnetic fieldB.Optimum working frequency2.Same as critical and frequencyC.Gyro frequency3.Highest frequency of radio waves that can be usedD.Maximum usable frequency4.The most effective frequency for ionosphere propagation of radio waves", "opta": "A-2, B-4, C-1, D-3", "optb": "A-4, B-1, C-3, D-2", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I  List II A.Synchro1.AmplifierB.Amplidyne2.ActuatorC.Servo3.CompensatorD.RC network4.Transducer", "opta": "A-1, B-2, C-3, D-4", "optb": "A-4, B-3, C-2, D-1", "optc": "A-3, B-2, C-4, D-1", "optd": "A-4, B-1, C-2, D-3", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I  List II A.Silicon1.is trivalentB.Arsenic2.rarely used as semiconductorC.Indium3.is pentavalentD.Germanium4.intrinsic semiconductor", "opta": "A-1, B-2, C-3, D-4", "optb": "A-4, B-3, C-2, D-1", "optc": "A-4, B-3, C-1, D-2", "optd": "A-2, B-1, C-3, D-4", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I  List II A.VOH(min)1.2.4 VB.VIH(min)2.1.5 VC.VOL(max)3.0.4 V  4.2.0 V  5.0.8 V", "opta": "A-1, B-3, C-4", "optb": "A-1, B-4, C-3", "optc": "A-5, B-4, C-3", "optd": "A-1, B-5, C-2", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I  List II A.n Channel JFET1.B.p Channel JFET2.C.Depletion MOSFET3.D.Enhancement MOSFET4.", "opta": "A-4, B-3, C-2, D-1", "optb": "A-1, B-3, C-4, D-2", "optc": "A-3, B-4, C-1, D-2", "optd": "A-2, B-4, C-3, D-1", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I  List II A.Ring modulator1.Clock recoveryB.VCO2.Demodulation of FMC.Foster Seeley discriminator3.Frequency conversionD.Mixer4.Summing of two points  5.Generation of FM  6.Generation of DSB-SC", "opta": "A-1, B-3, C-2, D-4", "optb": "A-6, B-5, C-2, D-3", "optc": "A-6, B-1, C-3, D-2", "optd": "A-5, B-6, C-1, D-3", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I  List II A.Serial Binary adder1.(2n - 1)tpdB.Ripple carry adder2.(n - 1)tpdC.Carry look ahead binary adder3.Operation time independent of size  4.6tpd for 4 bit carry look ahead adder", "opta": "A-2, B-1, C-3", "optb": "A-2, B-1, C-4", "optc": "A-1, B-2, C-4", "optd": "A-1, B-2, C-3", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I  List II A.Zener diode1.B.Tunnel diode2.C.Schottky diode3.D.Diode4.", "opta": "A-1, B-3, C-2, D-4", "optb": "A-2, B-3, C-1, D-4", "optc": "A-4, B-3, C-2, D-1", "optd": "A-3, B-2, C-4, D-1", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I (Instrument)  List II (Parameters) A.Moving coil galvanometer1.High inertia, soft spring controlB.Ballistic galvanometer2.No control, high dampingC.Vibration galvanometer3.Soft spring control, critical dampingD.Moving coil flux meter4.Low inertia, tuned spring control", "opta": "A-4, B-2, C-3, D-1", "optb": "A-1, B-3, C-2, D-4", "optc": "A-2, B-1, C-4, D-3", "optd": "A-3, B-1, C-4, D-2", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I  List II A.Output of signal generator1.ModulatedB.Error signal from a synchro2.DigitalC.Output of a JK flip flop3.AnalogD.Signal received by radar4.Stoichastic", "opta": "A-1, B-3, C-2, D-4", "optb": "A-3, B-1, C-2, D-4", "optc": "A-3, B-1, C-4, D-2", "optd": "A-1, B-3, C-4, D-2", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I (Types of transmission structure)  List II (Modes of propagation)A.Strip line1.Quasi TEMB.Hollow rectangular waveguide2.Pure TEMC.Microstrip3.TE/TMD.Corrugated waveguide4.Hybrid", "opta": "A-2, B-1, C-3, D-4", "optb": "A-4, B-1, C-3, D-2", "optc": "A-2, B-3, C-1, D-4", "optd": "A-4, B-3, C-1, D-2", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I (\u03bcP)  List II (Number of bits in register) A.80851.32 bitB.80862.16 bitC.680003.8/16 bit", "opta": "A-1, B-2, C-3", "optb": "A-2, B-3, C-1", "optc": "A-3, B-2, C-1", "optd": "A-3, B-1, C-2", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I (DOS commands)  List II (Meaning) A.DBLSPACE1.Deletes a director and its sub-directoriesB.MEM2.Displays the amount of used and free memoryC.SYS3.Put a copy of DOS on diskD.DELTREE4.Compresses files to increase the storage capacity of disc", "opta": "A-4, B-3, C-2, D-1", "optb": "A-2, B-3, C-4, D-1", "optc": "A-4, B-2, C-3, D-1", "optd": "A-1, B-2, C-3, D-4", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I  List II A.Zener diode1.used in seven segment displayB.Tunnel diode2.used in voltage regulator circuitsC.LED3.used is solar energy utilizationD.Photovoltaic cell4.used in digital circuits", "opta": "A-1, B-3, C-2, D-4", "optb": "A-2, B-3, C-1, D-4", "optc": "A-2, B-4, C-1, D-3", "optd": "A-3, B-2, C-4, D-1", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I  List II A.Reactance theorem1.FosterB.Driving point impedance2.BartlettC.Continued fraction expansion3.CauerD.Bisection Theorem4.Positive real function", "opta": "A-1, B-4, C-3, D-2", "optb": "A-1, B-2, C-3, D-4", "optc": "A-2, B-3, C-1, D-4", "optd": "A-3, B-4, C-2, D-1", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I (Operator)  List II (Description) A.& &1.AssignmentB.| |2.Logical ANDC.=3.Logical OR", "opta": "A-1, B-2, C-3", "optb": "A-2, B-3, C-1", "optc": "A-3, B-2, C-1", "optd": "A-1, B-3, C-2", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I  List II A.shift Register1.Frequency divisionB.Counter2.Addressing in memory chipsC.Decoder3.Serial to parallel Data conversion", "opta": "A-3, B-2, C-1", "optb": "A-3, B-1, C-2", "optc": "A-2, B-1, C-3", "optd": "A-1, B-2, C-2", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Match the following: List I  List II A.DMA controller1.Interface between computer and video display adapterB.CKT controller2.Used to read data directly from disk into directly memoryC.Interrupt controller3.Supervises the operation of control signal", "opta": "A-1, B-2, C-3", "optb": "A-2, B-3, C-1", "optc": "A-3, B-2, C-1", "optd": "A-2, B-1, C-3", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Diamond is a paramagnetic material.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Diamond is diamagnetic."}, {"question": "Which capacitor-store higher amount of energy?", "opta": "Air capacitor", "optb": "Paper capacitor", "optc": "Mica capacitor", "optd": "Plastic film capacitor", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Energy stored is proportional to capacitance and capacitance is proportional to permittivity."}, {"question": "Above ferroelectric curie temperature, spontaneous polarization in ferroelectric materials becomes stronger.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Spontaneous polarization vanishes above ferro-electric Curie temperature."}, {"question": "In paramagnetic materials", "opta": "permanent magnetic dipoles exist but the interaction between neighbouring dipoles is negligible", "optb": "permanent magnetic dipole do not exist", "optc": "permanent magnetic dipoles exist and the interaction between neighbouring dipoles is very strong", "optd": "permanent magnetic dipole moment may or may not exist", "ans": "A", "explanation": "In paramagnetic materials interaction between neighbouring dipoles is negligible."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  Atomic number of sodium is 11.Reason (R):  Sodium has a body centred cubic lattice.", "opta": "Both A and R are true and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are true but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true but R is false", "optd": "A is false but R is true", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Atomic number is not dependent on lattice structure."}, {"question": "The conductivity of intrinsic semiconductor is given by", "opta": "eni(\u03bcp - \u03bcn)", "optb": "eni(\u03bcp + \u03bcn)", "optc": "ni(\u03bcp + \u03bcn)", "optd": "ni(\u03bcp\u03bcn)", "ans": "B", "explanation": "For intrinsic semiconductor, \nConductivity = (Electron charge) x (Number of charge carriers) x (Sum of mobilities of holes and electrons)."}, {"question": "The core of a coil has a length of 10 cm. The self inductance is 8 mH. If the core length is doubled, all other quantities remaining the same, the self inductance will be", "opta": "32 mH", "optb": "16 mH", "optc": "8 mH", "optd": "4 mH", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Inductance is inversely proportional to the core length."}, {"question": "The minority carrier life time and diffusion constant in a semiconducting material are 100 \u03bcs and 100 cm2/s respectively. The diffusion length of carriers is", "opta": "0.1 cm", "optb": "0.01 cm", "optc": "0.0141 cm", "optd": "1 cm", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Diffusion length = sqrt(Carrier life time x Diffusion constant) = (100 x 10-6 x 100)0.5 = 0.1 cm."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  Electronic and Ionic polarization in a polyatomic gas are independent of temperature.Reason (R):  The orientation polarization is independent of temperature.", "opta": "Both A and R are true and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are true but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true but R is false", "optd": "A is false but R is true", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Orientation polarization is inversely proportional to temperature."}, {"question": "Two materials having temperature coefficients of 0.004 and 0.0004 respectively are joined in series. The overall temperature coefficient is likely to be", "opta": "0.08", "optb": "0.04", "optc": "0.001", "optd": "0.0001", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The overall temperature coefficient will be less than 0.004 and more than 0.0004."}, {"question": "The number of valence electrons in pentavalent impurity is", "opta": "5", "optb": "4", "optc": "3", "optd": "1", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Pentavalent means 5 valence electrons."}, {"question": "If the diameter of a wire is doubled, its current carrying capacity becomes", "opta": "one-fourth", "optb": "half", "optc": "twice", "optd": "four times", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Current carrying capacity depends on area of cross-section."}, {"question": "The law J = \u03c3E, where J is current density, \u03c3 is electrical conductivity and E is field strength is", "opta": "Ohm's law", "optb": "Gauss law", "optc": "Ampere's law", "optd": "Biot-Savart law", "ans": "A", "explanation": "It is another form of Ohm's law."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  Silicon is less sensitive to changes in temperature than germanium.Reason (R):  Cut in voltage in silicon is less than that in germanium.", "opta": "Both A and R are true and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are true but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true but R is false", "optd": "A is false but R is true", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Cut in voltage of silicon is higher than that in germanium."}, {"question": "Material which lack permanent magnetic dipoles are known as", "opta": "paramagnetic", "optb": "diamagnetic", "optc": "ferromagnetic", "optd": "ferrimagnetic", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Diamagnetic materials have no permanent magnetic diploes."}, {"question": "A parallel plate capacitor has its length, width and separation doubled. It fringing effects are neglected, to keep the capacitance same, the dielectric constant must be", "opta": "halved", "optb": "kept the same", "optc": "doubled", "optd": "made 4 times", "ans": "A", "explanation": ". When dimensions are changed, A become four times and d becomes twice.\nSince \u22080 is constant, \u2208r must be halved to keep C constant."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  In imperfect capacitors, the current does not lead the applied ac voltage by 90\u00b0.Reason (R):  When subjected to ac fields, the dielectric constant can be expressed as \u2208'r - j\u2208\"r.", "opta": "Both A and R are true and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are true but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true but R is false", "optd": "A is false but R is true", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Imaginary part of \u2208r gives rise to absorption of energy by the material from alternating field. \nHence current does not lead the voltage by 90\u00b0."}, {"question": "In atomic physics, a state with l = 0 is called p state.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The state with l = 0 is called s state."}, {"question": "If a sample of germanium and a sample of silicon have the same impurity density and are kept at room temperature", "opta": "both will have equal value of resistivity", "optb": "both will have equal negative resistivity", "optc": "resistivity of germanium will be higher than that of silicon", "optd": "resistivity of silicon will be higher than that of germanium", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Resistivity of silicon is more than that of germanium."}, {"question": "When an electric field E is applied to solid and liquid insulating materials, the internal field Ei acting at the location of atom is such that", "opta": "Ei = E", "optb": "Ei > E", "optc": "Ei < E", "optd": "Ei may be equal to or less than E", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The actual field seen by an atom is larger than applied field."}, {"question": "Which element exhibits the property of inertia?", "opta": "Resistance", "optb": "Capacitance", "optc": "Inductance", "optd": "Both resistance and inductance", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Inductance opposes rise and decay of current. Hence it has the property of inertia."}, {"question": "For a permanent magnetic material", "opta": "the residual induction and coercive field should be large", "optb": "the residual induction and coercive field should be small", "optc": "area of hysteresis loop should be small", "optd": "initial relative permeability should be high", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Materials suitable for permanent magnet have large hysteresis loop.\nHence residual and coercive field are large."}, {"question": "In a coaxial cable, braided copper is used for", "opta": "conductor", "optb": "shield", "optc": "dielectric", "optd": "jacket", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Braided material is used for shield."}, {"question": "The hysteresis phenomenon in ferromagnetic materials exists at all temperatures.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Hysteresis phenomenon exists below ferromagnetic curie temperature."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  Magnetic susceptibility of diamagnetic materials is much less than that of paramagnetic materials.Reason (R):  For diamagnetic as well as paramagnetic materials, \u03bcr is nearly equal to 1.", "opta": "Both A and R are true and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are true but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true but R is false", "optd": "A is false but R is true", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Magnetic susceptibility = (\u03bcr - 1)H. \nFor diamagnetic and paramagnetic materials magnetic susceptibility is very very small and \u03bcr = 1."}, {"question": "The attraction between the nucleus and valence electron of copper atom is", "opta": "zero", "optb": "weak", "optc": "strong", "optd": "either zero or strong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The valence electron, in copper atom, can be easily detached from nucleus."}, {"question": "If the temperature of an extrinsic semiconductor is increased so that the intrinsic carrier concentration is doubled, then", "opta": "the majority carrier density is doubled", "optb": "the minority carrier density is doubled", "optc": "the minority carrier density becomes 4 times the original value", "optd": "both the majority and minority carrier densities double", "ans": "D", "explanation": "As the intrinsic carrier concentration is doubled, the concentration of both electrons and holes is doubled."}, {"question": "There is no hysteresis phenomenon is any dielectric material.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Hysteresis phenomenon exists in dielectic materials."}, {"question": "The units of \u03bc0 and \u03bcr are", "opta": "H/m for both", "optb": "H/m for \u03bcr and no units for \u03bc0", "optc": "H/m for \u03bc0 and no units for \u03bcr", "optd": "Wb/m for \u03bc0 and no units for \u03bcr", "ans": "C", "explanation": "\u03bcr is only a numeric."}, {"question": "In metals the valence electron wave functions are strongly perturbed by the presence of neighbouring atoms.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "In a metal valence electrons are shared by all atoms."}, {"question": "For a paramagnetic material, susceptiblity increases with increasing temperature.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Susceptibility \u221d ."}, {"question": "Hydrogen is used in", "opta": "large size transformers", "optb": "MCB", "optc": "large size generators", "optd": "circuit breakers", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Modem large size generators have hydrogen cooling."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  Ferroelectric materials have spontaneous polarization.Reason (R):  Above curie temperature, \u2208 =  for ferro-electric materials.", "opta": "Both A and R are true and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are true but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true but R is false", "optd": "A is false but R is true", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Both A and R are correct. Spontaneous polarization vanishes above ferroelectric curie temperature."}, {"question": "If e is the charge of an electron, R is the radius of its orbit and \u03c9 is the angular velocity of electron, the magnetic dipole moment \u03bcm of the orbit is |\u03bcm| = e\u03c9R2.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "1 \u03bcm 1 = 0.5 e\u03c9r2."}, {"question": "If \u2208r' and \u2208r\" are the real and imaginary parts of complex dielectric constant \u2208r, and \u03b4 is the loss angle. Then", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "tan \u03b4 = \u2208'\u2208\"", "optd": "tan \u03b4 = 1 - \u2208'", "ans": "B", "explanation": "If \u2208r\" = 0, \u03b4 = 0."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  At a temperature of 1000 K, thermionic emission current is about 0.1 A/cm2 of surface.Reason (R):  Thermionic emission current is given by Ith = SA0 T2 e-Ew/kT.", "opta": "Both A and R are true and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are true but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true but R is false", "optd": "A is false but R is true", "ans": "A", "explanation": "If different values are substituted in the equation for Ith the value of emission current comes out to be about 0.1 A/cm2."}, {"question": "At room temperature, the current in intrinsic semiconductor is due to", "opta": "holes", "optb": "electrons", "optc": "ions", "optd": "holes and electrons", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Both electrons and holes contribute to flow of current in semiconductors."}, {"question": "Ferroelectric materials are those which", "opta": "cannot be polarized", "optb": "have a permanent polarization", "optc": "have ae equal to zero", "optd": "have \u03bcp = 0", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Ferroelectric materials have permanent polarization."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  Power loss in a conductor of resistance P = I2R.Reason (R):  When a conductor is carrying current with current density J as a result of applied field E, then heat developed/m3/ second = JE.", "opta": "Both A and R are true and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are true but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true but R is false", "optd": "A is false but R is true", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Heat developed depends an power loss."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  For Diamond, \u03bcr = 1Reason (R):  Diamond is a diamagnetic material.", "opta": "Both A and R are true and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are true but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true but R is false", "optd": "A is false but R is true", "ans": "A", "explanation": "For diamagnetic materials \u03bcr = 1."}, {"question": "If n denotes principal quantum number, the angular quantum number l = 0, 1... (n - 1).", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Angular quantum number determines the angular momentum of electron."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  In a perfect capacitor, the current density is given by \u03c9 \u22080E0\u2208'rcos(\u03c9t + 90\u00b0), where \u2208r' is real part of dielectric constant.Reason (R):  In a perfect capacitor, dielectric losses are zero.", "opta": "Both A and R are true and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are true but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true but R is false", "optd": "A is false but R is true", "ans": "A", "explanation": "If dielectric losses are zero, the current in capacitor leads the applied voltage by 90\u00b0. \nAlso imaginary part of is \u2208r is zero."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  For a solenoid having N turns, .Reason (R):  For all magnetic materials, B increases linearly with I.", "opta": "Both A and R are true and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are true but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true but R is false", "optd": "A is false but R is true", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Increase of B with I is not linear. Hence R is false."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  From the slope of the line in Figure, we can find permanent dipole moment of the molecules.Reason (R):  Total polarization of a polyatomic gas is given by P = N(ae + ai + \u03bc2p / 3kT)E.", "opta": "Both A and R are true and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are true but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true but R is false", "optd": "A is false but R is true", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The slope of the line in figure is . \nSince the total polarization is as given by the expression, we can find the permanent dipole moment of the molecules from the slope."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  If E is available energy state eV and EF is Fermi level, then probability of energy state E being occupied = 0.5.Reason (R): .", "opta": "Both A and R are true and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are true but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true but R is false", "optd": "A is false but R is true", "ans": "B", "explanation": "E = EF, f(E) = 0.5."}, {"question": "If a piece of wood is placed in a magnetic field", "opta": "the magnetic field will not be affected", "optb": "the magnetic lines of force will bend towards the piece", "optc": "the magnetic lines of force will bend away from the piece", "optd": "the flux may increase or decrease", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Wood is non-magnetic."}, {"question": "The apparent capacitance at a high angular frequency \u03c9 of an air cored capacitor having capacitance C and inductance L is given by", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The combination can be represented as L and C in series.\n.\nTherefore, ."}, {"question": "The number of valence electrons in donor impurity are", "opta": "5", "optb": "4", "optc": "3", "optd": "1", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Donor impurity has 5 valence electrons (while silicon has 4 valence electrons).\nHence donor impurity can donate electrons."}, {"question": "In a true valence crystal, the bonding between the atoms is accomplished by the sharing of valence electrons.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Sharing of valence electons is a characteristic of true valence crystal."}, {"question": "Which of the following are donor impurities? GoldPhosphorusBoronAntimonyArsenicInduim Select the correct answer using the following codes", "opta": "1, 2, 3", "optb": "1, 2, 4, 6", "optc": "3, 4, 5, 6", "optd": "2, 4, 5", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Donor impurities have five valence electrons."}, {"question": "To increase Q factor of a coil, the wire should be", "opta": "long", "optb": "thin", "optc": "thick", "optd": "long and thin", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Q is high if resistance is low. Therefore, wire should be thick."}, {"question": "An ammeter of 0-25 A range has a guaranteed accuracy of 1% of full scale reading. The current measured is 5 A. The limiting error is", "opta": "2%", "optb": "2.5%", "optc": "4%", "optd": "5%", "ans": "D", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "The coil of a moving iron instrument has a resistance of 500 &ohm; and an inductance of 1 H. It reads 250 V when a 250 V dc is applied. If series resistance is 2000 &ohm;, its reading when fed by 250 V, 50 Hz ac will be", "opta": "260 V", "optb": "252 V", "optc": "250 V", "optd": "248 V", "ans": "D", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "In 3 phase power measurement by two wattmeter method, the reading of one wattmeter is zero. The power factor of load is", "opta": "1", "optb": "0.5", "optc": "0", "optd": "0.8", "ans": "B", "explanation": "When p.f. = 0.5, 0 = 60\u00b0 and one of the wattmeters reads zero."}, {"question": "In a CRO which of the following is not a part of electron gun", "opta": "cathode", "optb": "grid", "optc": "accelerating anode", "optd": "X - Y plates", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Electron gun consists of cathode, grid and accelerating anode."}, {"question": "If reference sound pressure P0 is 2 x 10-5 N/m2, a sound pressure of 90 dB is equal to", "opta": "0.632 N/m2", "optb": "0.707 N/m2", "optc": "0.835 N/m2", "optd": "0.925 N/m2", "ans": "A", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "Which of the following voltmeters would you use for measuring voltage across 20 k&ohm; resistance?", "opta": "Voltmeter having a resistance of 5 k&ohm;", "optb": "Voltmeter having a sensitivity of 1 kW/V", "optc": "Voltmeter having sensitivity of 10 kW/V", "optd": "None of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Resistance of voltmeter should be very high as compared to 20 k&ohm;."}, {"question": "A single phase energy meter has the rating 1200 resolutions/ kWh. If a 500 W electric gadget is used for 4 hours, the energy meter will make", "opta": "1200 revolutions", "optb": "1800 revolutions", "optc": "2100 revolutions", "optd": "2400 revolutions", "ans": "D", "explanation": "0.5 x 4 = 2 kWh = 2 x 1200 revolutions."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  De sauty's bridge is suitable only for pure capacitor.Reason (R):  Capacitors are mostly perfect.", "opta": "Both A and R are true and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are true but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true R is false", "optd": "A is false R is true", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Capacitors are mostly imperfect."}, {"question": "In which of the transformer is the secondary nearly short circuited under normal operating conditions?", "opta": "CT", "optb": "PT", "optc": "Distribution transformer", "optd": "Power transformer", "ans": "A", "explanation": "CT is operated with secondary short-circuited otherwise a high emf would be induced across secondary."}, {"question": "A moving coil instrument has a resistance of 0.6 &ohm; and full scale deflection at 0.1 A. To convert it into an ammeter of 0-15 A range, the resistance of shunt should be", "opta": "0.6 &ohm;", "optb": "0.06 &ohm;", "optc": "0.1 &ohm;", "optd": "0.004 &ohm;", "ans": "D", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "A piezoelectric force transducer has a charge sensitivity of 20 pC/N. It is connected to a charge amplifier and overall gain of transducer and amplifier is 50 mV/N. The gain of amplifier is", "opta": "1 mV/pC", "optb": "1.5 mV/pC", "optc": "2.5 mV/pC", "optd": "4 mV/pC", "ans": "C", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "An LVDT is used to measure displacement. The LVDT feeds a Voltmeter of 0-5 V range through a 250 gain amplifier. For a displacement 0.5 mm the output of LVDT is 2 mV. The sensitivity of instrument is", "opta": "0.1 V/mm", "optb": "0.5 V/mm", "optc": "1 V/mm", "optd": "5 V/mm", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Final output = 2 x 10-3 x 250 = 0.5 V.\n."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  When a wattmeter is used for low impedance loads, the pressure coil is connected across the load.Reason (R):  A wattmeter measures apparent power.", "opta": "Both A and R are true and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are true but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true R is false", "optd": "A is false R is true", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Wattmeter measures active power."}, {"question": "As per BIS there are 6 accuracy classes of instruments.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "There are 8 classes of accuracy as per BIS."}, {"question": "In figure, Z1 = 200\u222060\u00b0 &ohm;, Z2 = 400\u2220 - 90\u00b0 &ohm;, Z3 = 300\u22200\u00b0. Then Z4 for bridge to be balanced is", "opta": "150\u222030\u00b0 &ohm;", "optb": "400\u2220 - 90\u00b0 &ohm;", "optc": "300\u222090\u00b0 &ohm;", "optd": "600\u2220 - 150\u00b0 &ohm;", "ans": "D", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "In a ballistic galvanometer, a charge of 100 \u03bcC gives a first swing of 25\u00b0. The charge required to cause first swing of 50\u00b0 is", "opta": "200 \u03bcC", "optb": "400 \u03bcC", "optc": "50 \u03bcC", "optd": "25 \u03bcC", "ans": "B", "explanation": "swing is proportional to charge."}, {"question": "Two resistors R1 = 36 &ohm; \u00b1 5% and R2 = 75 &ohm; \u00b1 5% are connected in series. The total resistance is", "opta": "111 \u00b1 0 &ohm;", "optb": "111 \u00b1 2.778 &ohm;", "optc": "111 \u00b1 5.55 &ohm;", "optd": "111 \u00b1 7.23 &ohm;", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Total maximum error \u00b1 (1.8 + 3.75) = \u00b1 5.55 &ohm;."}, {"question": "Figure shows an RC potentiometer to measure ac voltage. It is desired that V0/Vi should be independent of frequency. The value of C should be", "opta": "10 \u03bcF", "optb": "11 \u03bcF", "optc": "0.1 \u03bcF", "optd": "0.09 \u03bcF", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since resistances are in the ratio of 10 : 1, capacitances should be in the ratio of 1 : 10 because XC \u221d 1/C."}, {"question": "In a strain measuring device using a strain gauge, the output quantity is", "opta": "voltage", "optb": "resistance", "optc": "impedance", "optd": "either (a) or (b)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The measurement is done using an unbalanced bridge."}, {"question": "The Lissajous pattern observed on screen of CRO is a straight line inclined at 45\u00b0 to x axis. If X-plate input is 2 sin \u03c9t, the Y-plate input is", "opta": "2 sin \u03c9t", "optb": "2 sin (\u03c9t + 45\u00b0)", "optc": "2 sin (\u03c9t - 45\u00b0)", "optd": "22 sin \u03c9t + 45\u00b0)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "When signals to X and Y plates are in phase, the display is a straight line inclined at 45\u00b0."}, {"question": "The angle \u03b4 for a mica capacitor is about", "opta": "25\u00b0", "optb": "15\u00b0", "optc": "5\u00b0", "optd": "1\u00b0", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Mica capacitor has very low loss and loss angle \u03b4 is very very small."}, {"question": "A digital voltmeter has a read out range from 0 to 999 counts. If the full scale reading is 9.999 V, the resolution is", "opta": "1 V", "optb": "0.01 V", "optc": "1 mV", "optd": "1 \u03bcV", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Resolution is the smallest change in the quantity being measured which will cause an observable change in output. In this case it is 1 mV."}, {"question": "The coil of a moving coil meter has 100 turns, is 40 mm long and 30 mm wide. The control torque is 240 x 10-6 N-m on full scale. If B = 1 Wb/m2, range of meter is", "opta": "1 mA", "optb": "2 mA", "optc": "3 mA", "optd": "4 mA", "ans": "B", "explanation": "NBAI = Controlling torque or \n= 240 x 10-6 or I = 2 mA."}, {"question": "Consider the following statements: In a differential amplifier using JFET, the differential output offset is due to mismatch between FET parametersdifference in values of resistances used in circuitvariation in supply voltage. Of the statements, the correct statements are", "opta": "1 and 2", "optb": "1, 2, 3", "optc": "2, 3", "optd": "1, 3", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Variation in supply voltage affects both amplifiers equally."}, {"question": "Magnetic flux density has the dimensions", "opta": "MI-1T-2", "optb": "M-1I-2T-2", "optc": "ML-3T-2", "optd": "MI-1T-3", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Flux density = flux/area."}, {"question": "A meter with a resistance of 100 &ohm; and a full scale deflection of current of 1 mA is to be converted into voltmeter of 0 - 5 V range. The multiplier resistance should be", "opta": "490 &ohm;", "optb": "5000 &ohm;", "optc": "4900 &ohm;", "optd": "5100 &ohm;", "ans": "C", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "In a resistance strain gauge, G = 2, stress = 1050 kg/cm2, R = 1000 &ohm;. The value of \u0394R will be", "opta": "2 &ohm;", "optb": "3 &ohm;", "optc": "4 &ohm;", "optd": "1 &ohm;", "ans": "D", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "The household energy meter is", "opta": "indicating instrument", "optb": "recording instrument", "optc": "integrating instrument", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "It integrates energy over a period of time."}, {"question": "A standard cell of 1.0185 V is used with a slide wire potentiometer. The balance was obtained at 60 cm. When an unknown emf was connected, the balance was obtained at 82 cm. The magnitude of unknown emf is", "opta": "1.39 V", "optb": "0.75 V", "optc": "13.9 V", "optd": "7.45 V", "ans": "A", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "A full wave rectifier type meter is used to measure the wave shape shown in figure. The voltmeter is calibrated to read rms value of sine wave. The reading of voltmeter will be", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "100 V", "optd": "111 V", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Peak value of sine wave = 100 x 1.11 = 111 V."}, {"question": "A moving coil instrument has a resistance of 0.5 &ohm; and a full scale deflection of 0.1 A. To convert it into an ammeter of 0-10 A the shunt resistance should be", "opta": "0.004 &ohm;", "optb": "0.005 &ohm;", "optc": "0.05 &ohm;", "optd": "0.1 &ohm;", "ans": "B", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "Potentiometer method of dc voltage measurement is more accurate than direct measurement using a voltmeter because", "opta": "it loads the circuit to maximum extent", "optb": "it loads the circuit moderately", "optc": "it does not load the circuit at all", "optd": "it uses centre zero galvanometer instead of Voltmeters", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Since the circuit is not loaded, the accurate value of dc voltage is measured."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  A hot wire ammeter has a cramped scale.Reason (R):  The heat is proportional to square of current.", "opta": "Both A and R are true and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are true but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true R is false", "optd": "A is false R is true", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since heating \u221d I2, scale is cramped."}, {"question": "Which of the following is true about an impulse voltage?", "opta": "It is a unidirectional voltage", "optb": "Chopped impulse flashover does not occur", "optc": "Time taken to rise is equal to time taken to fall", "optd": "RMS value is always less than 50% of average value", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Impulse is unidirectional (either positive or negative)."}, {"question": "Which of the following are needed both for protection and metering?", "opta": "Wattmeters", "optb": "Instrument transformers", "optc": "Energy meters", "optd": "Power factor meters", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Instrument transformers are used to measure high currents and voltages. They also feed the relays for protection."}, {"question": "A digital frequency counter can be converted to DVM by addition of a suitable", "opta": "voltage controlled oscillator", "optb": "D/A converter", "optc": "power amplifier", "optd": "operational amplifier", "ans": "B", "explanation": "D/A converter changes digital output to analog output."}, {"question": "A dynamometer wattmeter is connected in ac circuit. The reading will be", "opta": "V-A product", "optb": "average power", "optc": "peak power", "optd": "instantaneous power", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Wattmeter measures average power over a cycle."}, {"question": "The speed transducer using a drag cup rotor has the main advantage of", "opta": "very high accuracy", "optb": "low energy requirement", "optc": "cheap construction", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "A drag cup rotor has low inertia. Therefore it requires little amount of energy."}, {"question": "A voltmeter using thermocouples measures", "opta": "rms value", "optb": "peak value", "optc": "average value", "optd": "peak to peak value", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since the thermocouple is based on heating effect, rms value is measured."}, {"question": "Which of the following measurements using a dc potentiometer do not require standardisation of potentiometer?", "opta": "Measurement of unknown voltage", "optb": "Measurement of resistance", "optc": "Measurement of unknown current", "optd": "Calibration of voltmeter", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Unknown resistance is compared with a standard resistance. Therefore standardisation of potentiometer is not necessary."}, {"question": "Which of the following statement is correct for two wattmeters method of power measurement in 3 phase circuit?", "opta": "Power can be measured by this method only for star connected loads", "optb": "When two wattmeters have equal readings power factor is 0.5.", "optc": "When power factor is 1, one of the wattmeters readings is zero", "optd": "When the two wattmeter read equal and opposite, p.f. is zero.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "When p.f. is zero, active power is zero and the two redaings are equal and opposite."}, {"question": "In a thermocouple temperature transducer, the output voltage is usually measured by", "opta": "high resistance ammeter", "optb": "high resistance voltmeter", "optc": "high resistance milli-voltmeter", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The output voltage is very small. So we need a milli voltmeter."}, {"question": "A moving iron instrument gives correct reading when used at", "opta": "low frequencies", "optb": "high frequencies", "optc": "only one frequency", "optd": "all frequencies upto a certain value", "ans": "C", "explanation": "If frequency changes reactance of coil changes and reading is affected."}, {"question": "Induction wattmeter can be used in", "opta": "ac circuit only", "optb": "dc circuit only", "optc": "both ac and dc circuit", "optd": "ac 3 phase only", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Induction effect occurs with ac only."}, {"question": "A dynamometer wattmeter is connected in ac circuit. The measured power is", "opta": "rms power", "optb": "average power", "optc": "peak power", "optd": "instantaneous power", "ans": "B", "explanation": "All wattmeters measure average power over a cycle."}, {"question": "Loss of charge method is suitable for medium resistances.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "It is suitable for high resistances."}, {"question": "In two wattmeter method of 3 phase power measurement, when does one wattmeter read negative", "opta": "when power factor is less than 0.5 lagging", "optb": "when power factor is greater than 0.5 lagging", "optc": "when power factor is less than 0.5", "optd": "when power factor is unity", "ans": "C", "explanation": "When p.f. is less than 0.5 (leading or lagging) one of the wattmeters reads negative."}, {"question": "It is required to measure angular position. Out of the transducers Circular potentiometerLVDTE pick upSynchro The proper devices are", "opta": "1, 2, 3, 4", "optb": "2 and 3", "optc": "1, 2, 4", "optd": "1 and 4", "ans": "D", "explanation": "LVDT and E pickup are suitable for linear displacement."}, {"question": "In figure the bridge is balanced when Z4 is", "opta": "120\u222070\u00b0", "optb": "187.5\u2220 - 10\u00b0", "optc": "187.5\u2220 - 70\u00b0", "optd": "333.3\u2220 - 70\u00b0", "ans": "C", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "Which of the following can be accessed only sequentially?", "opta": "Floppy disk", "optb": "Hard disk", "optc": "Magnetic tape", "optd": "ROM", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Magnetic tape can be accessed only sequentially."}, {"question": "MICR stands for", "opta": "Magnetic Ink Chart Receipt", "optb": "Magnetic Ink Character Recognition", "optc": "Magnetic Ink Chart Recognition", "optd": "Magnetic Ink Character Receipt", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Magnetic ink character recognition is used in banking."}, {"question": "8085 has 6 sign flags.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "It has one sign flag S."}, {"question": "JCOKE = 3JCOKE = JCOKE + 1GO TO (5, 8, 9, 11, 15, 16 18, 20) JCOKE.After the execution of above statement, the control is transferred to statement number", "opta": "8", "optb": "11", "optc": "16", "optd": "20", "ans": "B", "explanation": "It is a computed GO TO statement. Since J COKE = 3 + 1 = 4, the control is transferred to statement 11."}, {"question": "Binary number 1101.101 is equivalent to decimal number?", "opta": "13.5", "optb": "13.75", "optc": "13.625", "optd": "13.875", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Binary .101 equals 0.625 in decimal."}, {"question": "Expression ++i is equivalent to", "opta": "i = i + 2", "optb": "i = i + 1", "optc": "i = i - 1", "optd": "i = i + i + i", "ans": "B", "explanation": "i is incremented by 1."}, {"question": "To multiply a number by 8 in 8085 we have to use RAL instruction", "opta": "once", "optb": "twice", "optc": "thrice", "optd": "four times", "ans": "C", "explanation": "When RAL instruction is used once the number is doubled."}, {"question": "IC (instruction cycle), FC (fetch cycle) and EC (executive cycle) are related as", "opta": "IC = FC - EC", "optb": "IC = FC + EC", "optc": "IC = FC + 2EC", "optd": "EC = IC + EC", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Instruction cycle consists of fetch and execute cycles."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not a valid variable name in C?", "opta": "1 a", "optb": "a 1 2", "optc": "a b 123", "optd": "a b c 123", "ans": "A", "explanation": "First character must be alphabet."}, {"question": "When .4546 E 5 and .5433 E 7 are to be added in normalized floating point mode", "opta": "none of the numbers is changed to any other form", "optb": ".4546 E 5 is changed .004546 E 7 and .5433 E 7 is not changed", "optc": ".5433 E 7 is changed to 54.33 E 5 and .4546 E 5 is not changed", "optd": "both the numbers are changed and their exponents are made equal to 6", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Exponents are made equal and integer part is made zero."}, {"question": "Computer virus can hide itself in a diskette but not in a hard disk.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Computer virus can hide in hard disk also."}, {"question": "The size of cache memory in most microcomputers is about", "opta": "a few bytes", "optb": "a few kilobytes", "optc": "a few megabytes", "optd": "a few gigabytes", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Size of Cache memory varies from about 16 K bytes to about 256 K bytes."}, {"question": "Which of the following computer memories is fastest?", "opta": "Cache", "optb": "Primary", "optc": "Mass storage", "optd": "Off line back up", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Cache memory has a speed of about four times the speed of main memory. It is a small high speed memory."}, {"question": "During processing the instructions, data, intermediate results and final results in a computer are held in", "opta": "CPU", "optb": "ALU", "optc": "Primary memory", "optd": "Secondary memory", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Primary memory holds these during processing of instructions."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not a valid variable name in C?", "opta": "p o, t", "optb": "p o t", "optc": "po_t", "optd": "p_ot", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Comma is not allowed."}, {"question": "Z flag is reset if an ALU operation results in 0.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Z flag is set if ALU operation results in zero."}, {"question": "The power requirements of a DRAM in active and stand by modes is about", "opta": "350 mW and 5 mW respectively", "optb": "350 mW each", "optc": "5 mW each", "optd": "350 mW and 100 mW respectively", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Power requirement in stand by mode is very low 1000."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not a valid real constant in C?", "opta": "1.2 e 2.0", "optb": "-2.3 e - 2", "optc": "-2.3 E 2", "optd": "-2.3 e 2", "ans": "C", "explanation": "In C real constant expressed in exponential form, mantissia and exponent should be separated by e (and not E)."}, {"question": "In a computer the instructions, data, intermediate and final results during processing are held in ALU.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "These are not held in ALU. Only computations are done by ALU."}, {"question": "The number of storage classes in C is", "opta": "2", "optb": "3", "optc": "4", "optd": "6", "ans": "C", "explanation": "C has four storage classes viz. automatic storage class, register storage class, static storage class and external storage class."}, {"question": "Most of the memory chips in static RAM", "opta": "do not require any supply", "optb": "need 2 V supply", "optc": "need 5 V supply", "optd": "need 12 V supply", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Digital chips need 5 V supply."}, {"question": "The interface chip for 8086 and 16 bit ADC is", "opta": "8259", "optb": "8255", "optc": "8253", "optd": "8251", "ans": "B", "explanation": "8255 is interface chip for 8086 and ADC."}, {"question": "Which of the following real variable names is not valid in Fortran?", "opta": "BETA", "optb": "ALPHA", "optc": "A", "optd": "AB * 2", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Operator is not allowed."}, {"question": "Temporary register in 8085 is a 16 bit register.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "It is 8 bit-register."}, {"question": "In which computer language is 'break' statement used", "opta": "Fortran 77", "optb": "Pascal", "optc": "C", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Whenever keyword 'break' is encountered inside any C loop control passes to the first statement after the loop."}, {"question": "In a microprocessor", "opta": "all instructions need only one machine cycle", "optb": "some instructions need only one machine cycle while some other instructions need more than one machine cycle", "optc": "all instructions need only fraction of one machine cycle", "optd": "some instructions need less than one machine cycle", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Some instructrions do need more than one machine cycle."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  If source and destination addresses are made implicit the length of instruction is reduced.Reason (R): 8085 has only 3 addressing modes.", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are correct but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is correct R is wrong", "optd": "A is wrong R is correct", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The number of addressing modes is five."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  Microprocessor 8085 has on-chip oscillator with inbuilt crystal.Reason (R): For frequency stability crystal oscillator is preferred.", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are correct but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is correct R is wrong", "optd": "A is wrong R is correct", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Crystal has to be connected externally to pins 1 and 2 of 8085."}, {"question": "Consider the following program in Pascal X = 2.57X = (X + 0.06) * 10I = TRUNC (X)X = IX = X / 10.0 The final value of X would be", "opta": "2", "optb": "2.6", "optc": "2.63", "optd": "26.3", "ans": "B", "explanation": "(2.57 + 0.06) 10 = 26.3 \u2192  ."}, {"question": "Consider the following The first letter of a Java variable is lower case.Each successive word in Java variable begins with a capital letter.All other letters are lower case.A Java variable can have a digit as first character. Which of the above are correct?", "opta": "All", "optb": "1, 2, 3 only", "optc": "1, 2, 4 only", "optd": "2, 3, 4 only", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Digit as first character is not allowed."}, {"question": "Consider the following DO statement in Fortran 77 DO 52 N = 1, 10, 3 The number of DO loop executions in the above statement is", "opta": "1", "optb": "10", "optc": "3", "optd": "4", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Do statement is executed when N = 1, 4, 7, 10, i.e.,  a total of 4 times."}, {"question": "Which of the following can not be used as a variable name in C?", "opta": "else", "optb": "coal", "optc": "ram", "optd": "vendy", "ans": "A", "explanation": "else is not allowed as variable name in C."}, {"question": "In Java it is possible to have An array of integersAn array of string objectsAn array of arraysAn array on integer and strings Which of the above are correct?", "opta": "All", "optb": "1, 2 and 3 only", "optc": "1 and 2 only", "optd": "1, 3 and 4 only", "ans": "B", "explanation": "An array on integers and strings is not possible."}, {"question": "A 256 x 4 EPROM has", "opta": "8 address pins and 4 data pins", "optb": "8 address pins and 8 data pins", "optc": "4 address pins and 8 data pins", "optd": "4 address pins and 4 data pins", "ans": "A", "explanation": "28 = 256"}, {"question": "To evaluate X = (A + B + 1.2) * (A + B - C) the sequence of operation is", "opta": "+ + + - * =", "optb": "* + + + - =", "optc": "+ + - * + =", "optd": "- + + + * =", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Parenthesis has first priority."}, {"question": "In ALU 1C 74181 the addition and subtraction is in", "opta": "2's complement", "optb": "1's complement", "optc": "binary", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "2's complement is universally used in computers."}, {"question": "While selecting a memory chip the feature which should be examined is", "opta": "capacity", "optb": "ac characteristics", "optc": "dc characteristics", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "All these characteristics are important."}, {"question": "EEPROM permits", "opta": "read operation only", "optb": "read and byte erase operations", "optc": "read, byte erase and byte write operations", "optd": "read, byte erase, byte write and chip erase operations", "ans": "D", "explanation": "All the four are permitted."}, {"question": "Which is not a valid Java variable", "opta": "lot", "optb": "c 1t", "optc": "s $ 2", "optd": "2 s $", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The first letter of variable name should be lower case."}, {"question": "Which of the following is invalid in Basic?", "opta": "A ** B + - C", "optb": "A ** B - C", "optc": "A * B - C", "optd": "A * B - C ** D", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Two operators cannot exist together."}, {"question": "If A = 20 and B = - 7 in PASCAL, A mod B =", "opta": "6", "optb": "2", "optc": "- 1", "optd": "3", "ans": "A", "explanation": "It gives remainder in division operation."}, {"question": "Which of the following is a computer language?", "opta": "MS WORD", "optb": "Page maker", "optc": "MS EXCEL", "optd": "LISP", "ans": "D", "explanation": "LISP is a computer language. The remaining are software packages."}, {"question": "Which of the following DO statements is invalid in FORTRAN 77?", "opta": "DO 161 = 1, 15", "optb": "DO 16 1 = 1, 10, 1", "optc": "DO 16 I = - 5, 5, 2", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "All are valid."}, {"question": "Read the following statements about files in Pascal A file is a data structure which consists of a sequence of components of the same type.The number of components in a file is variable.The components in a file can be accessed only sequentially starting from the beginning of the file. Which of the above are correct?", "opta": "All", "optb": "1 and 2 only", "optc": "2 and 3 only", "optd": "1 and 3 only", "ans": "A", "explanation": "All statements are true."}, {"question": "Consider the following C program int ramfloat alpha, gammaram = 6400alpha = 0.562gamma = alpha * ram + 1Now consider the following statements about this program ram is an integer variablealpha, gamma are real variables*, + are arithmetic operators0.562 may be an integer constant or real constant Which of the above are correct?", "opta": "All", "optb": "1, 2, 3 only", "optc": "2, 3, 4 only", "optd": "1, 2, 4 only", "ans": "B", "explanation": "0.562 is not an integer constant."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not an integer constant?", "opta": "0", "optb": "-8", "optc": "+1074", "optd": "-8.1", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Integer constant should not have decimal point."}, {"question": "Let JCOKE = 98 and LPEPSI = 42 Consider the statement IF (JCOKE - 3 * LPEPSI) 5, 6, 75 JCOKE = JCOKE + 56 JCOKE = JCOKE + 87 JCOKE = JCOKE + 11 The value of JCOKE after the execution of above statement will be", "opta": "103", "optb": "106", "optc": "109", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since (J COKE - 3 x L PEPSI) is negative, statement 5 is executed and the result is 98 + 5 = 103."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not a valid real constant in C?", "opta": "426", "optb": "321.0", "optc": "-621.231", "optd": "+201.2314", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Real constant must have a decimal point."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not a valid integer constant in C (for 16 bit)?", "opta": "321", "optb": "-162", "optc": "-65321", "optd": "+1", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The range is from - 32768 to + 32767."}, {"question": "Assume that x = 5 and y = 2. Then in Java operation x + = y, the result is", "opta": "x = 7", "optb": "x = 2", "optc": "x = 3", "optd": "x = 2", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The operator + = means add and assign."}, {"question": "The velocity factor of a transmission line depends on", "opta": "temperature", "optb": "skin effect", "optc": "relative permittivity of dielectric", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "\u2208r of a dielectric changes with humidity."}, {"question": "A loss less line of characteristic impedance Z0 is terminated in pure reactance of -jZ0 value. VSWR is", "opta": "10", "optb": "2", "optc": "1", "optd": "infinity", "ans": "D", "explanation": "A pure reactance does not absorb any power.\nTherefore VSWR is infinite because |rv| = 1."}, {"question": "In a klystron amplifier the input cavity is called", "opta": "buncher", "optb": "catcher", "optc": "Pierce gun", "optd": "collector", "ans": "A", "explanation": "A Klystron is a vacuum tube used for generation/amplification of microwaves. \nAn electron beam is produced by oxide coated indirectly heated cathode and is focussed and accelerated by focussing electrode. \nThis beam is transmitted through a glass tube. The input cavity where the beam enters the glass tube is called buncher. \nAs electrons move ahead they see an accelerating field for half cycle and retarding field for the other half cycle. \nTherefore, some electrons are accelerated and some are retarded. This process is called velocity modulation. \nThe velocity modulation causes bunching of electrons. This bunching effect converts velocity modulation into density modulation of beam. \nThe input is fed at buncher cavity and output is taken at catcher cavity. \nIn a two cavity klystron only buncher and catcher cavity are used. In multi cavity klystron one or more intermediate cavities are also used. \nThe features of a multicavity klystron are :\n1. Frequency range - 0.25 GHz to 100 GHz\n2. Power output - 10 kW to several hundred kW\n3. Power gain - 60 dB (nominal value)\n4. Efficiency - about 40%.\nA multicavity klystron is used in UHF TV transmitters, Radar transmitter and satellite communication."}, {"question": "In a circular waveguide the dominant mode is", "opta": "TE01", "optb": "TE11", "optc": "TE20", "optd": "TE21", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Some applications require dual polarization capability. Circular waveguide has this capability. \nThese analysis uses cylindrical coordinates. \nIn circular waveguide TE11 mode has the lowest cut off frequency and is the dominant mode. \nIf D is diameter of waveguide\n\u03bbc = 1.706 D for TE11 mode\n\u03bbc = 1.029 D for TE21 mode\n\u03bbc = 0.82 D for TE01 mode\n\u03bbc = 1.306 D for TM01 mode."}, {"question": "The reflection coefficient on a line is 0.2 \u222045\u00b0. The SWR is", "opta": "0.8", "optb": "1.1", "optc": "1.2", "optd": "1.5", "ans": "D", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Microwave resonators are used in", "opta": "microwave oscillators", "optb": "microwave narrow band amplifier", "optc": "microwave frequency metres", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "They are used in all the devices."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  TWT uses a focussing mechanism to prevent the electron beam from spreading.Reason (R): In a TWT the electron beam has to travel a much longer distance than in klystron.", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are correct but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is correct but R is wrong", "optd": "A is wrong but R is correct", "ans": "A", "explanation": "In a klystron the resonant structure limits the bandwidth. \nA TWT is a broadband device. Its main components are electron gun (to produce the electron beam) and a structure supporting the slow electromagnetic wave. \nThe velocity of wave propagation along the helix structure is less than velocity of light. \nThe beam and wave travel along the structure at the same speed. \nThus interaction occurs between beam and wave and the beam delivers energy to the RF wave. \nTherefore the signal gets strengthened and amplified output is delivered at the other end of tube. \nThe main features of TWT are :\n1. Frequency range - 0.5 GHz to 90 GHz\n2. Power output - 5 mW at low frequencies(less than 20 GHz) 250 kW (continuous wave) at 3 GHz 10 MW (pulsed) at 3 GHz\n3. Efficiency - about 5 to 20%\n4. Noise - about 5 dB for low power TWT 25 dB for high power TWT \nTWT is used as RF amplifier in broadband microwave receivers, repeater amplifier in broad band communication systems, communication satellites etc."}, {"question": "In a TWT the amplitude of resultant wave travelling down the helix", "opta": "increases exponentially", "optb": "increases linearly", "optc": "decreases exponentially", "optd": "is almost constant", "ans": "A", "explanation": "In a klystron the resonant structure limits the bandwidth. \nA TWT is a broadband device. Its main components are electron gun (to produce the electron beam) and a structure supporting the slow electromagnetic wave. \nThe velocity of wave propagation along the helix structure is less than velocity of light. \nThe beam and wave travel along the structure at the same speed. \nThus interaction occurs between beam and wave and the beam delivers energy to the RF wave. \nTherefore the signal gets strengthened and amplified output is delivered at the other end of tube. \nThe main features of TWT are :\n1. Frequency range - 0.5 GHz to 90 GHz\n2. Power output - 5 mW at low frequencies(less than 20 GHz) 250 kW (continuous wave) at 3 GHz 10 MW (pulsed) at 3 GHz\n3. Efficiency - about 5 to 20%\n4. Noise - about 5 dB for low power TWT 25 dB for high power TWT \nTWT is used as RF amplifier in broadband microwave receivers, repeater amplifier in broad band communication systems, communication satellites etc."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not a travelling wave?", "opta": "e = Em sin (\u03b2x - \u03c9t)", "optb": "e = Em cos (\u03b2x - \u03c9t)", "optc": "e = Em sin (\u03c9t - \u03b2x)", "optd": "e = Em sin (\u03b2x)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "In a travelling wave both x and t increase simultaneously so that a constant phase point moves in the direction of positive (or negative) x."}, {"question": "Both Impatt and Trapatt devices use avalanche effect", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "An Impatt diode has n+ - p - i - p + structure and is used with reverse bias. \nIt exhibits negative resistance and operates on the principle of avalanche breakdown. \nImpatt diode circuits are classified as broadly tunable circuit, low Q circuit and high Q circuit. \nThe impedance of Impatt diode is a few ohms. The word Impatt stands for Impact Avalanche Transit Time diode. \nThe features of Impatt diode oscillator are : frequency 1 to 300 GHz, Power output (0.5 W to 5 W for single diode circuit and upto 40 W for combination of several diodes), efficiency about 20%. \nIts applications include police radar systems, low power microwave transmitter etc.\nAvalanche diode can also be operated in large signal high efficiency mode called Trapped Avalanche Transit Time mode. \nThe Trapatt oscillations depend on the delay in the current caused by avalanche process. \nThe avalanche delay makes it possible to increase the diode voltage well above the breakdown voltage. \nTherefore a very rapid multiplication of charge carriers occurs. A Trapatt diode is also a negative resistance device. \nThe features of Trapatt diode oscillator are : Frequency 3 to 50 GHz, Power output 1-3 W, efficiency about 25%. \nIts applications are low power doppler radar, microwave beacon landing system etc."}, {"question": "In a directional coupler", "opta": "isolation (dB) equals coupling plus directivity", "optb": "coupling (dB) equals isolation plus directivity", "optc": "directivity (dB) equals isolation plus coupling", "optd": "isolation (dB) equals (coupling) (directivity)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Isolation equals coupling plus directivity."}, {"question": "As the frequency is increased, the charging MVAR in a cable", "opta": "decreases", "optb": "increases", "optc": "remain the same", "optd": "decreases or remains the scheme", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Charging current and MVAR are proportional to frequency."}, {"question": "Loss angle of a good quality cable is about", "opta": "1\u00b0", "optb": "30\u00b0", "optc": "70\u00b0", "optd": "90\u00b0", "ans": "A", "explanation": "For ideal dielectric loss angle is zero. For good quality cables, loss angle is very small, about 1\u00b0 only."}, {"question": "In a three cavity klystron amplifier, the oscillations are excited in", "opta": "input cavity", "optb": "output cavity", "optc": "intermediate cavity", "optd": "both (a) and (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "A Klystron is a vacuum tube used for generation/amplification of microwaves. \nAn electron beam is produced by oxide coated indirectly heated cathode and is focussed and accelerated by focussing electrode. \nThis beam is transmitted through a glass tube. The input cavity where the beam enters the glass tube is called buncher. \nAs electrons move ahead they see an accelerating field for half cycle and retarding field for the other half cycle. \nTherefore, some electrons are accelerated and some are retarded. This process is called velocity modulation. \nThe velocity modulation causes bunching of electrons. This bunching effect converts velocity modulation into density modulation of beam. \nThe input is fed at buncher cavity and output is taken at catcher cavity. \nIn a two cavity klystron only buncher and catcher cavity are used. In multi cavity klystron one or more intermediate cavities are also used. \nThe features of a multicavity klystron are :\n1. Frequency range - 0.25 GHz to 100 GHz\n2. Power output - 10 kW to several hundred kW\n3. Power gain - 60 dB (nominal value)\n4. Efficiency - about 40%.\nA multicavity klystron is used in UHF TV transmitters, Radar transmitter and satellite communication."}, {"question": "In the given figure reflection coefficient at load is", "opta": "0.6", "optb": "- 0.6", "optc": "0.4", "optd": "- 0.4", "ans": "B", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Which of the following lines is non-radiating?", "opta": "Open two wire", "optb": "Coaxial", "optc": "Both", "optd": "None of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since fields are confirmed within a coaxial cable it is non-radiating."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  The impedance of a matched load is equal to characteristic impedance of line.Reason (R): A matched termination absorbs all the power incident on it.", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are correct but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is correct but R is wrong", "optd": "A is wrong but R is correct", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Matched load means no reflections."}, {"question": "Skin effect is more pronounced at high frequencies.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Skin effect increases as frequency increases."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  The phenomenon of differential mobility is called transferred electron effect.Reason (R): GaAs exhibits transferred electron effect.", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are correct but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is correct but R is wrong", "optd": "A is wrong but R is correct", "ans": "B", "explanation": "A Gunn diode uses GaAs which has a negative differential mobility, i.e., a decrease in carrier velocity with increase in electric field. \nThis effects is called transferred electron effect. The impedance of a Gunn diode is tens of ohms.\nA Gunn diode oscillator has a resonant cavity, an arrangement to couple Gunn diode to cavity, biasing arrangement for Gunn diode and arrangement to couple RF power to load.\nApplications of Gunn diode oscillator include continuous wave radar, pulsed radar and microwave receivers."}, {"question": "Which of the following devices uses a helix?", "opta": "Klystron amplifier", "optb": "Klystron oscillator", "optc": "TWT", "optd": "Both (a) and (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "In a klystron the resonant structure limits the bandwidth. \nA TWT is a broadband device. Its main components are electron gun (to produce the electron beam) and a structure supporting the slow electromagnetic wave. \nThe velocity of wave propagation along the helix structure is less than velocity of light. \nThe beam and wave travel along the structure at the same speed. \nThus interaction occurs between beam and wave and the beam delivers energy to the RF wave. \nTherefore the signal gets strengthened and amplified output is delivered at the other end of tube. \nThe main features of TWT are :\n1. Frequency range - 0.5 GHz to 90 GHz\n2. Power output - 5 mW at low frequencies(less than 20 GHz) 250 kW (continuous wave) at 3 GHz 10 MW (pulsed) at 3 GHz\n3. Efficiency - about 5 to 20%\n4. Noise - about 5 dB for low power TWT 25 dB for high power TWT \nTWT is used as RF amplifier in broadband microwave receivers, repeater amplifier in broad band communication systems, communication satellites etc."}, {"question": "Which of the following parameters is negligible in transmission lines?", "opta": "R", "optb": "L", "optc": "C", "optd": "G", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Shunt conductance can be neglected in most of calculations."}, {"question": "The width of a radio beam from a 1 m diameter parabolic antenna at 10 GHz is about", "opta": "100\u00b0", "optb": "50\u00b0", "optc": "5\u00b0", "optd": "1\u00b0", "ans": "C", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "The diagram to show distance time history of electrons in klystron amplifier is called", "opta": "apple gate diagram", "optb": "asynchronous diagram", "optc": "bunching diagram", "optd": "velocity modulation diagram", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Applegate diagram is distance time plot."}, {"question": "Impedance level of Impatt diodes is generally lower than that of Gunn diodes", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "An Impatt diode has n+ - p - i - p + structure and is used with reverse bias. \nIt exhibits negative resistance and operates on the principle of avalanche breakdown. \nImpatt diode circuits are classified as broadly tunable circuit, low Q circuit and high Q circuit. \nThe impedance of Impatt diode is a few ohms. The word Impatt stands for Impact Avalanche Transit Time diode. \nThe features of Impatt diode oscillator are : frequency 1 to 300 GHz, Power output (0.5 W to 5 W for single diode circuit and upto 40 W for combination of several diodes), efficiency about 20%. \nIts applications include police radar systems, low power microwave transmitter etc."}, {"question": "A quarter wave line open circuited at far end behaves as", "opta": "inductance", "optb": "L and C in parallel", "optc": "capacitance", "optd": "L and C in series", "ans": "D", "explanation": "A quarter wave line o.c. at far end behaves as a series tuned circuit."}, {"question": "A line has Z0 = 300 \u2220 0\u00b0 \u03a9. If ZL = 150 \u2220 0\u00b0 \u03a9, reflection coefficient is", "opta": "0.5", "optb": "0.3333", "optc": "-0.3333", "optd": "-0.5", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Reflection coefficient"}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  A backward wave oscillator has an internal positive feedback.Reason (R): A positive feedback is necessary for sustained oscillations.", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are correct but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is correct but R is wrong", "optd": "A is wrong but R is correct", "ans": "B", "explanation": "It is somewhat similar to TWT and can deliver microwave power over a wide frequency band. \nIt has an electron gun and a helix structure. However the interaction between electron beam and RF wave is different than in TWT. \nThe growing RF wave travels in opposite direction to the electron beam. \nThe frequency of wave can be changed by changing the voltage which controls the beam velocity. \nMoreover the amplitude of oscillations can be decreased continuously to zero by changing the beam current. \nIt features are:\n1. Frequency range - 1 GHz to 1000 GHz.\n2. Power output - 10 mV to 150 mW (continuous wave) 250kW (pulsed).\nIt is used as signal source in transmitters and instruments."}, {"question": "In a microstrip transmission the signal can be easily redirected by changing the centre strip.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "A Microstrip line has a single dielectric substratc with ground plane on one side and a strip on the other face. \nIts special feature is easy access to top surface so that minor adjustments can be made after circuit fabrication. \nThe high dielectric constant of the substrate reduces guide wavelength and circuit dimensions. \nA microstrip line is the most commomly used transmission structure for microwave integrated circuits."}, {"question": "The frequency of oscillation in a backward wave oscillator can be changed by", "opta": "varying the voltage which controls beam velocity", "optb": "varying the beam current", "optc": "both by varying the beam current and by light varying the voltage which controls beam velocity", "optd": "changing the rate of thermionic emission", "ans": "A", "explanation": "It is somewhat similar to TWT and can deliver microwave power over a wide frequency band. \nIt has an electron gun and a helix structure. However the interaction between electron beam and RF wave is different than in TWT. \nThe growing RF wave travels in opposite direction to the electron beam. \nThe frequency of wave can be changed by changing the voltage which controls the beam velocity. \nMoreover the amplitude of oscillations can be decreased continuously to zero by changing the beam current. \nIt features are:\n1. Frequency range - 1 GHz to 1000 GHz.\n2. Power output - 10 mV to 150 mW (continuous wave) 250kW (pulsed).\nIt is used as signal source in transmitters and instruments."}, {"question": "A line has a phase constant of 29.8 rad/m. At 1000 MHz the wavelength is", "opta": "29.8 m", "optb": "2.98 m", "optc": "2.1 m", "optd": "0.21 m", "ans": "D", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "In the given figure the time taken by the wave to make one round trip is", "opta": "10 ns", "optb": "20 ns", "optc": "30 ns", "optd": "40 ns", "ans": "D", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "For a 50 \u03a9 resistor for 3 GHz application, the stray capacitance should be less than", "opta": "1 \u03bcF", "optb": "1 nF", "optc": "1 pF", "optd": "0.1 pF", "ans": "D", "explanation": "XC should be at least ten times greater than R. Therefore for 50 \u03a9 resistor at 3 GHz, C should be less than 0.1 pF."}, {"question": "In a travelling wave tube distributed interaction between an electron beam and a travelling wave takes place", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "In a klystron the resonant structure limits the bandwidth. \nA TWT is a broadband device. Its main components are electron gun (to produce the electron beam) and a structure supporting the slow electromagnetic wave. \nThe velocity of wave propagation along the helix structure is less than velocity of light. \nThe beam and wave travel along the structure at the same speed. \nThus interaction occurs between beam and wave and the beam delivers energy to the RF wave. \nTherefore the signal gets strengthened and amplified output is delivered at the other end of tube. \nThe main features of TWT are :\n1. Frequency range - 0.5 GHz to 90 GHz\n2. Power output - 5 mW at low frequencies(less than 20 GHz) 250 kW (continuous wave) at 3 GHz 10 MW (pulsed) at 3 GHz\n3. Efficiency - about 5 to 20%\n4. Noise - about 5 dB for low power TWT 25 dB for high power TWT \nTWT is used as RF amplifier in broadband microwave receivers, repeater amplifier in broad band communication systems, communication satellites etc."}, {"question": "The fabrication of microstrip line is done by", "opta": "photo etching", "optb": "printed circuit technique", "optc": "oxidation", "optd": "cladding", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Printed circuit techniques is used for micro strip line."}, {"question": "The condition of minimum distortion in a transmission line is", "opta": "RL = 1", "optb": "R = 0", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The condition for minimum distortion is found by equating The result is ."}, {"question": "The action of backward wave oscillator is similar to that of", "opta": "klystron amplifier", "optb": "reflex klystron oscillator", "optc": "TWT", "optd": "magnetron", "ans": "C", "explanation": "It is somewhat similar to TWT and can deliver microwave power over a wide frequency band. \nIt has an electron gun and a helix structure. However the interaction between electron beam and RF wave is different than in TWT. \nThe growing RF wave travels in opposite direction to the electron beam. \nThe frequency of wave can be changed by changing the voltage which controls the beam velocity. \nMoreover the amplitude of oscillations can be decreased continuously to zero by changing the beam current. \nIt features are:\n1. Frequency range - 1 GHz to 1000 GHz.\n2. Power output - 10 mV to 150 mW (continuous wave) 250kW (pulsed).\nIt is used as signal source in transmitters and instruments."}, {"question": "In the given figure the reflection coefficient at source end is", "opta": "1", "optb": "-1", "optc": "1/3", "optd": "-1/3", "ans": "C", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  Artificial transmission lines are frequently used in laboratories.Reason (R): An artificial transmission line can be used to represent an actual line and can also be used as a delay circuit, as attenuator, as filter network etc.", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are correct but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is correct but R is wrong", "optd": "A is wrong but R is correct", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Artificial transmission lines have many applications. One of the applications is to simulate an actual line in the laboratory."}, {"question": "In a backward wave oscillator the wave travelling along the line winds itself back and forth", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "It is somewhat similar to TWT and can deliver microwave power over a wide frequency band. \nIt has an electron gun and a helix structure. However the interaction between electron beam and RF wave is different than in TWT. \nThe growing RF wave travels in opposite direction to the electron beam. \nThe frequency of wave can be changed by changing the voltage which controls the beam velocity. \nMoreover the amplitude of oscillations can be decreased continuously to zero by changing the beam current. \nIt features are:\n1. Frequency range - 1 GHz to 1000 GHz.\n2. Power output - 10 mV to 150 mW (continuous wave) 250kW (pulsed).\nIt is used as signal source in transmitters and instruments."}, {"question": "A line is excited by a 100 V dc source. If reflection coefficients at both ends are 1 each then", "opta": "there will be no oscillations on line", "optb": "there will be only 1 or 2 oscillations on line", "optc": "there will be a finite number of oscillations on line", "optd": "the oscillations will continue indefinitely", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Because rv = 1 at each end, the line voltage will not reach a steady value and oscillations will continue indefinitely."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  A coaxial line is a non-radiating line.Reason (R): In a coaxial line the electric and magnetic fields are confined to the region between the concentric conductors.", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are correct but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is correct but R is wrong", "optd": "A is wrong but R is correct", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since the fields are confined, there is no radiation."}, {"question": "Reflex klystron oscillator is essentially a low power device", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "It uses a single cavity resonator for generating microwave oscillations. \nIts parts are electron gun, resonator, repeller and output coupling.\nIt operates on the principle of positive feed back. \nThe repeller electrode is at negative potential and sends the partially bunched electron beam back to resonator cavity. \nThis positive feedback supports oscillations. Its feature are: \n1. Frequency range - 2 to 100 GHz\n2. Power output - 10 MW to about 2 W\n3. Efficiency - 10 - 20 %\nIts applications include radar receivers, local oscillator in microwave devices, oscillator for microwave measurements in laboratories etc."}, {"question": "A 10 km long line has a characteristic impedance of 400 ohms. If line length is 100 km, the characteristic impedance is", "opta": "4000 \u03a9", "optb": "400 \u03a9", "optc": "40 \u03a9", "optd": "4 \u03a9", "ans": "B", "explanation": "and is independent of line length."}, {"question": "A matched generator (Zg = Z0) with 1 \u03a9 available. If all ports are matched, the power delivered at ports 1, 2, 3 respectively are", "opta": "0.5 W, 0.5 W, 0 W", "optb": "0 W, 0 W, 1 W", "optc": "0.33 W each", "optd": "0 W, 0.25 W, 0.25 W", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since all ports matched, input SWR = 1. No power is reflected and Pin = P4 = 1 W. \nThis power splits between ports 1 and 2. Therefore P1 = P2 = 0.5 \u03a9, P3 = 0."}, {"question": "Which TM mode in rectangular waveguide has lowest cutoff frequency?", "opta": "TM11", "optb": "TM01", "optc": "TM10", "optd": "TM21", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Hz = 0\n\n\n\nEx = \u00b1 ZTM Hy\nEy = \u00b1 ZTM Hx\nwhere E0 is the amplitude of the wave.\nThe expressions for \u03b2, \u03bbc, fc, \u03bbg, a are the same as for TE waves.\nFor TM wave the lowest cut off frequency in rectangular wave guide is for TM11 mode. \nIf , the cutoff frequency for TM11 mode is about 12% more than that for TE20 mode."}, {"question": "A resistive microwave load with ZL = 150 \u03a9 is connected to 50 \u03a9 coaxial line. SWR is", "opta": "more than 3", "optb": "less than 3", "optc": "equal to 3", "optd": "either (a) or (c)", "ans": "C", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Which of the following devices uses a slow wave structure?", "opta": "Klystron two cavity amplifier", "optb": "Klystron multicavity amplifier", "optc": "Reflex klystron oscillator", "optd": "TWT", "ans": "D", "explanation": "In a klystron the resonant structure limits the bandwidth. \nA TWT is a broadband device. Its main components are electron gun (to produce the electron beam) and a structure supporting the slow electromagnetic wave. \nThe velocity of wave propagation along the helix structure is less than velocity of light. \nThe beam and wave travel along the structure at the same speed. \nThus interaction occurs between beam and wave and the beam delivers energy to the RF wave. \nTherefore the signal gets strengthened and amplified output is delivered at the other end of tube. \nThe main features of TWT are :\n1. Frequency range - 0.5 GHz to 90 GHz\n2. Power output - 5 mW at low frequencies(less than 20 GHz) 250 kW (continuous wave) at 3 GHz 10 MW (pulsed) at 3 GHz\n3. Efficiency - about 5 to 20%\n4. Noise - about 5 dB for low power TWT 25 dB for high power TWT \nTWT is used as RF amplifier in broadband microwave receivers, repeater amplifier in broad band communication systems, communication satellites etc."}, {"question": "In a turnstile antenna two-half wave resonant wire radiators are placed at 90\u00b0 to each other in the same plane and are excited", "opta": "in phase", "optb": "in phase opposition", "optc": "90\u00b0 out of phase with each other", "optd": "45\u00b0 out of phase with each other", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Since the two wire radiators are at 90\u00b0 to each other, they have to be excited 90\u00b0 out of phase with each other."}, {"question": "A waveguide section in a microwave circuit acts as", "opta": "LP filter", "optb": "Bandpass filter", "optc": "HP filter", "optd": "Band stop filter", "ans": "C", "explanation": "It allows high frequencies."}, {"question": "In a klystron amplifier dc electron velocity is v0 and dc electron charge density is r0 the dc beam current is", "opta": "r0v0", "optb": "r0/v0", "optc": "v0/r0", "optd": "(v0/r0)2", "ans": "A", "explanation": "= coulomb |sec|m2 = current density."}, {"question": "In a parallel resonant circuit, the circuit current at resonance is maximum.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "In parallel resonance current is minimum."}, {"question": "The rms value of wave in figure is", "opta": "about 95 V", "optb": "about 80 V", "optc": "about 50 V", "optd": "about 25 V", "ans": "B", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "An RLC series circuit is underdamped. To make it overdamped, the value of R", "opta": "has to be increased", "optb": "has to be decreased", "optc": "has to be increased to infinity", "optd": "has to be reduced to zero", "ans": "A", "explanation": "For overdamping R is more."}, {"question": "Henry is equivalent to", "opta": "Volts/Ampere", "optb": "Weber/Volt", "optc": "Weber/Ampere", "optd": "Weber/Ampere2", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Inductance is flux per ampere."}, {"question": "In a minimum function", "opta": "the degree of numerator and denominator are equal", "optb": "the degree of numerator and denominator are unequal", "optc": "the degree of numerator is one more than degree of denominator", "optd": "the degree of numerator is one less than degree of denominator", "ans": "A", "explanation": "If degrees of numerator and denominator were unequal, a pole or zero can be removed. Such a function cannot be a minimum function. Therefore degrees of numerator and denominator must be equal."}, {"question": "When a current source I is suddenly connected across a two terminal relaxed RC circuit at time t = 0, the voltage across the current source is shown in figure. The RC circuit is", "opta": "a series combination of R and C", "optb": "a parallel combination of R and C", "optc": "a series combination of R and parallel combination of R and C", "optd": "a pure capacitor", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Initially capacitor behaves as short-circuit and finally as open circuit."}, {"question": "The driving-point impedance Z(s) of a network has a pole-zero locations as shown in the figure. If Z(0) = 3, then Z (s) is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "From figure, The impedance function\n \nand Z(0) =  while in question Z(0) = 3\n  = 3  k = 2."}, {"question": "and i(t) is a unit step, then V(t) in the steady state is given by", "opta": "4/9", "optb": "4/3", "optc": "0", "optd": "\u221e", "ans": "A", "explanation": "= 4/9."}, {"question": "For a transmission line open circuit and short circuit impedances are 20 &ohm; and 5 &ohm;. Then characteristic impedance is", "opta": "100 &ohm;", "optb": "50 &ohm;", "optc": "25 &ohm;", "optd": "10 &ohm;", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Z0 = Zoc Zsc ."}, {"question": "The terms RMS and average values apply only to sine waves.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "These terms are applicable to all waveshapes."}, {"question": "The drift velocity of electrons is", "opta": "very small as compared to speed of light", "optb": "equal to speed of light", "optc": "almost equal to speed of light", "optd": "half the speed of light", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Drift velocity of electrons is very small."}, {"question": "Wave A = 100 sin \u03c9t and wave B = 100 cos \u03c9t. Then", "opta": "rms values of the two waves are equal", "optb": "rms values of A is more than that of B", "optc": "rms values of A is less than that of B", "optd": "rms values of the two waves may or may not be equal", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since peak values are equal, their rms values are equal irrespective of phase difference."}, {"question": "Z(c) for the network shown in the figure is  The value of C and R are, respectively", "opta": "1/6 F and 4 &ohm;", "optb": "2/9 F and 9/2 &ohm;", "optc": "2/3 F and 1/2 &ohm;", "optd": "1/2 F and 1 &ohm;", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In an R-C series circuit excited by a voltage E, the charge across capacitor at t = 0+ is", "opta": "0", "optb": "CE", "optc": "CE (1 - e-t/RC)", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Voltage across a capacitor cannot change instantaneously."}, {"question": "Two networks are cascaded through an ideal buffer. If td1 and td2 are delay times of network, the overall delay time is", "opta": "td1 + td2", "optb": "t2d1 + t2d2", "optc": "td1 + td2", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "In cascaded networks delay times are added."}, {"question": "A series RC circuit has R = 5 &ohm; and C = 10 \u03bcF. The current in the circuit is 5 sin 20000t. The applied voltage is", "opta": "252 sin (20000t + 45\u00b0)", "optb": "252 sin (20000t - 45\u00b0)", "optc": "252 sin 20000t", "optd": "252 sin (20000t - 90\u00b0)", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Z = R2 + XC2 = 50\nV = 550 sin(20000 t - 45\u00b0)\nV = 252 sin(20000 t - 45\u00b0)"}, {"question": "A capacitor stores 0.15C at 5 V. Its capacitance is", "opta": "0.75 F", "optb": "0.75 \u03bcF", "optc": "0.03 F", "optd": "0.03 \u03bcF", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Q = CV or 0.15 = C(5) or C = 0.03 F."}, {"question": "A 0.5 \u03bcF capacitor is connected across a 10 V battery. After a long time, the circuit current and voltage across capacitor will be", "opta": "0.5 A and 0 V", "optb": "0 A and 10 V", "optc": "20 A and 5 V", "optd": "0.05 A and 5 V", "ans": "B", "explanation": "When the capacitor is fully charged, i = 0 and voltage across capacitor is equal to battery voltage."}, {"question": "For node 1 in figure, KCL equation is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "i(t) is the incoming current. The currents leaving node 1 are"}, {"question": "In the circuit of figure, the switch is closed at t = 0. At t = 0+ the current through C is", "opta": "4 A", "optb": "2.5 A", "optc": "3.1 A", "optd": "0", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Capacitor behaves as a short-circuit at t = 0."}, {"question": "A cable has an insulation resistance of 1010 ohms. If the length is doubled, the insulation resistance will be", "opta": "2 x 1010 &ohm;", "optb": "0.5 x 1010 &ohm;", "optc": "1010 &ohm;", "optd": "4 x 1010 &ohm;", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Insulation resistance of cable is inversely proportional to length."}, {"question": ", i(t) =", "opta": "3e-4t - e-5t", "optb": "3e-4t - 2e-3t", "optc": "2e-4t - 5e-2t", "optd": "3e-4t - e-t", "ans": "B", "explanation": "i(t) = 3e-4t - 2e-3t"}, {"question": "In the figure shown, A1, A2, A3 are identical Ammeters. If A1 and A3 read 5 and 13 A respectively, reading of A2 will be", "opta": "8", "optb": "13 A", "optc": "18", "optd": "12 A", "ans": "D", "explanation": "A2 = 132 - 25  12 A."}, {"question": "Which of the following pairs are correctly matched? Brune's realisation : realisation with ideal transformer.Cauer realisation : ladder realisation.Bott Duffin realisation : with non ideal transformer. Select the answer using the following codes:", "opta": "1, 2 and 3", "optb": "2 and 3", "optc": "1 and 3", "optd": "1 and 2", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Bott Duffins realisation does not use transformer."}, {"question": "The synthesis of minimum function was suggested by", "opta": "O'Brune", "optb": "R. Richards", "optc": "Bott and Duffin", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The procedure is called Brune's synthesis."}, {"question": "C = (2) (energy)/V2", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "A 3 phase balanced supply feeds 3 phase unbalanced load. Power supplied to the load can be measured by using 2 wattmeterone wattmeter3 wattmeter Which of the above statements is correct?", "opta": "1 and 2", "optb": "1 and 3", "optc": "2 and 3", "optd": "3 alone", "ans": "B", "explanation": "A minimum of 2 wattmeters is required to measure 3 phase power. Of course power can be measured by putting one wattmeter in each phase."}, {"question": "Which of the following is correct for a driving point functions?", "opta": "The real parts of all poles must be negative", "optb": "The real parts of all poles and zeros must be negative", "optc": "The real parts of all poles and zeros must be negative or zero", "optd": "The real parts of all zeros must be negative", "ans": "C", "explanation": "It is a necessary condition for response to be stable."}, {"question": "An infinite ladder is constructed with 1 &ohm; and 2 &ohm; resistors shown below.", "opta": "8.18 A", "optb": "0 A", "optc": "9 A", "optd": "can't determined", "ans": "C", "explanation": "R = 1 + (2 || R)\n R = 2\n."}, {"question": "In the circuit of figure the voltage across capacitor when switch is closed at t = \u221e is", "opta": "0 V", "optb": "20 V", "optc": "very large", "optd": "7.5 V", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Voltage across capacitor = voltage across 3&ohm; resistance ="}, {"question": "In the series circuit shown in figure, for series resonance, the value of the coupling coefficient, K will be", "opta": "0.25", "optb": "0.5", "optc": "0.1", "optd": "1", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Mutual inductance wm = \u03c9k L1L2\n m = k. 2. 8j2 = 4k. j\nZ = 20 - j10 + j2 + j6 + 2.4kj - 2j + 8kj = 0 at resonance\n -2 = -8k\nk = 1/4  0.25 ."}, {"question": "The degree of the nodes 1, 2, 3, 4 is", "opta": "2", "optb": "3", "optc": "2 for 1, 2, 3, and 3 for 4", "optd": "all 3", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Degree of node is the no.of branch incident to it."}, {"question": "In an RC series circuit R = 100 &ohm; and XC = 10 &ohm;. In this circuit", "opta": "the current and voltage are in phase", "optb": "the current leads the voltage by about 6\u00b0", "optc": "the current leads the voltage by about 84\u00b0", "optd": "the current lags the voltage by about 6\u00b0", "ans": "B", "explanation": "In RC circuit the current leads the voltage."}, {"question": "The impedance of an RC series circuit is 12 &ohm; at f= 50 Hz. At f= 200 Hz, the impedance will be", "opta": "more than 12", "optb": "less than 3", "optc": "more than 3 &ohm; but less than 12 &ohm;", "optd": "more than 12 &ohm; but less than 24 &ohm;", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Z = R2 + XC2. When f is made four times, XC becomes one-fourth but R remains the same."}, {"question": "A current is flowing through a conductor with non-uniform area of cross-section. Then", "opta": "current will be different at different cross-sections.", "optb": "current will be the same at all the cross-sections.", "optc": "current will be different but current density will be same at all the cross-sections", "optd": "current will be the same but current density will be different at different cross-sections.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Current density = current/area of cross-section. Same current throughout the conductor. \nSince, area of cross-section is non-uniform, current density will be different at different cross-sections."}, {"question": "A series RL circuit has . If a voltage 4 sint + 4t is applied, the steady state current will be", "opta": "4 sin (4t - 45\u00b0)", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "R = 4 &ohm;, L = 1 H, \u03c9 = 4 rad/sec, XL = 4 &ohm;"}, {"question": "The electrical energy required to heat a bucket of water to a certain temperature is 2 kWh. If heat losses, are 25%, the energy input is", "opta": "2.67 kWh", "optb": "3 kWh", "optc": "2.5 kWh", "optd": "3.5 kWh", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since 25% of input is lost, 0.75 Input = 2 or input ="}, {"question": "The circuit in figure will act as ideal current source with respect to terminals A and B when frequency is", "opta": "0", "optb": "1 rad/sec", "optc": "4 rad/sec", "optd": "16 rad/sec", "ans": "B", "explanation": "When \u03c9 = 4 rad/sec \u03c9L and  are equal."}, {"question": "The current rating of a cable depends on", "opta": "length of cable", "optb": "diameter of cable", "optc": "both length and diameter of cable", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Current rating depends only on area of cross-section and hence diameter."}, {"question": "In an ac circuit, the maximum and minimum values of power factor can be", "opta": "2 and 0", "optb": "1 and 0", "optc": "0 and -1", "optd": "1 and -1", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Power factor is maximum and equal to 1 for purely resistive load. Power factor is minimum and equal to zero for purely reactive load."}, {"question": "The time constant of the circuit in figure shown.", "opta": "RC", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Time constant  Req.C\nwhen V is shorted and R is seen from C then Req = R || R = R/2 \n."}, {"question": "In the circuit shown in given figure, the values of i(0+) and I(\u221e), will be respectively", "opta": "zero and 1.5 A", "optb": "1.5 A and 3 A", "optc": "3 A and zero", "optd": "3 A and 1.5 A", "ans": "C", "explanation": "I(t) = 6 e-t - 3 e-0.5t\nat t = 0, I(0) = 3A\nat t = \u221e, I(\u221e) = 0."}, {"question": "A two branch parallel circuit has a 20 &ohm; resistance and 1 H inductance in one branch and a 100 \u03bcF capacitor in the second branch. It is fed from 100 V ac supply, at resonance, the input impedance of the circuit is", "opta": "500 &ohm;", "optb": "50 &ohm;", "optc": "20 &ohm;", "optd": "5 &ohm;", "ans": "A", "explanation": "At parallel resonance circuit impedance = ."}, {"question": "The impedance matrices of two, two-port network are given by  and . If these two networks are connected in series, the impedance matrix of the resulting two-port network will be", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "indeterminate", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Impedance matrices will be added."}, {"question": "As compared to the number of network elements in Brune synthesis, the number of network elements Bott-and Duffin in realization is", "opta": "more", "optb": "less", "optc": "equal", "optd": "any of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "To avoid mutually coupled inductors, more elements are needed."}, {"question": "A sinusoidal voltage has peak to peak value of 100 V. The rms value is", "opta": "50 V", "optb": "70.7 V", "optc": "35.35 V", "optd": "141.41 V", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Peak value = 50 V, rms value =  = 35.35 V."}, {"question": "A capacitor is needed for an ac circuit of 230 V, 50 Hz the peak voltage rating of the capacitor should be", "opta": "230 V", "optb": "0.5 x 230 V", "optc": "2 x 230V", "optd": "230/2V", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Peak voltage rating = 2 (rms voltage rating)."}, {"question": "The current wave shape shown in figure (1) is applied to a circuit element. The voltage across the element is shown in figure (2). The element is", "opta": "R", "optb": "L", "optc": "C", "optd": "Semiconductor", "ans": "C", "explanation": "When a current pulse is applied to a capacitor the voltage rises linearly and becomes constant at the end of pulse."}, {"question": "In figure, the current supplied by battery immediately after switching on the circuit is", "opta": "1 A", "optb": "4 A", "optc": "10 A", "optd": "0", "ans": "A", "explanation": "At t = 0, inductance behaves as open circuit."}, {"question": "RMS value of i(t) = 10[1 + sin (- t)] is", "opta": "10", "optb": "10/2", "optc": "l50", "optd": "102", "ans": "C", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "A cycloconverter can be", "opta": "step down", "optb": "step up", "optc": "step down or step up", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The output frequency can be more or less than input frequency."}, {"question": "In the below figure the average load current is 15 A. The rms value of transformer secondary current is", "opta": "15 A", "optb": "10.61 A", "optc": "7.5 A", "optd": "14.14 A", "ans": "B", "explanation": "RMS secondary current =  = 15/1.414 = 10.608 A."}, {"question": "In a 3 phase fully controlled converter the firing frequency is", "opta": "3 times the line frequency", "optb": "6 times the line frequency", "optc": "9 times the line frequency", "optd": "12 times the line frequency", "ans": "B", "explanation": "It is a 6 pulse converter."}, {"question": "Two thyristor of same rating and same specifications", "opta": "will have equal turn on and turn off periods", "optb": "will have equal turn on but unequal turn off periods", "optc": "may have equal or unequal turn on and turn off periods", "optd": "will have unequal turn on and turn off periods", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Turn on and turn off times of similar SCRs may not be same."}, {"question": "The amount of dielectric heating is inversely proportional to frequency.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "It is proportional to frequency."}, {"question": "A semiconverter feeding an RLE load operates in", "opta": "first quadrant only", "optb": "first and second quadrants", "optc": "first and fourth quadrants", "optd": "first and third quadrants", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Semiconvertor operates only in first quadrant."}, {"question": "The phenomenon of overlap in converter operation due to", "opta": "source resistance", "optb": "source inductance", "optc": "both source resistance and source inductance", "optd": "high value of firing angle", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Source inductance delays turn off and hence causes overlap."}, {"question": "A thyristor has a maximum allowable junction temperature of 120\u00b0C and the ambient temperature is 40\u00b0C. If thermal resistance is 1.6\u00b0 C/W, the maximum allowable internal power dissipation is", "opta": "20 W", "optb": "50 W", "optc": "92 W", "optd": "128 W", "ans": "B", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "For a 12 pulse operation, the two 6 pulse units are fed by", "opta": "Y - Y and Y - Y transformers", "optb": "\u0394 - \u0394 and \u0394 - \u0394 transformers", "optc": "Y - Y and Y - \u0394 transformers", "optd": "Y - \u0394 and Y - \u0394 transformers", "ans": "C", "explanation": "30\u00b0 phase difference is necessary."}, {"question": "In a single phase full wave converter (M - 2 connection) feeding a highly inductive load, the firing angle for each thyristor is a in the respective half cycle. The period of conduction of each thyristor is", "opta": "p - a", "optb": "p", "optc": "p + a", "optd": "p - 2a", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since conduction is from a to p + a, period of conduction is p in each half cycle."}, {"question": "An SCR is triggered at 40\u00b0 in the positive half cycle only. The average anode current is 50 A. If the firing angle is changed to 80\u00b0, the average anode current is likely to be", "opta": "50 A", "optb": "25 A", "optc": "less than 50 A but more than 25 A", "optd": "less than 25 A", "ans": "C", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "The characteristics of a non-linear resistance is i = kv4. If i becomes 100 times, v becomes", "opta": "about 100 times", "optb": "about 10 times", "optc": "about 3 times", "optd": "about twice", "ans": "C", "explanation": "v \u221d (i)1/4 \u221d (100)1/4 \u2248 3."}, {"question": "In a step down chopper using pulse width modulation, Ton = 3 x 10-3 and Toff = 1 x 10-3 s. The chopping frequency is", "opta": "333.33", "optb": "250", "optc": "500", "optd": "1000", "ans": "B", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "Thyristors are suitable for dc circuit breakers but not for ac circuit breakers.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "They are suitable for both dc and ac circuit breakers."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  Inverters and choppers use fast switching thyristors Reason (R):  Fast switching SCR has low turn off time.", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R correct but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is correct but R is wrong", "optd": "A is wrong but R is correct", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Low turn off time enables fast switching."}, {"question": "The value of capacitor C for dynamic equalising circuit of series connected thyristors is determined by", "opta": "forward characteristics of thyristors", "optb": "reverse recovery characteristics of thyristors", "optc": "both forward and reverse recovery characteristics of thyristors", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Value of C is proportional to maximum difference between reverse charge of SCRs in series."}, {"question": "A chopper", "opta": "converts constant voltage dc into ac and then into variable voltage dc", "optb": "converts constant voltage dc into variable voltage dc directly", "optc": "converts ac of one frequency into ac of another frequency", "optd": "converts ac to dc", "ans": "B", "explanation": "A chopper is a dc-ac converter. It converts a fixed dc voltage into a variable dc voltage."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  If the duty cycle of chopper is low the current would not become discontinuousReason (R):  If the time constant L/R of the load in chopper is low the current may become discontinuous.", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R correct but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is correct but R is wrong", "optd": "A is wrong but R is correct", "ans": "C", "explanation": "If duty cycle is low, current may become discontinuous."}, {"question": "In a single phase full wave regulator, the firing angles in the positive and negative half cycles are generally", "opta": "equal", "optb": "different", "optc": "equal or different", "optd": "different but sometimes equal", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Firing angles are kept equal to get symmetrical output voltage."}, {"question": "An electric heater is controlled by thyristors through on-off control. If a = 0.4, the heating is", "opta": "16% maximum", "optb": "40% of maximum", "optc": "60% of maximum", "optd": "84% of maximum", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Vl = V a. Therefore Vl2 - V2 (a). Heating is proportional to a."}, {"question": "A two winding transformer is feeding a single phase half wave rectifier circuit. The load is purely resistive. The rms value of transformer secondary current is Is and rms value of load current in Irms. Then", "opta": "Is = Irms irrespective of the value of firing angle", "optb": "Is = 0.5 Irms irrespective of the value of firing angle", "optc": "Is = Irms if firing angle is less than 30\u00b0", "optd": "Is = Irms if firing angle is more than 30\u00b0", "ans": "A", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "The terminals of a power BJT are called", "opta": "emitter, base, collector", "optb": "emitter, base, drain", "optc": "source, base, drain", "optd": "source, base, collector", "ans": "A", "explanation": "In a BJT terminals are emitter, base and collector irrespective of rating."}, {"question": "In single phase half wave regulator, the average current over one full cycle", "opta": "is always positive", "optb": "may be positive or negative", "optc": "may be negative", "optd": "is always negative", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The input current during positive half cycle is less than that during negative half cycle."}, {"question": "The dynamic equalising circuit consists of a series combination of capacitor C and resistor RC across each thyristor. This resistance RC (along with parallel connected diode)", "opta": "limits charging current", "optb": "limits discharging current", "optc": "limits both charging and discharging currents", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Discharge current flows through Re ."}, {"question": "A single phase semiconverter is feeding a highly inductive load and has freewheeling diode across the load. The waveshapes of output voltage and output current", "opta": "are similar", "optb": "are not similar", "optc": "may be similar or dissimilar", "optd": "are similar only if firing angle is zero", "ans": "B", "explanation": "When freewheeling diode conducts output current exists but output voltage is zero."}, {"question": "Current derating may be necessary when thyristors are operating in", "opta": "series", "optb": "parallel", "optc": "series or parallel", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since current does not divide equally, current derating is necessary."}, {"question": "If duty cycle is a and the load is a resistance R, the rms value of output voltage is", "opta": "aV", "optb": "a V", "optc": "a2V", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "RMS output voltage\nVL = a V."}, {"question": "For a BJT a = 0.98, then \u03b2 =", "opta": "0.02", "optb": "0.5", "optc": "4.9", "optd": "48", "ans": "D", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  Power transistor has lower switching time than SCR Reason (R):  Power transistor has greater switching time than SCR", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R correct but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is correct but R is wrong", "optd": "A is wrong but R is correct", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Power transistor does not have high  rating."}, {"question": "A 3 kV circuit uses SCR of 800 V rating. If derating is 25%, the number of SCRs in series is", "opta": "4", "optb": "5", "optc": "6", "optd": "8", "ans": "B", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "In a circuit using a full wave converter (M - 2 connection) the PIV of each thyristor is 400 V. For the same output voltage and fully controlled bridge converter, PIV will be", "opta": "400 V", "optb": "800 V", "optc": "200 V", "optd": "2002 V", "ans": "C", "explanation": "In bridge connection PIV is half of that in M-2 connection."}, {"question": "A dc separately excited motor has constant field current. The armature is fed from a single phase supply through a full converter. When a = 0, speed is 500 rpm. If a = 45\u00b0, the speed is likely to be", "opta": "about 350 rpm", "optb": "about 250 rpm", "optc": "about 175 rpm", "optd": "about 125 rpm", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Average output voltage \u221d cos a and therefore reduced to 0.707 of the value for a = 0. Speed is nearly proportional to voltage."}, {"question": "In a multiphase chopper, all choppers operate together.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "They operate in a sequence."}, {"question": "The terminals of a power MOSFET are called", "opta": "emitter, base, collector", "optb": "source, gate, drain", "optc": "source, base, drain", "optd": "emitter, gate, drain", "ans": "B", "explanation": "In a MOSFET terminals are source, gate, drain irrespective of rating."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  The surge current which an SCR can withstand is much higher than rms on state current.Reason (R):  The duration of surge current is very small.", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R correct but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is correct but R is wrong", "optd": "A is wrong but R is correct", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since duration of surge current is small, the associated energy is small."}, {"question": "A single phase half wave controlled rectifier circuit has a free wheeling diode. The load is a combination of R and L. The firing angle is a. The period of conduction of SCR and free wheeling diode respectively are", "opta": "a < \u03c9t < p and p < \u03c9t < (2p + a)", "optb": "a < \u03c9t < p and p < \u03c9t < 2p", "optc": "a < \u03c9t < (p + a) and (p + a) < \u03c9t < 2p", "optd": "a < \u03c9t < p and p < \u03c9t < (2p - a)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "SCR conducts from a to p and free wheeling diode from p to (2p + a)."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  A transistor requires a continuous base signal for conduction but a thyristor requires a gate pulse.Reason (R):  Transistor find widespread application in power electronic circuits.", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R correct but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is correct but R is wrong", "optd": "A is wrong but R is correct", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Transistors are used but not very widely."}, {"question": "In a thyristor the gate current is increased, then", "opta": "anode current will increase", "optb": "anode current will decrease", "optc": "anode current will remain constant", "optd": "anode current may increase or decrease", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Gate current does not affect the magnitude of anode current."}, {"question": "Thyristors are not suitable for logic circuits.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Thyristors can be used for logic circuits."}, {"question": "A single phase half wave rectifier is feeding a resistive load. Input voltage v = Vm sin \u03c9t. The output dc voltage is Vdc and output rms voltage is Vrms . If firing angle is 180\u00b0, Vdc and Vrms respectively are", "opta": "0 and 0", "optb": "", "optc": "0 and - Vm", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Put a = 180\u00b0 in Eqs  \nOtherwise also a = 180\u00b0 means no conduction. \nHence zero output voltage."}, {"question": "The number of leads in an SCR are :", "opta": "2", "optb": "3", "optc": "4", "optd": "5", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Anode, cathode and gate."}, {"question": "In a single phase full wave converter (M-2 connection) feeding on R - L load, the input voltage is v = Vm sin \u03c9t. The expression for dc output voltage is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Due to inductive load the period of conduction is a to p + a in each half cycle."}, {"question": "A thyristor has a turn on time of 6 \u03bcs. If the anode circuit is inductive, the turn on time will be", "opta": "6 \u03bcs", "optb": "less than 6\u03bcs", "optc": "more than 6 \u03bcs", "optd": "either 6 \u03bcs or less", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Inductive load increases the turn on time."}, {"question": "The total number of leads in reverse conducting thyristor is", "opta": "2", "optb": "3", "optc": "1", "optd": "4", "ans": "B", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  A TRIAC is a bidirectional SCR.Reason (R):  A TRIAC is a four layers 3 terminal device and can conduct in both directions.", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R correct but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is correct but R is wrong", "optd": "A is wrong but R is correct", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since a TRIAC can conduct in both directions it is bi directional SCR."}, {"question": "If Vdc1 is the dc output voltage in half wave controlled rectifier circuit feeding resistive load and Vdc2 is the dc output voltage in full wave controlled rectifier circuit (M - 2 connection) feeding resistive load, then", "opta": "Vdc1 = 0.5 Vdc2 for all values of firing angle", "optb": "Vdc1 = Vdc2 for all values of firing angle", "optc": "Vdc1 \u2264 0.5 Vdc2 for all values of firing angle", "optd": "Vdc1 \u2265 0.5 Vdc2 for all values of firing angle", "ans": "A", "explanation": "and Vdc =  (1 + cos a)."}, {"question": "A semi converter operates in two quadrants.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "It operates only in quadrant."}, {"question": "Figure shows a chopper feeding RLE load, The free wheeling diode conducts when", "opta": "thyristor is on", "optb": "thyristor is off", "optc": "both when thyristor is on and thyristor is off", "optd": "partly when thyristor is off and partly when thyristor is on", "ans": "B", "explanation": "FD is forward biased only when thyristor is off."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  An ideal rectifier should have unity harmonic factorReason (R):  An ideal rectifier should have unity displacement factor.", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R correct but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is correct but R is wrong", "optd": "A is wrong but R is correct", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Ideal rectifier should have zero harmonic factor and unity displacement factor."}, {"question": "A single phase half wave rectifier is feeding a resistive load. When a = 0, dc output voltage is 127 V. When a = 30\u00b0, the dc output voltage will be about", "opta": "127 V", "optb": "120 V", "optc": "110 V", "optd": "100 V", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Using Eq  \n = 0.933. \nHence Vdc for 30\u00b0 firing angle = 0.933 x 127 = \u2248 120 V."}, {"question": "The noise generated by a resistor depends upon", "opta": "its resistance value", "optb": "its operating temperature", "optc": "both its resistance value and operating temperature", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a superheterodyne receiver", "opta": "the IF stage has better selectivity than RF stage", "optb": "the RF stage has better selectivity than IF stage", "optc": "the RF stage has same selectivity than IF stage", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The function of an AM detector circuit is to", "opta": "rectify the input signal", "optb": "discard the carrier", "optc": "provide audio signal", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following should be used in order to prevent overloading or the last IF amplifier in a receiver?", "opta": "Variable selectivity", "optb": "Variable sensitivity", "optc": "Double conversion", "optd": "Squelch", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Most popular IF for receivers tuning to 540 to 1650 kHz is", "opta": "433 kHz", "optb": "455 kHz", "optc": "545 kHz", "optd": "555 kHz", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a broadcast superheterodyne receiver", "opta": "the local oscillator operates below the signal frequency", "optb": "local oscillator frequency is normally double the IF", "optc": "RF amplifier normally works at kHz above the carrier frequency", "optd": "mixer input must be tuned to the signal frequency", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A duplexer is a device used to", "opta": "feed more than one receiver from a single antenna", "optb": "connect two transmitters to the same antenna", "optc": "connect a receiver and a transmitter to the same antenna", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A heterodyne frequency changer is called a", "opta": "Modulator", "optb": "Mixer", "optc": "Demodulator", "optd": "Frequency translator", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "RF amplifiers are used in radio receivers for", "opta": "improved image frequency rejection", "optb": "improved rejection of adjacent unwanted signals", "optc": "prevention of re-radiation of the local oscillator through the antenna of the receiver", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The sensitivity curve of a standard receiver is represented by", "opta": "curve A", "optb": "curve B", "optc": "curve C", "optd": "curve D", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which are the popular IF frequencies for microwave and radar receivers operating on frequencies in the range 1 to 10 GHz", "opta": "30, 60 and 70 kHz", "optb": "3, 6 and 7 kHz", "optc": "30, 60 and 70 MHz", "optd": "3, 6 and 7 GHz", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a ratio detector", "opta": "the linearity is worse than in a phase discriminator", "optb": "the output is twice that obtainable from a similar phase discriminator", "optc": "stabilization against signal strength variations is provided", "optd": "the circuit is the same as in a discriminator, except that the diodes are reversed", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Neutralization is used in RF amplifiers to", "opta": "stop oscillation", "optb": "increase bandwidth", "optc": "improve selectivity", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When fs is the signal frequency and fi is the intermediate frequency, then image frequency fsi is given by", "opta": "fsi = fs - 2fi", "optb": "fsi = fs + 2fi", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "It is known that noise phase modulates the FM wave. As the noise side band frequency approaches the carrier frequency, the noise amplitude", "opta": "will increase", "optb": "will decrease", "optc": "will remain constant", "optd": "will reduce to negligible value", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a receiver, which of the following device has IF input but RF output?", "opta": "Demodulator", "optb": "Loudspeaker", "optc": "Audio amplifier", "optd": "Frequency changer", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Transistor are free from which type of noise?", "opta": "Resistance noise", "optb": "Partition noise", "optc": "Flicker noise", "optd": "Shot noise", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Standard AM radio broadcasts are confined to", "opta": "MF", "optb": "HF", "optc": "VHF", "optd": "UHF", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a radio receiver with simple AGC", "opta": "the highest AGC voltage is produced between stations", "optb": "the faster the AGC time constant, the more accurate the output", "optc": "an increase in signal strength produces more AGC", "optd": "the audio stage gain is normally controlled by AGC", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following cannot be used to demodulate SSB?", "opta": "Complete phase-shift generator", "optb": "Product detector", "optc": "Diode balanced modulator", "optd": "Bipolar transistor balanced modulator", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A transmitter serial current contains", "opta": "carrier frequencies", "optb": "audio frequencies", "optc": "radio frequencies", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a broadcast superheterodynes receiver having no RF amplifier, the loaded Q of the antenna coupling circuit is 100. If the intermediate frequency is 455 kHz. The image frequency at 25 MHz will be", "opta": "24.09 MHz", "optb": "24.54 MHz", "optc": "25.45 MHz", "optd": "25.91 MHz", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a communication system, noise is most likely to affect the signal", "opta": "at the transmitter", "optb": "in the channel", "optc": "in the information source", "optd": "at the destination", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The noise produced by a resistor is proportional to", "opta": "absolute temperature", "optb": "(absolute temperature)2", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a radio receiver, if the intermediate frequency is too high", "opta": "Selectivity will be poor", "optb": "Tracking difficulties will be least", "optc": "Adjacent channel rejection will improve", "optd": "All of the above will occur", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a superheterodyne receiver, the IF is 455 kHz. If it is tuned to  1200 kHz, the image frequency will be", "opta": "1655 kHz", "optb": "2110 kHz", "optc": "745 kHz", "optd": "910 kHz", "ans": "B", "explanation": "A signal (image) can interfere with a superheterodyne receiver if fits the following equation.\nImage = Signal  +/-  2 x I.F.\nWhich says that a signal has the capacity to interfere with a superhet receiver if its frequency is equal to the signal frequency (1200 kHz in our question) plus or minus twice the IF (455 kHz in our question).\nSo one possible image is: 1200 + ( 2 x 455 ) = 2110 kHz (possible).\nAnd the other: 1200 - ( 2 x 455 )  = 290 kHz (not likely)."}, {"question": "The selectivity of most receivers is determined largely by", "opta": "sensitivity", "optb": "characteristics of IF section", "optc": "antenna direction", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a superheterodyne receiver with an IF of 450 kHz is tuned to a signal at 1200 kHz. The image frequency is", "opta": "750 kHz", "optb": "990 kHz", "optc": "1650 kHz", "optd": "2100 kHz", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a broadcast superheterodynes receiver having no RF amplifier, the loaded Q of the antenna coupling circuit is 100. If the intermediate frequency is 455 kHz. The rejection ratio at 25 MHz will be", "opta": "1.116", "optb": "1.386", "optc": "2.116", "optd": "2.386", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "As compared to tuned radio frequency receivers which of the following is the advantage of using superheterodyne receivers?", "opta": "High gain and better sensitivity", "optb": "Better selectivity at high frequencies", "optc": "Stability", "optd": "Noise suppression", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a radio receiver, if the intermediate frequency is too low", "opta": "Image-frequency rejection will improve", "optb": "Selectivity will be too sharp", "optc": "The frequency selectivity of the local oscillator will have to be lowered", "optd": "All of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "FM amplifier in a superheterodyne receiver", "opta": "increases selectivity", "optb": "suppresses noise", "optc": "provides improved tracking", "optd": "improves the rejection of the image frequency", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Padders are used in a receiver to", "opta": "discard the carrier", "optb": "facilitate tracking", "optc": "filter the input signal", "optd": "suppress noise", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a radio receiver, the local oscillator is tuned to a frequency", "opta": "lower than the incoming frequency", "optb": "higher than the incoming frequency", "optc": "equal to incoming frequency", "optd": "any of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following oscillator is generally not used at VHF?", "opta": "Colpitts oscillator", "optb": "Clapp oscillator", "optc": "Armstrong oscillator", "optd": "Ultra Audio oscillator", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An unmodulated voltage 10 V effective is applied to a dioxide detector in which load resistance is 4 x 10-5 ohms. A micrometer shows that the rectified DC current in this resistance is 30 A. The input resistance of the detector is", "opta": "114 kW", "optb": "336 kW", "optc": "384 kW", "optd": "455 kW", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The output of a diode detector contains", "opta": "D.C. voltage", "optb": "modulating signal", "optc": "RF ripple", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following noise does not occur in transistors?", "opta": "Partition noise", "optb": "Shot noise", "optc": "Flicker noise", "optd": "Resistance noise", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Noise generated in a resistor is also known as", "opta": "partition noise", "optb": "white noise", "optc": "thermal noise", "optd": "shot noise", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is used to provide tracking between RF amplifier and local oscillator stages of receiver?", "opta": "Variable tuning inductor", "optb": "Ganged tuning inductor", "optc": "Variable capacitor", "optd": "Variable preset", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The selectivity of a radio receiver is", "opta": "its ability to reject adjacent unwanted signals", "optb": "its ability to amplify weak signals", "optc": "the frequency at which it gives maximum amplification to signal.", "optd": "its ability to suppress noise.", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If the intermediate frequency of a superheterodyne receiver falls within the tuning range of the receiver", "opta": "Unsuitability will occur", "optb": "Heterodyne whistles will be heard", "optc": "Tuning to the frequency band immediately adjacent to the intermediate frequency will become impossible", "optd": "All of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "EM 84 tube is used in radio receivers as", "opta": "audio amplifier", "optb": "RF amplifier", "optc": "full wave rectifier", "optd": "magic eye", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following statement about receivers is false?", "opta": "Double conversion is used to improve image rejection", "optb": "Double conversion is used to improve selectivity", "optc": "Variable sensitivity is used to improve selectivity", "optd": "Variable sensitivity is used to eliminate selective fading", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Modulated carrier power in FM", "opta": "increases with modulating signal power", "optb": "decreases with modulating signal power", "optc": "is independent of the modulating signal power", "optd": "none", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In superheterodyne receivers, the local oscillator is used to", "opta": "detect the modulating signal", "optb": "amplify the received modulated carrier", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is same in AM and FM receivers?", "opta": "Demodulator", "optb": "AGC", "optc": "IF amplifier", "optd": "All of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A notch filter is sometimes used in communication receivers to", "opta": "reduce receiver gain at some specific frequency", "optb": "increase receiver gain at some specific frequency", "optc": "made selectivity more precise", "optd": "spread the bandwidth", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following is not a useful quantity for comparing the noise performance of receivers?", "opta": "Noise figure", "optb": "Noise temperature", "optc": "Input noise voltage", "optd": "Equivalent noise resistance", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following statement about the amplitude limiter is not valid?", "opta": "Leak type bias must be used", "optb": "Output must be tuned", "optc": "The circuit is always biased in class C, by virtue of the leak type bias", "optd": "When the input increases past the threshold of limiting, the gain decreases to keep the output constant", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The first geostationary satellite launched in 1965 was called", "opta": "ANIK", "optb": "EARLY BIRD (Intelsat-I)", "optc": "WESTAR", "optd": "MOLNIYA", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Rotation of a geosynchronous satellite means its", "opta": "drift from stationary position", "optb": "wobbling", "optc": "three-axis stabilization", "optd": "three-dimensional stabilization", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The present total cost per watt of power generation in geosynchronous orbit is nearly Rs.", "opta": "20", "optb": "50", "optc": "100", "optd": "5", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Noise temperature of Sun is more than __________ \u00b0K.", "opta": "1000", "optb": "5000", "optc": "100000", "optd": "500", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A 20 m antenna gives a certain uplink gain at frequencies of 4/6 GHz. For getting same gain in the 20/30 GHz band, antenna size required is metre.", "opta": "100", "optb": "4", "optc": "1", "optd": "10", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The discussing sharing of a communication satellite by many geographically dispersed Earth station, DAMA means", "opta": "Demand-Assigned Multiple Access", "optb": "Decibel Attenuated Microwave Access", "optc": "Digital Analog Master Antenna", "optd": "Dynamically-Assigned Multiple Access", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The angle subtended by earth at geostationary communication satellite is", "opta": "17.34\u00b0", "optb": "51.4\u00b0", "optc": "120\u00b0", "optd": "60\u00b0", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The INTELSAT-IV satellite launched in 1974 had two earth coverage antenna and two narrower-angle antennas subtending 4.5\u00b0. The signal from narrow-angle antenna was stronger than that from earth- coverage antenna by a factor of", "opta": "17.34/4.5", "optb": "17.34 x 4.5", "optc": "(17.34/4.5)2", "optd": "(17.34/4.5)4", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A transponder is a satellite equipment which", "opta": "receives a signal from Earth station and amplifies", "optb": "changes the frequency of the received signal", "optc": "retransmits the received signal", "optd": "does all of the above-mentioned functions", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A geosynchronous satellite", "opta": "has the same period a that of the Earth", "optb": "has a circular orbit", "optc": "rotates in the equatorial plane", "optd": "has all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To make antenna more directional, either its size must be increased or", "opta": "the number of its feed horns must be increased", "optb": "the frequency of its transmission must be increased", "optc": "its effective isotropic radiated power (EIRP) must be increased", "optd": "its footprint must be increased", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "India's first domestic geostationary satellite 1NSAT-IA was launched on 10th April 1982 from", "opta": "USSR", "optb": "USA", "optc": "UK", "optd": "UP", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Satellite launch sites are invariably located on Eastern seaboards to ensure that", "opta": "launch takes place eastward", "optb": "expenditure of propulsion fuel is reduced during plane changing", "optc": "the satellite achieves circular orbit quickly", "optd": "spent rocket motor and other launcher debris falls into the sea", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The owner of a communication satellite is usually required to keep the spacecraft on station at its assigned place in the geosynchronous orbit with an accuracy of __________ degree.", "opta": "0.1", "optb": "1.0", "optc": "2.0", "optd": "0.5", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The number of days when Earth's shadow falls on a geosynchronous satellite is", "opta": "88", "optb": "277", "optc": "5", "optd": "10", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Of the four INSAT-I satellites planned by India so for, only __________ has proved to be successful.", "opta": "INSAT-IA", "optb": "INSAT-IB", "optc": "INSAT-IC", "optd": "INSAT-ID", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Radio broadcasting is a familiar example of", "opta": "space multiplexing", "optb": "time multiplexing", "optc": "frequency multiplexing", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "As compared to 17.34\u00b0 antenna, the total increase in the signal relayed by 4.5\u00b0 antenna of INTELSAT-IV is", "opta": "14.85", "optb": "220", "optc": "78", "optd": "3.85", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following statements regarding DSI is wrong?", "opta": "It is a digital form of TASI", "optb": "Though it is more efficient than TASI, it is much slower", "optc": "A speaker has to wait (it at all) for only a few milliseconds for reallocation of channel", "optd": "It has increased the capacity of satellite channels by a factor of 2.2 or more with out degrading speech quality", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following statements regarding compandor is FALSE?", "opta": "It compresses the higher-amplitude parts of a signal before modulation and expands them back to normal again after demodulation.", "optb": "It gives preferential treatment to the weaker parts of the signal", "optc": "For weaker signals it gives a poor ratio of signal strength to quantizing error", "optd": "Weaker signals, traverse more quantum steps than they would do otherwise and so quantizing error is reduced.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The quality of a space-link is measured in terms of the __________ ratio.", "opta": "C/N", "optb": "S/N", "optc": "G/T", "optd": "EIRP", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The useful operational life of INSAT-IB (launched in 1983) is expected to end by", "opta": "1992-93", "optb": "1991-92", "optc": "1989-90", "optd": "1993-94", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "At present, the radio-frequency band mainly used by most satellites is", "opta": "EHF", "optb": "UHF", "optc": "VHF", "optd": "SHF", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Orbital disturbances of a geosynchronous satellite are caused by the", "opta": "moon", "optb": "sun", "optc": "earth", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following statement is correct?", "opta": "Satellite spacing is not affected by the bandwidth of the transmitting earth station", "optb": "Beamwidth is independent of antenna size and frequency band used", "optc": "The width of a beam in space is inversely proportional to the width of the transmitting antenna", "optd": "Use of high-frequency bands permits less number of satellites to share the orbit", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a stop-and-wait ARQ system, the transmitting terminal", "opta": "waits for positive or negative acknowled-gement from the receiving terminal after sending a block", "optb": "sends another block if positive acknowledge is received through ACK character", "optc": "resends the previous block if negative acknowledgement is received through a NAK character", "optd": "does not wait for acknowledgement after sending a block", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A geostationary satellite is one which", "opta": "hangs motionless in space about 36000 km about Earth", "optb": "travels around the Earth in 24 hours", "optc": "remains stationary above the Earth", "optd": "appears stationary to everybody on Earth", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The geostationary communication satellite APPLE is parked in the equatorial orbit at", "opta": "102\u00b0 E longitude over Sumatra", "optb": "90\u00b0 E longitude over Bangladesh", "optc": "74\u00b0 E longitude over India", "optd": "67\u00b0 E longitude over Pakistan", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Power received from Sun per m2 surface area of a geosynchronous satellite in nearly __________ watt.", "opta": "100", "optb": "500", "optc": "2000", "optd": "1000", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A certain sound has 10000 times more energy than another sound. The number of times it would sound stronger to a listener is", "opta": "40", "optb": "10000", "optc": "100", "optd": "10", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "While keeping the down-link frequency constant, the diameter of a satellite antenna is reduced by half. To offer the same EIRP over the increased coverage area, the RF output power has to be increases by a factor of", "opta": "2", "optb": "4", "optc": "8", "optd": "16", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A communication satellite is a repeater between", "opta": "a transmitting station and a receiving station", "optb": "a transmitting station and many receiving station", "optc": "many transmitting station and many receiving station", "optd": "none", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ending part of the popular teleserial Mahabharat will be beamed to the viewers", "opta": "WESTAT", "optb": "INSAT-IC", "optc": "ARABSAT", "optd": "INSAT-ID", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The most effective anti jamming technique is", "opta": "frequency hopping", "optb": "spread-spectrum modulation", "optc": "key leverage", "optd": "once-only key", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For satellite communication, standard Earth stations have antenna diameters in the range of __________ metre.", "opta": "27.5 to 30", "optb": "10 to 15", "optc": "30 to 50", "optd": "5 to 10", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The Sun blots out the transmission of a geosynchronous satellite twice a year when satellite passes directly in front of it. This outage lasts for about", "opta": "10 minutes on 5 consecutive days", "optb": "5 minutes on 10 consecutive days", "optc": "30 minutes for 5 consecutive days", "optd": "one hour for 5 consecutive days", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In satellite communication, frequency modulation is used because satellite channel has", "opta": "small bandwidth and negligible noise", "optb": "large bandwidth and severe noise", "optc": "maximum bandwidth and minimum noise", "optd": "high modulation index", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the case of a 70-MHz IF carrier for a transponder bandwidth of 36 MHz, energy must lie between MHz.", "opta": "34 and 106", "optb": "52 and 88", "optc": "106 and 142", "optd": "34 and 142", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following factor does NOT contribute to the drift of a geostationary satellite from its stationary position in space?", "opta": "Pressure of solar radiations", "optb": "Gravitational changes due to Sun and Moon", "optc": "Oblateness of the Earth", "optd": "Weight of the satellite", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In communication satellites, the up-link normally operates at a higher frequency than the down-link because it", "opta": "gives a narrow beam shining into space", "optb": "results in lesser signal attenuation", "optc": "gives better beam-shaping", "optd": "is easier to polarize a high frequency beam", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For global communication, the number of satellites needed is", "opta": "1", "optb": "3", "optc": "10", "optd": "5", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "What about the stability of system in", "opta": "system is stable", "optb": "unstable", "optc": "stable at 0.4", "optd": "cant say", "ans": "A", "explanation": "ROC include the unit circle hence it is stable."}, {"question": "Which one most appropriate dynamic system?", "opta": "y(n) + y(n - 1) + y(n + 1)", "optb": "y(n) + y(n - 1)", "optc": "y(n) = x(n)", "optd": "y(n) +  y(n - 1) + y(n + 3) = 0", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Because present output of y(n) depend upon past y(n - 1) and future y(n + 1)."}, {"question": "An energy signal has G(f) = 10. Its energy density spectrum is", "opta": "10", "optb": "100", "optc": "50", "optd": "20", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Energy density spectrum = |G(f)|2 = |10|2 = 100."}, {"question": "Consider Pole zero diagram as shown, If two Poles are moved in opposite direction towards \u03c9 = p/2 and -p/2, the filter will be", "opta": "change to high pass filter", "optb": "change to Band Pass filter", "optc": "remains same", "optd": "change to LPF", "ans": "C", "explanation": "But still we will get the same response, zero are at same position."}, {"question": "In an ac circuit the fundamental component of current wave lags the corresponding voltage wave by 20\u00b0. The third harmonic component of current wave lags the corresponding voltage by an angle.", "opta": "less than 20\u00b0", "optb": "more than 20\u00b0", "optc": "equal to 20\u00b0", "optd": "equal to or more than 20\u00b0", "ans": "B", "explanation": "For third harmonic \u03b8 = tan-1 = ."}, {"question": "If  and A + B is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Add elements individually."}, {"question": "A voltage V(t) is a Gaussian ergodic random process with a mean of zero and a variance of 4 volt2. If it is measured by a dc meter. The reading will be", "opta": "0", "optb": "4", "optc": "2", "optd": "2", "ans": "A", "explanation": "DC meter reads mean value."}, {"question": "A first order system will never be able to give a __________ response band stopband passall pass Choose the correct option", "opta": "1, 2, 3 true", "optb": "1 and 3 true, 2 false", "optc": "1, 2 are true 3 is false", "optd": "1, 2 are false, 3 is true", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Because to design band pass or band stop, transfer function of must be second order."}, {"question": "In the given figure the ratio T/d is the duty factor.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "If \u00a3[f(t)] = F(s), then \u00a3[f(t - T)] =", "opta": "est F(s)", "optb": "e-st F(s)", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "A linear system is one in which the relationship between input and output is linear. \n\nAll linear system possess the property of superposition i.e.,  if input u1 gives output y1 and input u2 gives output y2 then input u1 + u2 will give output y1 + y2. \n\nSuperposition implies homogencity i.e.,  if input u gives output y, then input ku gives output ky where k is a rational number. \n\nIn general a system is linear if a transformation T satisfies the relation\n\nT(au1 + \u03b2u2) = aT(u1) + \u03b2T(u2)\n\nwhere a and \u03b2 are constant."}, {"question": "The z-transform of a particular signal is given  whereThe system after implementation will be", "opta": "casual and stable", "optb": "non-casual and stable", "optc": "non-casual and unstable", "optd": "casual and unstable", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Include unity circle and exterior of circle hence x(z) will be stable, causal."}, {"question": "The system with given pole-zero diagram is", "opta": "casual", "optb": "non-casual", "optc": "both sided", "optd": "not-possible", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Because no.of zero is more than Pole, therefore when you find transfer function.\n\nNumerator power will higher than denominator, and such transfer functions is not realizable."}, {"question": "A pole zero pattern of a certain filter is shown in figure. This filter must be", "opta": "LPF", "optb": "BFP", "optc": "HPF", "optd": "APF", "ans": "D", "explanation": "In transfer function, no of zeros = no. of poles, hence it is all pass fliter."}, {"question": "If transfer function of a system is H(z) = 6 + z-1 + z-2 then system is", "opta": "minimun phase", "optb": "maximum phase", "optc": "mixed phase", "optd": "none", "ans": "A", "explanation": "H(z) = 6 + z-1 - z-2, solve it by considering H(z) = 0 z = 1/3, -1/2 in H(z) only numerator.\n\nHence z = 1/3, - 1/2 will be zero, and if zero lies inside the unit circle, system will be of minimum phase."}, {"question": "The period of the function cos  is", "opta": "", "optb": "8s", "optc": "4s", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "Let x(t) and y(t) with F.T. x(f) and y(f) respectively be related as shown in figure Then y(f) is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "-X(f/2)ej2pf", "optd": "-X(f/2)e- j2pf", "ans": "B", "explanation": "By applying time shifting and scaling property."}, {"question": "Which one is a linear system?", "opta": "y[n] = x[n] x x[n - 1]", "optb": "y[n] = x[n] + x[n - 10]", "optc": "y[n] = x2[n]", "optd": "(a) and (c)", "ans": "B", "explanation": "For linearity\n\ny1[n] = x1[n] + x2[n - 10] ...(1)\n\ny2 = x2[n] + x2[n - 10] ...(2)\n\ny1[n] = x1[n] + x2[n] + x2[n - 10] + x2[n - 10] ...(3)\n\nNow find y1[n] + y2[n]\n\nCorresponding to x1[n] + x2[n] \n\nIt is same as equation (3) hence linear.\n\nBut in part (c) y[n] = x2[n]\n\n&Rightarrow; y1[n] = x21[n], y2[n] = x22[n]&Rightarrow; y1[n] + y2[n] = x22[n]...3\n\nBut y1[n] + y2[n]\n\nCorresponing x1[n] + x2[n] is y1[n] + y2[n] = {x1[n] + x2[n]}2\n\n= x12[n] + x22[n] + 2x1[n] x2[n]....4\n\nEquations (3) and (4) are not same hence not linear."}, {"question": "Laplace transform of a pulse function of magnitude E and duration from t = 0 to t = a is", "opta": "E /  s", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "The continuous time system with impulse response h(t) = is stable, for n is even, when", "opta": "a = 0", "optb": "a > 0", "optc": "a < 0", "optd": "a \u2264 0", "ans": "C", "explanation": "For stable system exponential must be -ve so that a < 0."}, {"question": "If I (s)  , initial value of i(t) is", "opta": "5A", "optb": "12.5 A", "optc": "0.05 A", "optd": "1250 A", "ans": "A", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "If then for this to be true x(t) is", "opta": "exp (j2p f/t)", "optb": "exp (-j2p f/t)", "optc": "exp (j2p ft)", "optd": "exp (-j2p f/t)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "If  \n\n\n\n\n\n."}, {"question": "For the discrete time system of the given figure", "opta": "yk - 0.5 yk - 1 - 0.25 yk - 2 = uk", "optb": "yk + 0.5 yk - 1 - 0.25 yk - 2 = uk", "optc": "yk - 0.5 yk - 1 + 0.25 yk - 2 = uk", "optd": "yk + 0.5 yk - 1 + 0.25 yk - 2 = uk", "ans": "C", "explanation": "uk + 0.5 yk - 1 - 0.25 yk - 2 = yk."}, {"question": "The analog signal m(t) is given below m(t) = 4 cos 100 pt + 8 sin 200 pt + cos 300 pt, the Nyquist sampling rate will be", "opta": "1/100", "optb": "1/200", "optc": "1/300", "optd": "1/600", "ans": "C", "explanation": "m (t) = 4 cos 100 pt + 8 sin 200 pt + cos 300 pt\n\nNyquist sampling freq fs \u2264 2fm where fm is highest frequency component in given signal and highest fm in 3rd part\n\n2pfmt = 300 pt\n\nfm = 150 Hz\n\nfs = 2 x 150 p 300 Hz\n\n."}, {"question": "The ROC of sequence in the Z.T. of sequence x[n] = an \u222a [n] is", "opta": "z > a", "optb": "z < a", "optc": "|z| > a", "optd": "|z| < a", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The simplest method to find the ROC. Put denominator to greater than zero."}, {"question": "In Laplace transform, multiplication by e-at in time domain becomes", "opta": "translation by a in s domain", "optb": "translation by (-a) in s domain", "optc": "multiplication by e-as in s domain", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "\u00a3e-at f(t) = F(s + a)."}, {"question": "A function having frequency f is to be sampled. The sampling time T should be", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Sampling frequency must be more than 2f. Therefore ."}, {"question": "The final value theorem is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "\u00a3f(t) = \n\n\u00a3-1F(s) = f(t)\n\n\u00a3[a f1(t) + bf2(t)] = aF1(s) + bF2(s)\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\nwhere \n\n\u00a3[f(t - T)] = e-sT F(s)\n\n\u00a3[e-at f(t)] = F(s + a)\n\nInitial value theorem \n\nFinal value theroem \n\nConvolution Integral \n\n\n\nwhere t is dummy variable for t."}, {"question": "If", "opta": "- 12", "optb": "12", "optc": "20", "optd": "- 20", "ans": "A", "explanation": "det.|A| = 3(8 - 12) = - 12."}, {"question": "Inverse Fourier transform of sgn (\u03c9) is", "opta": "", "optb": "1", "optc": "U(t)", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "By duality Property."}, {"question": "If I (s)  , the final value of i(t) is", "opta": "5A", "optb": "12.5 A", "optc": "0.05 A", "optd": "1250 A", "ans": "B", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "A signal m(t) is multiplied by a sinusoidal waveform of frequency fc such thatv(t)=m(t) cos 2pfctIf Fourier transform of m(t) is M(f), Fourier transform of v(t) will be", "opta": "0.5 M(f + fc)", "optb": "0.5 M(f - fc)", "optc": "0.5 M(f + fc) + 0.5 M(f - fc)", "optd": "0.5 M(f - fc) + 0.5 M(f - fc)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "It is a modulation process. The resultant has (f + fc) and (f - fc) terms."}, {"question": "A voltage wave having 5% fifth harmonic content is applied to a series RC circuit. The percentage fifth harmonic content in the current wave will be", "opta": "5%", "optb": "more than 5%", "optc": "less than 5%", "optd": "equal or more than 5%", "ans": "B", "explanation": "IC = V(j\u03c9C)."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  If , the initial value of i(t) is 5AReason (R): As per initial vaue theroem", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are correct but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true, R is false", "optd": "A is false, R is true", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Initial value theorem when applied to I(s) gives 5 A."}, {"question": "\u03b4(t) is a", "opta": "energy signal", "optb": "power signal", "optc": "neither energy nor power", "optd": "none", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Because Unit step is a Power signal. So By trignometric identifies d(t) also power.\n\n."}, {"question": "The analog signal given below is sampled by 600 samples per second for m(t) = 3 sin 500 pt + 2 sin 700 pt then folding frequency is", "opta": "500 Hz", "optb": "700 Hz", "optc": "300 Hz", "optd": "1400 Hz", "ans": "C", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "The signal defined by the equations f(t) = 0 for t < 0, f(t) = E for 0 \u2264 t \u2264 a and f(t) = 0 for t > a is", "opta": "a step function", "optb": "a pulse function", "optc": "a shifted step function originating at t = a", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "It is a pulse lasting for t = a."}, {"question": "Inverse Laplace transform of  is", "opta": "2 exp (- 2.5 t) cosh (0.5 t)", "optb": "exp (- 2 t) + exp (- 3 t)", "optc": "2 exp (- 2.5 t) sinh (0.5 t)", "optd": "2 exp (- 2.5 t) cos 0.5 t", "ans": "B", "explanation": "f(t) = e-2t + e-3t."}, {"question": "Two function g1(t) and g2(t) with correlation of 6 has average power of 4 and 5 respectively. The power of g1(t) + g2(t) is", "opta": "9", "optb": "21", "optc": "3", "optd": "15", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Power of two correlated signal is P = P1 + P2 +2R1, 2(t)."}, {"question": "A box has 4 white and 3 red balls. Two balls are taken out in succession. What is the probability that both are white?", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The probability that first ball is white is  and the probability the second ball is white is . The probability that both are white is ."}, {"question": "Z transform is a non-linear operation.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Z transform is a linear operation."}, {"question": "A signal g(t) = A then g(t) is a", "opta": "energy signal", "optb": "power signal", "optc": "neither energy nor power signal", "optd": "insufficient data", "ans": "B", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "The Fourier series of an odd periodic function contains", "opta": "odd harmonics only", "optb": "even harmonics only", "optc": "cosine harmonics only", "optd": "sine harmonics only", "ans": "D", "explanation": "For an odd function f(- x) = - f(x) Hence, only sine terms."}, {"question": "If , the terms in f(t) will have", "opta": "e-t and e-2t", "optb": "et and e2t", "optc": "te-t and te-2t", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "(s + 1) term will give e-t  and (s + 2) term will give e-2t ."}, {"question": "An impulse function consist of", "opta": "pure dc", "optb": "pure a.c", "optc": "entire frequency range with constant phase", "optd": "infinite bandwidth with linear phase vaariations", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Because F.T. of \u03b4(t) = 1, 1 is a Constant function ranging from -\u221e to +\u221e."}, {"question": "As per time displacement theorem in Laplace transformation, displacement in the time domain by T becomes", "opta": "division by s in the s domain", "optb": "division by e-sT in the s domain", "optc": "multiplication by s in the s domain", "optd": "multiplication by e-sT in the s domain", "ans": "D", "explanation": "\u00a3f(t - T) = e-st F(s)."}, {"question": "Which one is a causal system?", "opta": "y(n) = 3x[n] - 2x[n - 1]", "optb": "y(n) = 3x[n] + 2x[n + 1]", "optc": "y(n) = 3x[n + 1] + 2x[n - 1]", "optd": "y(n) = 3x[n + 1] 2x[n - 1] + x[n]", "ans": "A", "explanation": "For causal output must depend upon Present and past not on future."}, {"question": "If , the coefficient of term e-t in f(t) will be", "opta": "1", "optb": "0", "optc": "0.5", "optd": "2/3", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Coefficient of e-t = ."}, {"question": "Double integration of a unit step function would lead to", "opta": "an impulse", "optb": "a parabola", "optc": "a ramp", "optd": "a doublet", "ans": "B", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "If f(t) = A d(t - a), F(s) is", "opta": "A e-as", "optb": "A eas", "optc": "A a e-as", "optd": "Aa eas", "ans": "A", "explanation": "It is an impulse having area A and originating at t = a."}, {"question": "If  is the Laplace transform of f(t) then f(0+) is", "opta": "0", "optb": "", "optc": "27", "optd": "\u221e", "ans": "C", "explanation": "."}]]}